<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<manuscript xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" manuscript-id="04" name="" title="MCC_Chapter_04_DJHrev" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/digfir_manuscript.xsd">
<chapter number="4" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-chapter-4" title="4: Understanding Culture" start-numbering-at="4" numbered="true">
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="86">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_86" block_type="page_start">86</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p1" block_type="chapter_number">4</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p2" block_type="chapter_title">Understanding Culture</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p3" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">H</phrase>elen Torres was born in Puerto Rico but spent her early childhood in a diverse Detroit neighborhood of Polish, Hispanic, Lebanese, and Euro-American families. The summer before she entered third grade, her family moved. Now in a suburb populated mostly by white families, the Torreses were the only Hispanic family in the area.<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p4"><sup>1</sup></link> Excited about the change, Helen&#8217;s mother immediately volunteered to help out with activities at Helen&#8217;s new school, including fund-raising and school parties.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p4" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p3"><sup>1</sup></link>All information that follows was provided to the authors by Helen Torres in a personal interview, December 5, 2012. Published with the permission of Helen Torres.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p5" block_type="co-txt">Soon an incident occurred that changed Helen&#8217;s view of communication and culture forever. A parent called Helen&#8217;s mother and asked her to bake cupcakes for an upcoming school event. Helen&#8217;s mother, a bilingual but dominantly Spanish speaker, didn&#8217;t know what &#8220;cupcakes&#8221; were. Why would anyone want a <em>cup</em>-sized cake? Concluding that the caller must be confused, Helen&#8217;s mom baked a beautiful full-sized cake and brought it to school. Seeing the cake, the other kids teased Helen. &#8220;I shut them up,&#8221; Helen explains. &#8220;I said, &#8216;My mom can speak two languages. <em>Can yours?</em>&#8217;&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p6" block_type="co-txt">The cupcake incident quickly faded from Helen&#8217;s classmates&#8217; memories, but for Helen&#8217;s mother it fostered a sense of insurmountable difference between her and the other mothers. She stopped volunteering for school functions, afraid of embarrassing her daughters. For Helen, the misunderstanding inspired an intense curiosity about communication and cultural difference. This curiosity would eventually lead her to earn a master&#8217;s degree in communication and to become a national activist on behalf of Hispanic civil rights.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p7" block_type="co-txt">Years later, Helen hosted a roundtable for a federal agency looking to expand its reach and service to underrepresented communities. One participant was a woman who ran a nonprofit organization helping victims of eastern European war crimes establish themselves in the United States. The woman spoke slowly and nervously, with a thick accent. Helen immediately sensed that the other group members were getting irritated with how long the woman was taking to express herself. As Helen describes, &#8220;I kept imagining my mother and the cupcake. So I told the other group members to be patient with her and allow her extra time to speak. She had great ideas, and the fact that she was willing to share these with us meant that we should support her.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_87" block_type="page_start">87</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-1" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-1" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Courtesy of Helen Torres</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_88" block_type="page_start">88</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p8" block_type="co-h"><strong>CHAPTER OUTLINE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p9" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-1"><strong>What Is Culture?</strong> 88</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p10" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-2"><strong>Cultural Influences on Communication</strong> 96</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p11" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-3"><strong>Creating Intercultural Competence</strong> 106</link></p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p12" block_type="txt">Today, Helen Torres is executive director and CEO of Hispanas Organized for Political Equality (HOPE), an influential nonprofit committed to achieving political and economic equality for Latinas through leadership, advocacy, and education. But she still recalls the cupcake incident and its impact on her life. &#8220;Some may think it&#8217;s a silly story, but it illustrates a profound point: communicating competently with people from other cultural communities is an essential skill. We must be able to bridge cultural divides through our communication to ensure that all people have their voices heard, understood, respected, and valued, and that no one feels the sense of alienation that my mother once did.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p13" block_type="txt">Have you been in situations in which, like Helen&#8217;s mother, you felt distant from others because of cultural differences? How did you bridge such divides? One way to approach such situations is through your communication. By understanding cultural influences and improving your ability to communicate competently with people from other cultures, you can build more positive and mutually satisfying connections with them. In this chapter, you&#8217;ll learn:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p14" block_type="bl-f">The defining characteristics of culture</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p15" block_type="bl-m">What co-cultures are, and their role in communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p16" block_type="bl-m">The impact of ingroups, outgroups, and prejudice on communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p17" block_type="bl-m">The ways that cultural differences influence how people communicate</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p18" block_type="bl-l">How to improve your intercultural communication competence</p></li>
</list>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p19" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-2" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e"><strong>macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</strong></link>.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-1" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="88">
<section-metadata><section-title>What Is Culture?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p20" block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>Whether you realize it or not, your culture affects your communication all the time. More than just your race or ethnicity, cultural traits like age, physical abilities, social class, and even your values and beliefs influence how you view yourself as well as how you perceive others.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p21" block_type="txt-ni">In the United States, cultural diversity is rapidly increasing. By 2020, for example, more than half the nation&#8217;s children (people under age 18) will be nonwhite&#8212;including Latino, Asian, African American, and mixed-raced children (U.S. Census Bureau, 2015). International student enrollments in the country are also on the rise (Institute of International Education, 2014), so your classmates are just as likely to be from Seoul as Seattle. Plus, with all the smartphones, tablets, and laptops available, there is easy access to people all over the world. This enables you to conduct business and personal relationships on a global level in a way never possible before. As your daily encounters increasingly cross cultural lines, the question arises: What exactly <em>is</em> culture?</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-1" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="88">
<section-metadata><section-title>Culture Defined</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p22" block_type="txt-ni">In this book, we take a broad and inclusive view of <termref term="culture">culture</termref>, defining it as an established, coherent set of beliefs, attitudes, values, and practices shared by a large group of people (Keesing, 1974). Culture includes many types of influences, such as your nationality, ethnicity, religion, gender, sexual orientation, physical abilities, and age. But what really makes a culture a &#8220;culture&#8221; is that it&#8217;s widely shared. This happens because cultures are learned, communicated, layered, and lived.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_89" block_type="page_start">89</p>
<box title="WHAT IS YOUR CULTURE?" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx1-1" block_type="bx1-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p23" block_type="bx1-txt"><strong>Culture is so integrated into your everyday life that it is easy to overlook how it can inform everything you see, hear, or believe. How do the activities and images shown relate to your culture or not? What other aspects of your culture make you <em>you</em>?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-2" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-3" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Asia Images Group/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-3" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-4" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P03.jpg"/>
<asset_source>NARINDER NANU/AFP/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-4" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-5" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P04.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Hero Images/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-5" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-6" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P05.jpg"/>
<asset_source>susafri/iStock/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-6" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-7" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P06.jpg"/>
<asset_source>susafri/iStock/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-7" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-8" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P07.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Mario Tama/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_90" block_type="page_start">90</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p24" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Culture Is Learned.</strong></phrase> You learn your cultural beliefs, attitudes, and values from many sources, including your parents, teachers, religious leaders, peers, and the mass media (Gudykunst &#38; Kim, 2003). This process begins at birth, through customs such as choosing a newborn&#8217;s name, taking part in religious ceremonies, and selecting godparents or other special guardians. As you mature, you learn deeper aspects of your culture, including the history behind certain traditions&#8212;for example, why unleavened bread is eaten during the Jewish Passover or why certain days of the year are more important than others. You also learn how to participate in rituals&#8212;everything from blowing out the candles on a birthday cake to carving pumpkins on Halloween. In most societies, teaching children to understand, respect, and practice their culture is considered an essential part of child rearing.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p25" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Culture Is Communicated.</strong></phrase> Each culture has its own practices regarding how to communicate (Whorf, 1952). Imagine you&#8217;re part of a group project and the other members decide to do the assignment in a particular way. If you grew up in Singapore, where your culture would emphasize group harmony over personal preferences, you&#8217;d be expected to support the group&#8217;s decision, even if you thought another approach would be better. Withholding your dissenting opinion would be considered competent communication. American culture, however, stresses the importance of individual expression. So if you grew up in the United States, you&#8217;d probably feel that it&#8217;s perfectly acceptable&#8212;and perhaps even your duty&#8212;to voice your concerns about the group&#8217;s decision.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p26" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Culture Is Layered.</strong></phrase> Many people belong to more than one culture simultaneously. This means they experience multiple layers of culture, as various traditions, heritages, and practices are recognized and held to be important. Steve&#8217;s Uncle Rick, for example, is originally from Canada but is now an American citizen. Rick is passionate about being an American: he played hockey for a U.S. collegiate team, is deeply patriotic, sings the national anthem at ball games, and celebrates the Fourth of July. But every four years, when the Winter Olympics roll around, his Canadian cultural allegiance emerges from beneath the American layer, and he cheers on the Canadians over and above everyone else&#8212;especially when it comes to hockey!</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p27" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Culture Is Lived.</strong></phrase> Culture affects everything about how you live your life. It influences the neighborhoods you live in; the means of transportation you use; the way you think, dress, talk, and even eat. Its impact runs so deep that it is often taken for granted. At the same time, culture is often a great source of personal pride. Many people consciously live in ways that celebrate their cultural heritage&#8212;through such behaviors as wearing a Muslim hijab, placing a Mexican flag decal on their car, or greeting others with the Thai gesture of the <em>wai</em> (hands joined in prayer, heads bowed).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_91" block_type="page_start">91</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx4-1" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-8" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="4.1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 4.1</strong></phrase> <strong>CULTURAL INFLUENCES</strong></caption>
<caption>Many factors combine to form your culture. Here is a sample of some influences, but what other aspects do you consider part of your culture? are some aspects more important than others?</caption>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-9" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_04_F01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>acequestions/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-2" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="91">
<section-metadata><section-title>Co-cultures</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p28" block_type="txt-ni">As societies become more culturally diverse, there is an increased awareness of how various cultures&#8212;and groups of people within them&#8212;interact. In any society, there&#8217;s usually a group of people who have more <termref term="power">power</termref> than everyone else&#8212;that is, the ability to influence or control people and events (Donohue &#38; Kolt, 1992). Having more power in a society comes from controlling major societal institutions, such as banks, businesses, the government, and legal and educational systems. According to <termref term="co-cultural communication theory">co-cultural communication theory</termref>, the people who have more power within a society determine the <em>dominant culture</em> because they get to decide the prevailing views, values, and traditions of the society (Orbe, 1998). Consider the United States. Throughout its history, wealthy Euro-American men have been in power. When the country was first founded, the only people allowed to vote were landowning males of European ancestry. Now, more than 200 years later, Euro-American men still make up the vast majority of the U.S. Congress and Fortune 500 CEOs. As a consequence, what is thought of as &#8220;American culture&#8221; is tilted toward emphasizing the interests, activities, and accomplishments of these men.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_92" block_type="page_start">92</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p29" block_type="txt">Members of a society who don&#8217;t conform to the dominant culture&#8212;by way of language, values, lifestyle, or physical appearance&#8212;often form what are called <termref term="co-cultures">co-cultures</termref>; that is, they have their own cultures that <em>coexist</em> within a dominant cultural sphere (Orbe, 1998). Co-cultures may be based on age, gender, social class, ethnicity, religion, mental and physical ability, sexual orientation, and other unifying elements, depending on the society (Orbe, 1998). U.S. residents who are not members of the dominant culture&#8212;people of color, women, members of the LGBTQ community, transgender persons, and so forth&#8212;exist as distinct co-cultures, with their own political lobbying groups, Web sites, magazines, and television networks (such as Lifetime, BET, Telemundo, and Here TV).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p30" block_type="txt">Because members of co-cultures are (by definition) different from the dominant culture, they develop and use numerous communication practices that help them interact with people in the culturally dominant group (Ramirez-Sanchez, 2008). There are three types of approaches, depending on whether the co-cultural members wish to <em>assimilate</em> (be accepted) into the dominant culture, get the dominant culture to <em>accommodate</em> their co-cultural identity, or <em>separate</em> themselves from the dominant culture altogether. For example, they might do some of the following:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-2" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p31" block_type="bl-f">Use overly polite language with individuals from the dominant culture (assimilation)</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p32" block_type="bl-m">Suppress reactions when members of the dominant culture make offensive comments (assimilation)</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p33" block_type="bl-m">Try to excel in all aspects of their professional and personal lives to counteract negative stereotypes about their co-culture (accommodation)</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p34" block_type="bl-m">Act, look, and talk as much as possible like members of the dominant culture (assimilation)</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p35" block_type="bl-m">Openly disparage their own co-culture (assimilation)</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p36" block_type="bl-m">Quietly but clearly express their co-cultural identity through appearance, actions, and words (accommodation)</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p37" block_type="bl-l">Conform to negative stereotypes in an exaggerated way to shock and scare members from the dominant culture (separation)</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p38" block_type="txt">How might these communication practices work in real life? Think back to our chapter opener and the story of Helen Torres, her mother, and the cake. When Helen&#8217;s family moved to a nearly all-white suburb, her mother immediately tried to assimilate by volunteering at the school and trying to act like all the other mothers. But because she didn&#8217;t know what a &#8220;cupcake&#8221; was, her attempt at assimilation failed, and she withdrew, separating herself from the dominant culture. Helen, on the other hand, never tried to assimilate. Instead, this feisty third-grader dressed in accordance with her family&#8217;s Hispanic customs; spoke Spanish when she felt like it; and, when the other kids teased her about her mother&#8217;s cake, flew to her mother&#8217;s defense by saying, &#8220;My mom can speak two languages. <em>Can yours?</em>&#8221; Without knowing it, Helen was trying to get the dominant white culture to accommodate her family&#8217;s Hispanic co-cultural identity.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_93" block_type="page_start">93</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-3" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="93">
<section-metadata><section-title>Ingroups and Outgroups</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p39" block_type="txt-ni">Culture has an enormous and powerful effect on your perceptions. When you grow up with certain cultural or co-cultural beliefs, attitudes, and values, you naturally perceive those who share these with you as <termref term="ingroupers">ingroupers</termref>&#8212;people you consider as similar to yourself (Allport, 1954). Individuals from many different social groups can be ingroupers if they share important cultural commonalities with you, such as nationality, religious beliefs, ethnicity, age, socioeconomic class, or political views (Turner, Hogg, Oakes, Reicher, &#38; Wetherell, 1987). In contrast, you may view people who aren&#8217;t culturally similar to yourself as <termref term="outgroupers">outgroupers</termref>.</p>
<box title="DOUBLE TAKE" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx3-1" block_type="bx3-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p40" block_type="bx3-t-c1"><strong>INGROUPS</strong> <image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-10" alt="image" src="images/or.jpg"/> <strong>OUTGROUPS</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p41" block_type="bx3-txt"><strong>Would you classify the people and activities shown below as ingroupers or outgroupers? What specific aspects in each image make someone seem similar or dissimilar to you? How does this classification influence your communication?</strong></p>
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-tab-1" numbered="false" number="false" block_type="">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-9" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-11" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P08.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Bob Sacha/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-12" alt="image" src="images/or1.jpg"/></td>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-10" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-13" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P09.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Kevin R. Morris/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_94" block_type="page_start">94</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p42" block_type="txt">People often feel passionately connected to their ingroups, especially when they reflect central aspects of their self-concept, such as sexual orientation, gender identity, religious beliefs, or ethnic heritage. This feeling of connection means you&#8217;re more likely to give your money, time, and help to ingroupers than to outgroupers (Castelli, Tomelleri, &#38; Zogmaister, 2008). For example, if two volunteers show up at your door asking you to donate money and time to a fund-raising effort, which one are you more likely to support: the volunteer working for a group you feel connected to, or the volunteer representing a group you feel no link to? Many people would pick the ingrouper.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p43" block_type="txt">You&#8217;re also more likely to form positive impressions of people you perceive as ingroupers (Giannakakis &#38; Fritsche, 2011). For instance, in one study of 30 ethnic groups in East Africa, members of each group perceived ingroupers&#8217; communication as more trustworthy, friendly, and honest than outgroupers&#8217; communication (Brewer &#38; Campbell, 1976). When people communicate in rude or inappropriate ways, you&#8217;re more inclined to form negative impressions of them if you see them as outgroupers (Brewer, 1999). If a customer at your job snaps at you but is wearing a T-shirt that advocates your cultural beliefs and values, you&#8217;re likely to make the attribution, &#8220;He&#8217;s just having a bad day.&#8221; The same communication coming from someone wearing a shirt attacking your cultural beliefs will likely provoke a negative, internal attribution: &#8220;What a jerk!&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p44" block_type="txt">One of the strongest determinants of ingroup and outgroup perceptions is race. <termref term="Race">Race</termref> classifies people based on common ancestry or descent and is judged almost exclusively by a person&#8217;s physical features (Lustig &#38; Koester, 2006). Perceiving someone&#8217;s race almost always means assigning him or her to ingrouper or outgrouper status (Brewer, 1999) and communicating with that person based on that status.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p45" block_type="txt">When categorizing other people as ingroupers or outgroupers, it&#8217;s easy to make mistakes. Even if a person seems to be the same race as you (e.g., white), she may have a very different ethnic, religious, and cultural heritage (you&#8217;re Irish Catholic; she&#8217;s Russian Jewish). Likewise, even if someone dresses differently than you do, he might hold cultural beliefs, attitudes, and values that are very similar to your own. If you assume that people are ingroupers or outgroupers based on surface-level differences, you may mistakenly perceive that you don&#8217;t share anything in common. As a consequence, you might never discover that you do share important qualities and thus could miss out on an opportunity to make a new friend, work productively with a colleague, or form a romantic bond.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-4" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="94">
<section-metadata><section-title>Prejudice</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p46" block_type="txt-ni">As the section on forming impressions in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link> explains (pp. 51&#8211;52), <em>stereotypes</em> are a way to categorize people into a social group and then evaluate them based on information you have related to this group. Stereotypes play a big part in how you form impressions about others during the perception process. This is especially true for racial and gender characteristics, since they are among the things you notice first when encountering others. But when stereotypes reflect rigid attitudes toward groups and their members, they become <termref term="prejudice">prejudice</termref> (Ramasubramanian, 2010).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_95" block_type="page_start">95</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx5-1" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p47" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>The story of how six-year-old Peyton Messenger learned to skateboard shows how it is possible to have meaningful experiences with someone we perceive as an outgrouper. In October 2015, Peyton&#8217;s mother, Jeanean, took Peyton to a skate park so she could learn to skateboard, but when they arrived they found a group of teenage boys there. Intimidated, Peyton wanted to go home, but one of the boys approached Peyton and spent over an hour teaching her to skateboard&#8212;despite being teased by his friends. Jeanean posted this photo on Twitter that day with an accompanying note to the boy (later identified as twenty-year-old Ryan Carney), thanking him for the confidence he gave Peyton. The photo and note quickly went viral.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-11" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-14" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P10.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Jeanean Thomas</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p48" block_type="txt">Because prejudice is rooted in stereotypes, it can vary depending on whether those stereotypes are positive or negative. According to the <termref term="Stereotype Content Model">Stereotype Content Model</termref> (Fiske, Cuddy, Glick, &#38; Xu, 2002), prejudice centers on two judgments made about others: how warm and friendly they are, and how competent they are. These judgments create two possible kinds of prejudice: <em>benevolent</em> and <em>hostile</em>.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p49" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Benevolent Prejudice.</strong></phrase> <em>Benevolent prejudice</em> occurs when people think of a particular group as inferior but also friendly and competent. For instance, someone judges a group as &#8220;primitive,&#8221; &#8220;helpless,&#8221; and &#8220;ignorant&#8221; but attributes their &#8220;inferiority&#8221; to forces beyond their control, such as lack of education, technology, or wealth (Ramasubramanian, 2010). Thus, although the group is thought of negatively, it also triggers feelings of sympathy (Fiske et al., 2002). People engaging in benevolent prejudice might think that members of a group of people are &#8220;inferior&#8221; but could improve themselves &#8220;if only they knew better.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_96" block_type="page_start">96</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p50" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Hostile Prejudice.</strong></phrase> <em>Hostile prejudice</em> happens when people have negative attitudes toward a group of individuals whom they see as unfriendly and incompetent (Fiske et al., 2002). Someone demonstrating hostile prejudice might see the group&#8217;s supposed incompetence as intrinsic to the people: &#8220;They&#8217;re naturally lazy,&#8221; &#8220;They&#8217;re all crazy zealots,&#8221; or &#8220;They&#8217;re mean and violent.&#8221; People exhibiting hostile prejudice often also believe that the group has received many opportunities to improve (&#8220;They&#8217;ve been given so much&#8221;) but that their innate limitations hold them back (&#8220;They&#8217;ve done nothing but waste every break that&#8217;s been given to them&#8221;).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p51" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Overcoming Prejudice.</strong></phrase> Prejudice, no matter what form, is destructive and unethical. Benevolent prejudice leads to condescending and disrespectful communication. Hostile prejudice is the root of every exclusionary &#8220;ism&#8221;: racism, sexism, ageism, classism, ableism, and so on.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p52" block_type="txt">The root of prejudice is deeply held negative beliefs about particular groups (Ramasubramanian, 2010). If you think you have prejudiced beliefs, your communication skills can help you confront them and permanently give them up. Use the perception-checking and empathy guidelines discussed in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link> (pp. 53&#8211;57) to help you evaluate and change your own beliefs. Also, learn about the cultures and groups you have prejudiced beliefs about. During interactions, ask members of these groups questions about themselves, and listen actively to the answers. This will ease the uncertainty and anxiety you may feel around others who are culturally different from you (Berger &#38; Calabrese, 1975). Finally, be open to new people and experiences; this can result in quality relationships that break down prejudicial barriers.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p53" block_type="txt">On the other hand, if you&#8217;ve been on the receiving end of prejudice, try not to generalize your experience with that one person (or persons) to all members of the same group. Just because someone of a certain age, gender, ethnicity, or cultural group behaves badly doesn&#8217;t mean that <em>all</em> members of that group do. One of the bitter ironies of prejudice is that it often triggers a reaction of prejudice in the people who have been unfairly treated. This is not to excuse the prejudice or poor communication of others but to help you avoid adding to the vicious cycle of prejudicial communication.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-2" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="96">
<section-metadata><section-title>Cultural Influences on Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p54" block_type="pul"><strong>Your cultural background differs from that of other people in many ways. One way those differences are expressed is through your communication&#8212;such as how you deal with power structures, share emotions, and even view time. Understanding and adapting to such factors will help you communicate more competently.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p55" block_type="txt-ni">The TV show <em>Modern Family</em> has remained a hit since 2009 because of the way it reveals the California clan&#8217;s diverse cultural backgrounds. Euro-American patriarch Jay is married to the (much younger) Gloria, who is originally from Colombia. Jay is stepfather to Gloria&#8217;s son, Manny, and together he and Gloria have a child, Joe. Jay&#8217;s children from a previous marriage also have families of their own. His son, Mitchell, and Mitchell&#8217;s husband, Cam, have an adopted daughter from Vietnam, while Jay&#8217;s daughter, Claire, and her goofy husband, Phil, have three children. Given this diversity, interactions between the characters routinely cross lines of age, gender, ethnicity, and sexual orientation&#8212;often at the same time. Not surprisingly, there&#8217;s a lot of miscommunication stemming from these differences. For example, Gloria speaks with a Colombian accent and often tangles up her English words. On Halloween, she tells Jay he&#8217;s &#8220;going to be a gargle.&#8221; Manny chimes in to clarify, &#8220;She means &#8216;gargoyle.&#8217;&#8221; Later, when a box of Jesus figurines is mysteriously delivered to their house, Jay realizes the error: he had told Gloria to call his secretary and order a box of baby <em>cheeses</em>.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_97" block_type="page_start">97</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx5-2" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p56" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Gloria Delgado-Pritchett, played by Sofia Vergara, is a Colombian woman whose cultural norms often conflict with those of her American-born family members. How do you navigate situations in which culture blurs the line of understanding between yourself and others?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-12" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-15" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P11.jpg"/>
<asset_source>The Kobal Collection at Art Resource, Inc.</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p57" block_type="txt">Shows like <em>Modern Family</em> poke lighthearted fun at cultural differences. However, the real-world communication distinctions between cultures can be profound. Scholars suggest that six cultural characteristics shape our communication: individualism versus collectivism, high and low context, uncertainty avoidance, emotion displays, power distance, and views of time.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-5" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="97">
<section-metadata><section-title>Individualism versus Collectivism</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p58" block_type="txt-ni">In an <termref term="individualistic culture">individualistic culture</termref>, people tend to value independence and personal achievement. Members of these cultures are encouraged to focus on themselves and their immediate family (Hofstede, 2001), and individual achievement is praised as the highest good (Waterman, 1984). Individualistic countries include the United States, Canada, New Zealand, and Sweden (Hofstede, 2001).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_98" block_type="page_start">98</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx5-3" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p59" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>The emergence of social media platforms like Snapchat and Instagram contributed to the popular trend of documenting everyday moments of life through photos. How does this exemplify the individualistic culture that exists in American society?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-13" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-16" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P12.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Pressmaster/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p60" block_type="txt">By contrast, in a <termref term="collectivistic culture">collectivistic culture</termref> people emphasize group identity (&#8216;we&#8217; rather than &#8216;me&#8217;), interpersonal harmony, and the well-being of ingroups (Park &#38; Guan, 2006). If you were raised in a collectivistic culture, you were probably taught that it&#8217;s important to belong to groups, or &#8220;collectives,&#8221; that look after you in exchange for your loyalty. In collectivistic cultures, people emphasize the goals, needs, and views of groups over those of individuals, and define the highest good as cooperation with others rather than individual achievement. Collectivistic countries include Guatemala, Pakistan, Taiwan, and Japan (Hofstede, 2001).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p61" block_type="txt">Differences between individualistic and collectivistic cultures can powerfully influence people&#8217;s behaviors&#8212;including which social networking sites they use and how they use them. For instance, people in collectivistic cultures tend to use sites that emphasize group connectedness, whereas those in individualistic cultures gravitate to sites that focus on self-expression (Barker &#38; Ota, 2011). American Facebook users devote most of their time on the site describing their own actions and viewpoints as well as events that are personally important to them. They also post controversial status updates and express their personal opinions&#8212;even if these trigger debate. Meanwhile, Japanese users of Mixi carefully edit their profiles so that they won&#8217;t offend anyone (Barker &#38; Ota, 2011). Mixi users tend to write in diaries that are shared with their closest friends, boosting ingroup solidarity, whereas American Facebook users often post photos of themselves alone doing various activities (Barker &#38; Ota, 2011).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_99" block_type="page_start">99</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-6" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="99">
<section-metadata><section-title>High and Low Context</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p62" block_type="txt-ni">Cultures can also be described as <em>high</em> or <em>low context.</em> In <termref term="high-context cultures">high-context cultures</termref>, such as China, Korea, and Japan, people use relatively vague and ambiguous language and even silence to convey important meanings. (High-context cultures are often collectivistic as well.) People in such cultures often talk indirectly (using hints or suggestions) because they presume that members of their ingroup will know what they&#8217;re trying to say. As a result, they don&#8217;t feel the need to provide a lot of explicit information.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p63" block_type="txt">In <termref term="low-context cultures">low-context cultures</termref>, people tend <em>not</em> to presume that others share their beliefs, attitudes, and values. Thus, they strive to be informative, clear, and direct in their communication (E. T. Hall &#38; Hall, 1987). Many low-context cultures are also individualistic; as a result, people openly express their views and try to persuade others to accept them (E. T. Hall, 1976, 1997a). Within such cultures, which include Germany, Scandinavia, Canada, and the United States, people work to make important information obvious, rather than hinting or implying.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p64" block_type="txt">How does the difference between high-context and low-context cultures play out in real interactions? Consider the experiences of Steve&#8217;s friend Naomi Kagawa, a Japanese communication professor. Growing up in Japan&#8212;a high-context culture&#8212;Naomi learned to reject requests by using words equivalent to <em>OK</em> or <em>sure</em>. The Japanese reject requests this way because it maintains the harmony of the encounter. These words, however, are accompanied by subtle vocal tones that <em>imply</em> no. Because all members of the culture know this practice, they recognize that such seeming assents are actually rejections. In contrast, in the United States&#8212;a low-context culture&#8212;people often come right out and say no, then apologize and explain why they can&#8217;t grant the request. When Naomi first visited the United States, this difference caused misunderstandings in her interactions. She rejected unwanted requests by saying, &#8220;OK,&#8221; only to find that people presumed she was consenting rather than refusing. And she was surprised, even shocked, when people rejected her requests by explicitly saying no.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-7" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="99">
<section-metadata><section-title>Uncertainty Avoidance</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p65" block_type="txt-ni">Cultures vary in how much they tolerate and accept unpredictability, known as <termref term="uncertainty avoidance">uncertainty avoidance</termref>. As scholar Geert Hofstede explains, &#8220;The fundamental issue here is how a society deals with the fact that the future can never be known: Should we try to control the future or just let it happen?&#8221; (Hofstede, 2009a). In <em>high-uncertainty-avoidance cultures</em> (such as Mexico, South Korea, Japan, and Greece), people place a lot of value on control. They define rigid rules and conventions to guide all beliefs and behaviors, and they feel uncomfortable with unusual or innovative ideas. People from such cultures want structure in their organizations, institutions, relationships, and everyday lives (Hofstede, 2001). For example, a coworker raised in a high-uncertainty-avoidance culture would expect everyone assigned to a project to have clear roles and responsibilities, including a designated leader. In his research on organizations, Hofstede found that in high-uncertainty-avoidance cultures, people commit to organizations for long periods of time, expect their job responsibilities to be clearly defined, and strongly believe that organizational rules should not be broken (2001, p. 149). Children raised in such cultures are taught to believe in cultural traditions and practices without ever questioning them.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_100" block_type="page_start">100</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p66" block_type="txt">In <em>low-uncertainty-avoidance cultures</em> (such as Jamaica, Denmark, Sweden, and Ireland), people put more emphasis on &#8220;letting the future happen&#8221; without trying to control it (Hofstede, 2001). They care less about rules, tolerate diverse viewpoints and beliefs, and welcome innovation and change. They also feel free to question and challenge authority. In addition, they teach their children to think critically about the beliefs and traditions they&#8217;re exposed to rather than automatically follow them. There is, however, some middle ground. Both the United States and Canada are considered moderately uncertainty avoidant.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-8" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="100">
<section-metadata><section-title>Emotion Displays</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p67" block_type="txt-ni">In all cultures, norms exist regarding how people should and shouldn&#8217;t express emotion. These norms are called <termref term="display rules">display rules</termref>: guidelines for when, where, and how to manage emotion displays appropriately (Ekman &#38; Friesen, 1975). Display rules govern very specific aspects of your <em>nonverbal communication</em>, such as how broadly you should smile, whether or not you should scowl when angry, and the appropriateness of shouting in public when you&#8217;re excited. (For more on nonverbal communication displays, see <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch06.xml">Chapter 6</link>, pp. 142&#8211;152.) Children learn such display rules and, over time, internalize them to the point where following these rules seems &#8220;normal.&#8221; This is why you likely think of the way you express emotion as natural, rather than as something that has been socialized into you through your culture (Hayes &#38; Metts, 2008).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p68" block_type="txt">Because of differences in socialization and traditions, display rules vary across cultures (Soto, Levenson, &#38; Ebling, 2005). Take the two fastest-growing ethnic groups in the United States&#8212;Mexican Americans and Chinese Americans (Buriel &#38; De Ment, 1997). In traditional Chinese culture, people prioritize emotional control and moderation; intense emotions are considered dangerous and are even thought to cause illness (Wu &#38; Tseng, 1985). This belief even shapes communication in close relationships. Chinese American couples don&#8217;t openly express positive emotions toward each other as often as Euro-American couples do (Tsai &#38; Levenson, 1997). On the other side of the spectrum, in traditional Mexican culture, people openly express emotion, even more so than those in Euro-American culture (Soto et al., 2005). For people of Mexican descent, the experience, expression, and deep discussion of emotions provide some of life&#8217;s greatest rewards and satisfactions.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_101" block_type="page_start">101</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p69" block_type="txt">When families immigrate to a new society, the move often provokes tension over which display rules they should follow. People more closely oriented to their cultures of origin continue to communicate their emotions in traditional ways. Others&#8212;usually the first generation of children born in the new society&#8212;may move away from traditional forms of emotional expression (Soto et al., 2005). For example, Chinese Americans who adhere strongly to traditional Chinese culture openly display fewer negative emotions than do those who are Americanized (Soto et al., 2005). Similarly, Mexican Americans with strong ties to traditional Mexican culture express intense negative emotions more openly than their Americanized counterparts.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p70" block_type="txt">It&#8217;s important to be aware of these differences when communicating with others. An emotional expression&#8212;such as a loud shout of intense joy&#8212;might be considered shocking and inappropriate in some cultures but perfectly normal and natural in others. At the same time, don&#8217;t presume that all people from the same culture necessarily share the same expectations. As much as possible, adjust your expressions of emotion to match the style of the individuals with whom you&#8217;re interacting.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx5-4" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p71" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Comedy writers often play with display rules, purposely enlarging the characters&#8217; reactions or going against the norm to create humor. The outlandish expressions and antics from Amy Schumer and Bill Hader in <em>Trainwreck</em> are an example. When it comes to display rules, where is the line between funny and wrong?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-14" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-17" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P13.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Universal Pictures/Photofest</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_102" block_type="page_start">102</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-9" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="102">
<section-metadata><section-title>Power Distance</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p72" block_type="txt-ni">The degree to which people in a particular culture view the unequal distribution of power as acceptable is known as <termref term="power distance">power distance</termref> (Hofstede, 1991, 2001). In <em>high-power-distance cultures</em>, it&#8217;s considered normal and even desirable for people of different social and professional status to have different levels of power (Ting-Toomey, 2005). In such cultures, people give privileged treatment and extreme respect to those in high-status positions (Ting-Toomey, 1999). They also expect individuals of lesser status to behave humbly, especially around people of higher status, who are expected to act superior.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p73" block_type="txt">In <em>low-power-distance cultures</em>, people in high-status positions try to minimize the differences between themselves and lower-status persons by interacting with them in informal ways and treating them as equals (Oetzel et al., 2001). For instance, a high-level marketing executive might chat with the cleaning service workers in her office and invite them to join her for a coffee break. See <link href="#choicesconnections2e_ch4-fig-15">Figure 4.2</link> for examples of high- and low-power-distance cultures.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx4-2" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-15" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="4.2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 4.2</strong></phrase> <strong>POWER DISTANCE ACROSS COUNTRIES</strong></caption>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-18" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_04_F02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Data from: Hofstede (2009)</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p74" block_type="txt">Power distance affects how people deal with conflict. In low-power-distance cultures, people with little power may choose to engage in conflict with high-power people. What&#8217;s more, they may do so <em>competitively</em>: confronting high-power people and demanding that their goals be met. For instance, employees may question management decisions and suggest that alternatives be considered, or townspeople may attend a meeting and demand that the mayor address their concerns. These behaviors are much less common in high-power-distance cultures (Bochner &#38; Hesketh, 1994), where low-power people are more likely to either <em>avoid</em> conflict with high-power people or <em>accommodate</em> them by giving in to their desires. <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch08.xml">Chapter 8</link> discusses more ways people approach conflict and how power affects those choices.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p75" block_type="txt">Power distance also influences how people communicate in close relationships, especially families. In traditional Mexican culture, for instance, the value of <em>respeto</em> (respect) emphasizes power distance between younger people and their elders (Delgado-Gaitan, 1993). As part of <em>respeto</em>, children are expected to defer to elders&#8217; authority and to avoid openly disagreeing with them. In contrast, many Euro-Americans believe that once children reach adulthood, power in family relationships should be balanced&#8212;with children and their elders treating each other as equals (Kagawa &#38; McCornack, 2004). To learn how you can handle cultural factors like power distance in group settings, see <link href="#choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx7-1">How to Communicate: Adapting to Cultural Differences</link> on pages 104&#8211;105.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-10" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="102">
<section-metadata><section-title>Views of Time</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p76" block_type="txt-ni">Cultures vary in terms of how people view time. Scholar Edward Hall (1997b) distinguished between two time orientations: monochronic (M-time) and polychronic (P-time). People who have a <termref term="monochronic time orientation">monochronic time orientation</termref> view time as a precious resource. It can be saved, spent, wasted, lost, or made up, and it can even run out. If you&#8217;re an M-time person, &#8220;spending time&#8221; with someone or &#8220;making time&#8221; in your schedule to share activities with him or her sends the message that you consider that person&#8212;and your relationship&#8212;important (E. T. Hall, 1983). You may view time both as a gift you give others to show your affection and as a tool for punishing someone (&#8220;I no longer have time for you&#8221;).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_103" block_type="page_start">103</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p77" block_type="txt">People who have a <termref term="polychronic time orientation">polychronic time orientation</termref> don&#8217;t view time as a resource to be spent, saved, or guarded. They don&#8217;t consider time of day (what time it is) as especially important or relevant to daily activities. Instead, they&#8217;re flexible when it comes to time, and they believe that harmonious interaction with others is more important than &#8220;being on time&#8221; or sticking to a schedule.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_104" block_type="page_start">104</p>
<box title="HOW TO COMMUNICATE &#124; Video Skills" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx7-1" block_type="bx7-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p78" block_type="bx7-t"><strong>ADAPTING TO CULTURAL DIFFERENCES</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p79" block_type="bx7-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-19" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> One way to improve your communication competence is by adapting your messages to others&#8217; behaviors. Learn how to better handle cultural differences in group settings by going to LaunchPad at <link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e"><strong>macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</strong></link> and completing the <strong>How to Communicate video scenario</strong> for <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link> to practice your skills.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p80" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>CONSIDER THIS:</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p81" block_type="bx7-txt">You&#8217;re assigned to a group project with several classmates from collectivistic, low-emotion-display, and high-power-distance cultures. The group chooses one of them, Lily, as group leader. At your first meeting, Lily begins by suggesting a topic for the project. All the other group members immediately agree. This makes you angry because you had a different idea that you were excited about and wanted the group to pursue.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p82" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>WHAT WOULD YOU DO?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p83" block_type="bx7-txt">The following advice illustrates how to communicate in a way that recognizes the cultural preferences of Lily and the other group members. This includes factors like power distance, collectivism, and emotion displays. As you watch the video, consider how the dialogue reflects each cultural factor. Then, test your knowledge of key skills, and create your own responses to the What if? video prompts.</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-16" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-20" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_04_HTC-1.jpg"/>
<caption>&#8220;I&#8217;m glad you were selected to be our group leader. I think you&#8217;ll do a great job overseeing everything.&#8221;</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p85" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-21" alt="image" src="images/1.jpg"/> <strong>OPENLY SUPPORT LILY&#8217;S AUTHORITY</strong> as group leader, even though you may see her as an equal rather than someone who has power over you.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_105" block_type="page_start">105</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p86" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-22" alt="image" src="images/2.jpg"/> <strong>AVOID AN OPEN DISPLAY OF ANGER;</strong> instead, keep your face neutral or smiling, and compliment Lily on the quality of her idea.</p>
</box>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-17" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-23" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_04_HTC-2.jpg"/>
<caption>&#8220;I like your idea for the project&#8212;it&#8217;s really smart.&#8221;</caption>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-18" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-24" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_04_HTC-2a.jpg"/>
<caption>&#8220;As there is obviously a consensus, I&#8217;m happy to support what everyone else in the group wants to do.&#8221;</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p88" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-25" alt="image" src="images/3.jpg"/> <strong>SUPPORT THE GROUP SENTIMENT,</strong> even though it may mean sacrificing your own desires.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p90" block_type="bx7-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-26" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> <strong>WHAT IF?</strong> But what if things don&#8217;t work out as shown? Test your ability to adapt your communication by watching the What if? videos and planning a response for each situation.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-3" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p91" block_type="bx7-nl-first">What if you realize Lily is trying to adapt to you when she says, &#8220;Don&#8217;t let my position as group leader keep you from expressing your own opinions. What do you really think about my idea?&#8221; What would you say?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p92" block_type="bx7-nl-last">How would you respond to Lily&#8217;s encouraging question, &#8220;I want to make sure everyone is happy. Is there something you would rather do instead?&#8221;</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_106" block_type="page_start">106</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p93" block_type="txt">Differences in time orientation can create problems when people from different cultures make appointments with each other (E. T. Hall, 1983). For example, those with an M-time orientation, such as many Americans, Canadians, Swiss, and Germans, often find it frustrating if P-time people show up for a meeting after the scheduled start time. In P-time cultures, such as those in Arabian, African, Caribbean, and Latin American countries, people think that arriving 30 minutes or more after a meeting&#8217;s scheduled start time is perfectly acceptable, and that it&#8217;s OK to change important plans at the last minute.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p94" block_type="txt">You can improve your communication by understanding other people&#8217;s views of time. Learn about the time orientation of a destination or country before you travel there. For example, when Steve&#8217;s family traveled to Saint Martin in the Caribbean, they quickly learned to schedule taxi pickup times for an hour <em>before</em> they actually wanted to be picked up. Why? Because Saint Martin runs on P-time. If you want to be picked up at 10:30 a.m., you had better tell the cabby 9:30. Even then, you never know whether he will be there by 10:30 or perhaps decide not to drive at all on that day&#8212; for example, if he unexpectedly runs into a friend and decides to hang out with him instead. You should also respect others&#8217; time orientation. If you&#8217;re an M-time person interacting with a P-time individual, don&#8217;t suddenly dash off to your next appointment because you feel you have to stick to your schedule. Your communication partner will likely think you&#8217;re rude. If you&#8217;re a P-time person interacting with an M-time individual, realize that he or she may get impatient with a long, leisurely conversation or see a late arrival to a meeting as inconsiderate. In addition, avoid criticizing or complaining about behaviors that stem from other people&#8217;s time orientations. Instead, accept the fact that people view time differently, and be willing to adapt your own expectations and behaviors accordingly.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-3" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="106">
<section-metadata><section-title>Creating Intercultural Competence</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p95" block_type="pul"><strong>Even when you understand what culture is, how co-cultures work, and the ways culture influences communication, you can still have trouble communicating with people from different backgrounds. To work toward competence, be mindful of the differences discussed so far, actively seek to understand other cultures, and adapt your communication as needed.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p96" block_type="txt-ni">It&#8217;s one of the most iconic moments&#8212;and images&#8212;from the civil rights era. On June 11, 1963, Governor George Wallace of Alabama, bolstered by state troopers, stood in the doorway of a University of Alabama building and blocked entry of two African American students (Vivian Malone and James A. Hood) who were attempting to attend class. Wallace had previously declared &#8220;segregation forever!&#8221; and now President John F. Kennedy had to deploy federal troops to force Wallace to allow admission. What few people know, however, is that Wallace&#8212;the man who had been a defining figure of racism&#8212;had a complete, 180-degree change of heart in the decades that followed. In fact, in March 1995, Wallace marked the 30th anniversary of the Selma-to-Montgomery civil rights march (depicted in the 2014 film <em>Selma</em>) by holding hands with African American leaders, singing &#8220;We Shall Overcome.&#8221; He publicly stated, &#8220;May your message be heard&#8212;may your lessons never be forgotten!&#8221; (McCarthy, 1995)</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_107" block_type="page_start">107</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx5-5" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p97" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>George Wallace is a historic example of someone who dramatically altered his judgments of people he perceived as outgroupers. Who among our contemporaries has had a similar change in perspective? Have you ever made judgments about outgroupers and later changed them, once you had achieved greater intercultural competence?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-19" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-27" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P14.jpg"/>
<asset_source>MPI/Stringer/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-20" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-28" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P15.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Alan S. Weiner Photography 2013</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p98" block_type="txt">We all make judgments regarding cultural outgroupers that lead us to perceive them as distant, different, and sometimes even inferior. But like George Wallace, we have the capacity to overcome these perceptions and prejudices, and form lasting bonds with people who come from cultures vastly different from our own. The gateway to such connections is <termref term="intercultural competence">intercultural competence</termref>, the ability to communicate appropriately, effectively, and ethically with people from diverse backgrounds. You can strengthen your intercultural competence by applying the following practices: world-mindedness, attributional complexity, and communication accommodation.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-11" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="107">
<section-metadata><section-title>World-Mindedness</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p99" block_type="txt-ni">When you possess <termref term="world-mindedness">world-mindedness</termref>, you demonstrate acceptance and respect toward other cultures&#8217; beliefs, values, and customs (Hammer, Bennett, &#38; Wiseman, 2003). You can practice world-mindedness in three ways. First, accept others&#8217; expression of their culture or co-culture as a natural element in their communication, just as your communication reflects your cultural background (Chen &#38; Starosta, 2005). Second, avoid any temptation to judge others&#8217; cultural beliefs, attitudes, and values as &#8220;better&#8221; or &#8220;worse&#8221; than your own. Third, treat people from all cultures with respect.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_108" block_type="page_start">108</p>
<box title="MAKING COMMUNICATION CHOICES" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx2-1" block_type="bx2-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p100" block_type="bx2-t"><strong>WHEN A FRIEND IS DIFFERENT</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p101" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>1</strong></phrase> <strong>CONSIDER THE DILEMMA</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p102" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">During your second semester at school, you move into a house with several other people. One of your housemates, Adoni, is an international student who differs from you in ethnicity, religion, and socioeconomic status. Having never lived with anyone but family members before, you are often amazed at Adoni&#8217;s beliefs and experiences. When Adoni shares stories about life growing up in a small village that lacked what you consider basic essentials, you can&#8217;t help but think, &#8220;How could anyone live like that!?&#8221; The more Adoni shares, the more you feel superior. Your culture and upbringing just seem so much better than Adoni&#8217;s.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p103" block_type="bx2-txt">However, you also quickly learn that Adoni is kind and generous. When you were stuck on a series of calculus proofs, Adoni took two hours to help you work through them. Then, when you came down with mono, Adoni helped you stay caught up in your classes, even sitting in on lectures and taking notes for you.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p104" block_type="bx2-txt">As the months go by, you find your mixed feelings toward Adoni intensifying. On the one hand, Adoni is honest, direct, and supportive. The two of you even share a lot of the same interests and tastes. But because Adoni is so culturally different, you&#8217;re not sure whether you could ever be close. Although you like Adoni, you still feel that Adoni&#8217;s cultural beliefs and traditions are silly and backwards.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p105" block_type="bx2-txt">One night, when the two of you are studying, Adoni says, &#8220;You know, it&#8217;s been really hard for me, adjusting to life here. Everything is so different. But your friendship has really helped. I consider you my best friend. How do you feel about me?&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p106" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>2</strong></phrase> <strong>CONNECT THE RESEARCH</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p107" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">Scholars Lily Arasaratnam and Smita Banerjee (2007) looked at the impact that <em>ethnocentrism</em>&#8212;the belief that one&#8217;s own cultural beliefs, attitudes, values, and practices are superior to those of others&#8212;has on the development of friendships. They surveyed over 400 African American, Asian American, Euro-American, and Hispanic college students, measuring ethnocentrism, the students&#8217; desire to form friendships with culturally diverse others, and the number of close friends students had from culturally dissimilar backgrounds.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p108" block_type="bx2-txt">Arasaratnam and Banerjee found that the more people believed things like &#8220;my culture is superior to all others&#8221; and &#8220;most cultures are backwards compared to my culture&#8221; (examples of ethnocentric beliefs, the less interested they were in learning about other cultures. Those with ethnocentric beliefs were also substantially less motivated to form new friendships with culturally different others and reported considerably fewer cross-cultural friends. In short, ethnocentrism acts as a powerful barrier against forming such relationships.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p109" block_type="bx2-txt">This research shows that although it&#8217;s important to possess pride in your cultural heritage, believing that your culture is <em>superior</em> to all others can cause you to avoid relationships with diverse others. Consequently, be mindful of the degree to which you judge others as culturally inferior, and always keep in mind that <em>most</em> people feel as strongly about their cultural backgrounds as you feel about yours.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_109" block_type="page_start">109</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p110" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>3</strong></phrase> <strong>COMMUNICATE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p111" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">Before making a communication choice, consider the facts of the situation, and think about the ethnocentrism research. Also, reflect on and connect what you&#8217;ve learned so far about culture (pp. 88&#8211;90), intercultural competence (pp. 106&#8211;111), and perception (pp. 93&#8211;96). Then answer these questions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-4" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p112" block_type="bx2-nl-c1">What are your thoughts and feelings toward Adoni? How is your view of your own culture&#8217;s superiority impacting your thoughts and feelings?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p113" block_type="bx2-nl-c1">How does Adoni view you and <em>your</em> culture? Does Adoni have the characteristics you look for in a good friend? Why or why not?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p114" block_type="bx2-nl-c1">What are you going to say to Adoni?</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p115" block_type="txt">This can be especially challenging when differences seem impossible to bridge or when the other person&#8217;s beliefs, attitudes, and values conflict with your own. But practicing world-mindedness means more than just tolerating cultural differences you find perplexing or problematic. Instead, treat all people with respect by being kind and courteous in your communication. You can also preserve others&#8217; personal dignity by actively listening to and asking questions about viewpoints that may differ from yours.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p116" block_type="txt">World-mindedness is the opposite of <termref term="ethnocentrism">ethnocentrism</termref>, the belief that one&#8217;s own cultural beliefs, attitudes, values, and practices are superior to those of others. Ethnocentrism is not the same thing as pride in your cultural heritage or patriotism. You can be culturally proud or nationally patriotic and not be ethnocentric. Instead, ethnocentrism is a <em>comparative evaluation</em>; ethnocentric people view their own culture or co-culture as the standard against which all other cultures should be judged, and they often have contempt for other cultures (Neuliep &#38; McCroskey, 1997; Sumner, 1906). Consequently, such people tend to see their own communication as competent and that of people from other cultures as incompetent.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-12" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="109">
<section-metadata><section-title>Attributional Complexity</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p117" block_type="txt-ni">When you practice <termref term="attributional complexity">attributional complexity</termref>, you acknowledge that other people&#8217;s behaviors have complex causes. To develop this ability, observe others&#8217; behavior, and analyze the various forces influencing it. For example, rather than deciding that a classmate&#8217;s reserved demeanor or limited eye contact means she&#8217;s unfriendly, consider the possibility that these behaviors might reflect cultural differences.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p118" block_type="txt">Also, learn as much as you can about different cultures and co-cultures, so that you can better understand people&#8217;s communication styles and preferences. Experiencing other cultures through observation, travel, or interaction is a great way to sharpen your intercultural communication competence (Arasaratnam, 2006).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_110" block_type="page_start">110</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx5-6" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p119" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>One way to enhance world-mindedness, practice attributional complexity, and try communication accommodation is to travel and experience other cultures firsthand. What experiences do you have with traveling in other cultures, and what did you learn from these interactions?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-21" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-29" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_04_P16.jpg"/>
<asset_source>bikeriderlondon/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p120" block_type="txt">In addition, routinely use <em>perception-checking</em> to avoid attributional errors, and regularly demonstrate <em>empathy</em> to identify with others. In situations in which the cultural gaps between you and others seem impossibly wide, try to see things from their perspectives, and consider the motivations behind their communication. Examine how people from diverse backgrounds make decisions, and compare their approaches to yours. Finally, ask others to explain the reasons for their behavior, and then accept and validate their explanations (&#8220;That makes sense to me&#8221;) rather than challenging them (&#8220;You&#8217;ve got to be kidding!&#8221;). Avoid making statements such as, &#8220;I know that people like you act this way because you think that . . .&#8221;; you&#8217;ll only come across as presumptuous.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec2-13" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="110">
<section-metadata><section-title>Communication Accommodation</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p121" block_type="txt-ni">A final way to enhance your intercultural competence is to adjust your communication to mesh with the behaviors of people from other cultures. According to <termref term="communication accommodation theory">communication accommodation theory</termref>, people are especially motivated to adapt their communication when they seek social approval, when they wish to establish relationships with others, and when they view others&#8217; language usage as appropriate (Giles, Coupland, &#38; Coupland, 1991). In contrast, people tend to accentuate differences between their communication and others&#8217; when they wish to convey emotional distance and disassociate themselves from others. Research suggests that people who use communication accommodation are perceived as more competent (Coupland, Giles, &#38; Wiemann, 1991; Giles et al., 1991).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_111" block_type="page_start">111</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p122" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-30" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e"><strong>macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</strong></link>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p123" block_type="txt">How does this work in practice? Try adapting to other people&#8217;s communication preferences (Bianconi, 2002). During interactions, notice how long a turn people take when speaking, how quickly they speak, how direct they are, and how much they appear to want to talk compared to you. You may also need to learn and practice cultural norms for nonverbal behaviors&#8212;including eye contact, head touching, and handshaking.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p124" block_type="txt">You can even do this during public presentations. For example, find out about your listeners&#8217; preferences during your audience analysis, and try to adapt your communication accordingly while developing your speech. So if you&#8217;ll be speaking to an audience whose first language is not English, avoid slang; your listeners may not understand it. At the same time, avoid imitating other people&#8217;s dialects, accents, or word choices. Most people consider such imitation inappropriate and insulting.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p125" block_type="txt">To help you boost your own intercultural communication competence, consider the five suggestions in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx6-1">Table 4.1</link>, which pulls together what we&#8217;ve discussed in this chapter.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-bx6-1" block_type="bx6">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p126" block_type="co-drop"><strong>TABLE 4.1 CREATING INTERCULTURAL COMMUNICATION COMPETENCE</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-fig-22" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-31" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_04_T01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>VLADGRIN/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_112" block_type="page_start">112</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-4" block_type="cr-h" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="112">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER 4 REVIEW</section-title></section-metadata>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-5" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="112">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER RECAP</section-title></section-metadata>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-5" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p128" block_type="cr-bl-v0">A <termref term="culture">culture</termref> is a set of widely shared beliefs, attitudes, values, and practices; cultures are learned, communicated, layered, and lived.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p129" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Judging someone as a member of a shared <termref term="co-culture">co-culture</termref>, as an <termref term="ingrouper">ingrouper</termref>, or as an <termref term="outgrouper">outgrouper</termref> influences how you perceive and communicate with that person.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p130" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Cultures vary in terms of where they fall in certain spectrums. Communication styles and tolerance for <strong>uncertainty avoidance</strong> are highly influenced by whether people identify as coming from an <strong>individualistic</strong> or a <strong>collectivistic culture</strong>, or from a <strong>high-</strong> or <strong>low-context culture</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p131" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Additional cultural influences on communication include emotion displays, <termref term="power distance">power distance</termref> preferences, and views of time. Considering these factors can help you better communicate with others.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p132" block_type="cr-bl-v0">You can strengthen your <termref term="intercultural competence">intercultural competence</termref> through <strong>world-mindedness</strong>, <termref term="attributional complexity">attributional complexity</termref>, and communication accommodation.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p133" block_type="cr-txt-ni"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-32" alt="image" src="images/launchpad.jpg"/> LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> offers unique video scenarios and encourages self-assessment through adaptive quizzing. Go to <link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e"><strong>macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</strong></link> to get access.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p134" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-33" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> LearningCurve adaptive quizzes</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p135" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-34" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> How to Communicate video scenarios</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p136" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-35" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> Video clips that illustrate key concepts</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-6" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="112">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p137" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p22">Culture, p. 88</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p138" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p28"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-36" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Power, p. 91</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p139" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p28">Co-cultural communication theory, p. 91</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p140" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p29">Co-cultures, p. 92</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p141" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p39">Ingroupers, p. 93</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p142" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p39">Outgroupers, p. 93</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p143" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p44">Race, p. 94</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p144" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p46">Prejudice, p. 95</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p145" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p48">Stereotype Content Model, p. 95</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p146" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p58">Individualistic culture, p. 97</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p147" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p60">Collectivistic culture, p. 98</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p148" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p62">High-context cultures, p. 99</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p149" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p63">Low-context cultures, p. 99</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p150" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p65">Uncertainty avoidance, p. 99</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p151" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p67"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-37" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Display rules, p. 100</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p152" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p72">Power distance, p. 102</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p153" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p76">Monochronic time orientation, p. 102</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p154" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p77">Polychronic time orientation, p. 103</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p155" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p98">Intercultural competence, p. 107</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p156" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p99">World-mindedness, p. 107</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p157" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p116">Ethnocentrism, p. 109</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p158" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p117">Attributional complexity, p. 109</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p159" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch4-p121">Communication accommodation theory, p. 110</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_113" block_type="page_start">113</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-7" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="113">
<section-metadata><section-title>POP QUIZ</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p160" block_type="cr-wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-img-38" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> Looking for more review questions? <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you master key concepts from this chapter. Go to<link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e"><strong>macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</strong></link>.</p>
</box>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-question-1" number="1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p161" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">According to co-cultural communication theory, the people with the most &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; within a society determine the <em>dominant culture</em>.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-6" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p162" block_type="cr-ll-v1">ethnocentrism</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p163" block_type="cr-ll-v1">world-mindedness</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p164" block_type="cr-ll-v1">prejudice</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p165" block_type="cr-ll-v1">power</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-question-2" number="2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p166" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">When people communicate in rude or inappropriate ways, you&#8217;re more inclined to form negative impressions of them if you see them as &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-7" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p167" block_type="cr-ll-v1">ingroupers</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p168" block_type="cr-ll-v1">M-time followers</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p169" block_type="cr-ll-v1">outgroupers</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p170" block_type="cr-ll-v1">P-time followers</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-question-3" number="3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p171" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">In &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; cultures, people tend not to presume that others share their beliefs, attitudes, and values; thus, they strive to be informative, clear, and direct in their communication.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-8" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p172" block_type="cr-ll-v1">individualistic</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p173" block_type="cr-ll-v1">low-context</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p174" block_type="cr-ll-v1">high-context</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p175" block_type="cr-ll-v1">collectivistic</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-question-4" number="4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p176" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">In high-uncertainty-avoidance cultures, what do people place a lot of value on?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p177" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Innovative ideas</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p178" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Control</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p179" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Comparative evaluation</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p180" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Change</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-question-5" number="5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p181" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">According to the chapter, which of the following is <em>not</em> a way to create intercultural competence?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p182" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Practicing attributional complexity</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p183" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Employing benevolent prejudice</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p184" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Using communication accommodation</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p185" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Considering cultural influences on communication</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-sec1-8" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch4" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="113">
<section-metadata><section-title>ACTIVITIES</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-exp4-1" block_type="mn4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p186" block_type="cr-wl-txt">For more activities, visit LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> at <link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e"><strong>macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</strong></link>.</p>
</box>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-list-11" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p187" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Exploring Your Cultural Layers</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p188" block_type="cr-txt">A basic truth about culture is that we all exist as multiple layers of cultural influences&#8212;including age, class, nationality, ethnicity, sexual orientation, gender, and religion. To better understand how your varied cultural and co-cultural identities impact your communication, list what you think are your most important cultural markers (e.g., &#8220;I&#8217;m an upper-middle-class, Evangelical, Latina female from the Southwest United States&#8221;). Then, write a brief comment (no more than one to two sentences for each cultural marker) explaining how exactly each culture or co-culture impacts your communication with others, both positively and negatively. Finally, connect your layered cultural identities to outcomes in your life. What personal and professional challenges and benefits have you experienced? How do those challenges and benefits influence your communication with others? If you feel comfortable, present this information to your class in a two- to three-minute speech.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p189" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Culture in the Media</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch4-p190" block_type="cr-txt">Many TV shows and movies base their jokes on stereotypical communication problems between men and women or between people from different cultures. For example, think about how shows like <em>Fresh Off the Boat</em> or movies like <em>Trainwreck</em> get a lot of their laughs. With a partner, find an example from the media that uses culture and communication in this way. Discuss how the example embodies or violates principles discussed in this chapter. How could the media better represent communication between people from different cultures?</p></li>
</list>
</section>
</chapter>
</manuscript>