<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<manuscript xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" manuscript-id="01" name="" title="MCC_Chapter_01_DJHrev" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/digfir_manuscript.xsd">
<chapter number="1" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-chapter-1" title="1: Introduction to Communication" start-numbering-at="1" numbered="true">
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_2" block_type="page_start">2</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p1" block_type="chapter_number">1</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p2" block_type="chapter_title">Introduction to Communication</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p3" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">H</phrase>is goal was simple: create a fun forum for talking about bands with other music enthusiasts.<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p4"><sup>1</sup></link> As he describes, &#8220;I originally decided to host the festival so I could connect and hang with club owners and music lovers I knew in Kansas City and New Orleans.&#8221; But little did newspaper editor Louis Black know that his brainchild&#8212;South by Southwest (SXSW)&#8212;would eventually morph into the world&#8217;s largest multipurpose festival, featuring not just music but every type of entertainment, communication, and media technology imaginable.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p4" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p3"><sup>1</sup></link>All content in the opener adapted from Dream Share Project (2011) and <link href="http://sxsw.com">http://sxsw.com</link>.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p5" block_type="co-txt">Each spring, SXSW draws tens of thousands of musicians, filmmakers, tech designers, and spectators to Austin, Texas. More than 2,500 artists perform, and they are as talented as they are diverse: rapper A&#36;AP Ferg, electronic duo Crystal Castles, and Americana rock bands like The Strumbellas and The Avett Brothers. Dozens of films are debuted. Hundreds of games and apps are demoed. SXSW has even become a key way to break into various media industries. Miguel, Alabama Shakes, and Foster the People all received Grammy nominations after appearing at the festival. Movies debuting at SXSW include <em>Fast and Furious 7, Ex Machina,</em> and <em>Bridesmaids</em>. Even Twitter first gained national (and international) popularity following heavy publicity at SXSW.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p6" block_type="co-txt">At the heart of SXSW, however, is communication. Festival organizers use social media such as Twitter, Instagram, Facebook, and Vimeo to coordinate and conduct the festival. Amid the various musical performances and film screenings, SXSW participants interact face-to-face with industry leaders, socialize at meet-ups with friends and new acquaintances, participate in group workshops, and even interview for jobs. Each day brings opportunities to listen in on panel discussions and presentations hosted by people like Facebook&#8217;s Mark Zuckerberg, television host Anthony Bourdain, YouTube cofounder Steve Chen and filmmaker J.J. Abrams. Many of these events are streamed live online, so people around the world can share in the experience. What began as quiet conversations in the darkened corners of nightclubs is now a multifaceted communication extravaganza.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p7" block_type="co-txt">Despite its size, impact, and global reach, SXSW remains dedicated to Louis Black&#8217;s original intent: connecting people through communication. As he describes, &#8220;We&#8217;ve struggled hard to maintain the integrity of the event. . . . What we love most is the creative community that comes out of the event. SXSW may be huge, but it&#8217;s fundamentally about people who love music and film and new media; and most importantly people who love to <em>talk</em> about it all with each other.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_3" block_type="page_start">3</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-1" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-1" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_01_P01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Michael Buckner/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_4" block_type="page_start">4</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p8" block_type="co-h"><strong>CHAPTER OUTLINE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p9" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-1"><strong>What Is Communication?</strong> 4</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p10" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-2"><strong>Studying Communication</strong> 11</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p11" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-3"><strong>Communication Competence</strong> 18</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p12" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-4"><strong>Choices and Connections</strong> 23</link></p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p13" block_type="txt-ni">Communication connects us to one another. Whether you&#8217;re attending a festival like SXSW or spending a normal day at school, work, or home, you interact with people one-on-one, in groups, and in public. You may text, tweet, post, e-mail, call, or talk face-to-face. You might give a presentation to a small or large audience or interview for a job.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p14" block_type="txt">Across all of these types and instances of communication, two things are important to keep in mind. First, <em>the communication choices you make are connected to the outcomes that follow</em>. When you communicate well, you increase the likelihood of desirable outcomes, such as successful group projects; compelling presentations; and satisfying, healthy relationships. When you communicate poorly, you are more likely to generate negative outcomes, such as group dissatisfaction, confused audience members, and relationship turmoil.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p15" block_type="txt">Second, <em>different types of communication are connected to each other in fundamental ways</em>. Sure, texting a close friend is different from sending an e-mail to a work group or giving a speech in front of a class. However, these forms of communication also share similarities. Specifically, they involve presenting yourself to others, planning your messages, and using language to convey your thoughts. Because of these connections, what you learn in every chapter of this book will apply to a wide variety of scenarios.</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p16" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-2" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p17" block_type="txt">This book will help you build your communication skills by deepening your understanding of communication choices and their connections. In this chapter, you&#8217;ll learn:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p18" block_type="bl-f">What communication is and how the communication process works</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p19" block_type="bl-m">The goals that communication helps you achieve</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p20" block_type="bl-m">How the study of communication developed</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p21" block_type="bl-m">The characteristics of communication competence</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p22" block_type="bl-l">The choices and connections underlying your communication</p></li>
</list>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-1" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="4">
<section-metadata><section-title>What Is Communication?</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p23" block_type="pul"><strong>Lots of people believe that communication is just common sense. But people are not born knowing how to communicate well. Instead, they become good communicators by learning about communication concepts and theories, building skills, and practicing in their everyday lives. You can take the first step toward becoming a competent communicator by learning what communication is and why it matters.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p24" block_type="txt-ni">When you think about communication and the role it plays in your life, what may leap to mind are the various challenges you face. For instance, &#8220;How do I make a good first impression?&#8221; &#8220;Why don&#8217;t the other group members listen to my ideas?&#8221; or &#8220;What can I do to amplify the impact of my presentations?&#8221; To answer these questions and meet these challenges, many people rely on intuition. Why? Because they think that communication is &#8220;just common sense.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_5" block_type="page_start">5</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx5-1" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p25" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Whether you&#8217;re covering up a crime like the law students in <em>How to Get Away with Murder</em> or just meeting a friend for coffee, the messages you convey, the context of the situation, and the channel and media through which you interact all have an impact on your conversation.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-2" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-3" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_11_P02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; ABC/Photofest</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p26" block_type="txt">But there&#8217;s a gulf of difference between a communicator who relies on intuition and one who is highly trained and educated. Communication is like any other knowledge-based skill set. Think about it: most of us have an intuitive sense of how to kick balls around a field. Does that mean we&#8217;re all World Cup soccer players? No. When you receive formal education about communication, you learn information based on theory, research, and practice. This empowers you to broaden and deepen your skills as a communicator, allowing you to surpass what you&#8217;d be able to do if you relied on intuition alone. Simply put, reading this book and taking this class will train you to become a world-class communicator. Your journey toward this goal begins with this basic question: What exactly <em>is</em> communication?</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-1" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="5">
<section-metadata><section-title>Defining Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p27" block_type="txt-ni">The National Communication Association (2002), a professional organization representing communication teachers and scholars in the United States, defines <termref term="communication">communication</termref> as the process through which people use messages to generate meanings within and across contexts, cultures, channels, and media. This definition highlights five features of communication.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p28" block_type="txt">First, communication is a <em>process</em> that unfolds over time through a series of interconnected actions. Imagine it&#8217;s the first day of the semester, and the professor asks a question. You raise your hand to demonstrate your attentiveness, but when the professor calls on you, your mind goes blank, and your classmates laugh. Now when the professor asks a question, you&#8217;ll be less likely to raise your hand. Think about the process that unfolded: the professor asked a question; you responded by raising your hand; your mind went blank; students laughed; your feelings were hurt; and now you&#8217;re more cautious about sharing your ideas out of fear of ridicule. Thinking of communication as a process means realizing that <em>everything you and others say and do during encounters shapes what happens in that moment and in the future</em>.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_6" block_type="page_start">6</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p29" block_type="txt">Second, people engaged in communication (&#8220;communicators&#8221;) use <em>messages</em> to convey meaning. A <termref term="message">message</termref> is the &#8220;package&#8221; of information transported during communication. When people exchange a series of messages, whether face-to-face or online, the result is an <termref term="interaction">interaction</termref> (Watzlawick, Beavin, &#38; Jackson, 1967).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p30" block_type="txt">Third, communication occurs in a seemingly endless variety of <termref term="contexts">contexts</termref>, or situations. For instance, you communicate with others in class, at parties, at work, and at home. In each context, many different factors affect how you communicate. These factors include how much time you have, how many people are in the situation, and whether the setting is personal or professional. This is why you probably communicate differently with a friend while playing video games than when the two of you are sitting next to each other in class.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p31" block_type="txt">Fourth, people communicate through various channels. A <termref term="channel">channel</termref> is the sensory dimension along which communicators transmit information. The most common channels are auditory (sound), visual (sight), and tactile (touch). For example, your professor smiles at you and says, &#8220;Great job on your presentation!&#8221; (visual and auditory channels), or a friend comforts you with a hug after you learn that you didn&#8217;t get the job offer you wanted (tactile).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p32" block_type="txt">Fifth, to transmit information, communicators use a broad range of <termref term="media">media</termref>, or tools for exchanging messages. Media can include texting, tweeting, posting, e-mailing, making a phone call, or talking face-to-face using video technology. Often people use several different media at once. For example, you text a friend while you&#8217;re checking Tumblr or Instagram, you call your mother while you&#8217;re scrolling through her latest e-mail to you, or you Google reviews for a movie you&#8217;re interested in seeing while Skyping a colleague who&#8217;s in a different office. <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link> (Mediated Communication) will explore more about how technology influences your communication.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-2" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="6">
<section-metadata><section-title>Why You Communicate</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p33" block_type="txt-ni">Why do you communicate? The answer may seem obvious: you communicate to share your thoughts and feelings to others. Although that is true, communication also helps you meet three types of goals (Clark &#38; Delia, 1979).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p34" block_type="txt">The first type is <termref term="self-presentation goals">self-presentation goals</termref>, which involve presenting yourself in certain ways so that others will view you as you want them to. For example, when SXSW founder Louis Black first came up with the idea of hosting a music festival in Austin, he had to pitch the proposal to both community leaders and corporate sponsors. In each of these encounters, he had to present himself as a credible, trustworthy person who would organize the gathering responsibly&#8212;or else his proposal would never have been supported.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_7" block_type="page_start">7</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p35" block_type="txt">The second type is <termref term="instrumental goals">instrumental goals</termref>&#8212;practical objectives you want to achieve or tasks you want to accomplish. To create SXSW, Louis Black needed community leaders and corporate sponsors to perceive him (through how he communicated) as credible and trustworthy (self-presentation goals). But he <em>also</em> needed to <em>persuade</em> them to approve the necessary permits and provide him with money for events, and so he tailored his communication toward achieving these instrumental goals. Oftentimes, you&#8217;ll find that presenting yourself in certain ways (likable, trustworthy, credible) facilitates the achievement of your practical goals.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p36" block_type="txt">The third type is <termref term="relationship goals">relationship goals</termref>&#8212;building, maintaining, or terminating bonds with others. This is perhaps the coolest part of the SXSW story. Although it&#8217;s now a &#36;300 million global media and music festival, SXSW originally began because Louis Black wanted to talk and build friendships with fellow music lovers. Like Louis, whenever we use our communication to create emotional connections with others, we are pursuing relationship goals.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-3" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="7">
<section-metadata><section-title>Communication Models</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p37" block_type="txt-ni">Think about all the different ways you communicate each day. You text your best friend, saying you&#8217;re finished with work and are ready to be picked up. You present awards at your soccer team&#8217;s end-of-season banquet, acting more animated when you see people&#8217;s attention start to wander. You spend the evening with your brother, reliving and retelling stories from your childhood.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p38" block_type="txt">But how does the communication process differ in each scenario? Sometimes you create messages and send them to receivers (like your text message). Other times you present messages to recipients, and they indicate their understanding and interest (like the audience members at the soccer banquet). Or you may mutually create meanings with others, with no one serving as &#8220;sender&#8221; or &#8220;receiver&#8221; (like you and your brother sharing family stories). These scenarios reflect three different ways of viewing the communication process: the <em>linear model</em>, the <em>interactive model</em>, and the <em>transactional model</em>.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p39" block_type="txt">As you continue reading about these models, keep a few things in mind. First, communication scholars developed these models to examine and describe how communication works. Second, the models represent a historical evolution of scholarly thought, from a relatively simple depiction of communication as a linear process (the linear model) to one that views communication as a complicated process that is mutually crafted (the transactional model). Finally, each model doesn&#8217;t necessarily represent a good or a bad way of thinking about communication. Instead, each offers a different way of identifying the important elements affecting the communication process.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p40" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Linear Communication Model.</strong></phrase> The linear model was the first formal model of communication and was created more than sixty years ago by engineers at Bell Labs to explain how information is transmitted across telephone lines (Shannon &#38; Weaver, 1949). According to the <termref term="linear communication model">linear communication model</termref>, communication is an activity in which information flows in one direction, from a start point to an end point. The linear model contains several components. In addition to a <em>message</em> and a <em>channel</em>, there is a <termref term="sender">sender</termref> (or senders)&#8212;the individual who generates the information to be communicated, packages it into a message, and chooses one or more channels for sending it. The person (or people) for whom a message is intended is the <termref term="receiver">receiver</termref>. The transmission of the message is often affected by <termref term="noise">noise</termref><strong>&#8212;</strong>distractions that change how the message is received. Noise may originate outside the communicators&#8212;such as lagging or pixelation during Skype. Or it can come from the communicators themselves, such as when distracting thoughts cause senders&#8217; or receivers&#8217; attention to drift. (See <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-3">Figure 1.1</link>.)</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx4-1" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-3" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="1.1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 1.1</strong></phrase> <strong>LINEAR MODEL OF COMMUNICATION</strong></caption>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-4" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_F01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Kira Kuznetsova/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_8" block_type="page_start">8</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p41" block_type="txt">Although the linear model was conceived more than six decades ago, it still accurately illustrates the broad range of communication forms you experience every day. For example, much of your online communication&#8212;including tweets, texts, e-mails, and wall posts&#8212;reflects this model. Certain public-speaking contexts may also fit, especially those in which you present prepared scripts to audience members who are expected to sit quietly and listen without responding to or challenging you. But the linear model doesn&#8217;t accurately explain other communication forms, such as face-to-face conversation. For example, when you converse with a friend face-to-face, you may speak in partial sentences and rely on the other person to mentally fill in the missing information. The linear model doesn&#8217;t account for the back-and-forth flow of such encounters.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_9" block_type="page_start">9</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p42" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Interactive Communication Model.</strong></phrase> The <termref term="interactive communication model">interactive communication model</termref> also views communication as a process involving senders and receivers. However, according to this model, communication is influenced by two additional factors: feedback and fields of experience (Schramm, 1954). <termref term="Feedback">Feedback</termref> consists of the verbal and nonverbal messages coming from recipients in response to messages. For example, by nodding and saying &#8220;Uh-huh&#8221; or &#8220;That&#8217;s right,&#8221; recipients let senders know they&#8217;ve received and understood messages. Feedback also lets receivers indicate their approval or disapproval of messages. <termref term="Fields of experience">Fields of experience</termref> consist of the beliefs, attitudes, values, and experiences that each participant brings to a communication event. People with similar fields of experience are more likely to understand each other than are individuals with dissimilar fields of experience. (See <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-4">Figure 1.2</link>.)</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx4-2" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-4" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="1.2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 1.2</strong></phrase> <strong>INTERACTIVE MODEL OF COMMUNICATION</strong></caption>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-5" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_F02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Kira Kuznetsova/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p43" block_type="txt">Like the linear model, the interactive model accurately describes a range of communication forms that you experience. For example, while giving a speech in class, you may notice the reactions of your classmates&#8212;such as fidgeting or lack of eye contact&#8212;and then modify your message on the spot as needed to capture their attention and get your message across. Classroom instruction, group presentations, and weekly team meetings among coworkers are often viewed as interactive.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p44" block_type="txt">Also like the linear model, the interactive model presents communication as a process in which there is a clearly designated and active sender and a receiver. But it overlooks the active role that receivers often play in constructing the meaning of communication events, as well as instances in which people jointly create meaning. At a family reunion, for example, your uncle starts droning on as usual about &#8220;kids these days.&#8221; You and your sister glance at each other and immediately understand the meaning of your shared look. If you were to put words to this meaning, you would both be saying, &#8220;Here he goes again.&#8221; But neither of you is the sender or the receiver in this instance; instead, you <em>collaboratively</em> create communication meaning. The transactional communication model can help explain such encounters.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_10" block_type="page_start">10</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p45" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Transactional Communication Model.</strong></phrase> The <termref term="transactional communication model">transactional communication model</termref> views communication as multidirectional; that is, participants mutually influence one another&#8217;s communication behavior (Miller &#38; Steinberg, 1975). According to this model, there aren&#8217;t senders or receivers. Instead, participants constantly exchange verbal and nonverbal messages and feedback to collaboratively create meanings. (See <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-5">Figure 1.3</link>.) This may be something as simple as a shared look, as in the preceding example with your sister and your uncle. It may be an animated and intense conversation between you and a friend, in which the meanings exchanged go way beyond the words that are said. It may even involve people jointly creating acts of communication. Sociologist Jurgen Streek (1980), in discussing the transactional nature of communication, describes a classroom roll call he once observed. The teacher asked, &#8220;Now, where is . . .&#8221; and before she could complete her query, a student chimed in &#8220;Ernesto?&#8221; knowing just who the teacher was seeking. Such instances illustrate how we often build communication collaboratively rather than simply receiving or sending messages.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx4-3" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-5" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="1.3" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 1.3</strong></phrase> <strong>TRANSACTIONAL MODEL OF COMMUNICATION</strong></caption>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-6" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_F03.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Kira Kuznetsova/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_11" block_type="page_start">11</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p46" block_type="txt">The transactional communication model intuitively captures encounters that seem interpersonal in nature. These include instances such as you and your romantic partner having a phone conversation in which the words seem secondary to the feelings being conveyed, as well as conversations with close friends, in which a few key words or looks instantly convey a wealth of shared information (we discuss interpersonal communication in more detail in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch09.xml">Chapters 9</link> and <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch10.xml">10</link>). But the transactional model doesn&#8217;t fit certain types of online communication, such as tweets, texts, e-mails, and wall posts, in which senders and receivers are more clearly designated; those types of communication are better described as either linear or interactive.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-2" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="11">
<section-metadata><section-title>Studying Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p47" block_type="pul"><strong>Now that you have a better understanding of what communication is, let&#8217;s look at how people have studied communication throughout the ages, and the types of communication that teachers and scholars focus on today. Understanding the past, present, and future of the communication field will help you apply what you learn to your everyday life.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p48" block_type="txt">The authors of this book, Steve and Joe, both started college with the goal of becoming lawyers. But their plans&#8212;and their lives&#8212;changed when they began to study communication. For Joe, the turning point came during an afternoon jog with an attorney named Tom Roebuck, who occasionally trained with Joe&#8217;s university cross-country team. While talking about classes and potential majors, Tom told Joe, &#8220;I can&#8217;t think of any better preparation for law school than a communication degree.&#8221; The next day, Joe switched his major. As he continued his course work, he grew fascinated with communication as a field of study and ultimately decided to pursue a teaching career instead of going to law school.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p49" block_type="txt">Steve&#8217;s story is similar. As an undergrad at the University of Washington, he visited his professor, Mac Parks, during office hours. While chatting about a reading from class, Steve remarked that he had <em>always</em> been fascinated by how people communicate, but that he had never pursued this interest because he didn&#8217;t know how it translated into a collegiate major or profession. Mac then described all of the things that Steve could potentially do with a communication degree: sales, marketing, public relations, publishing, lobbying, consulting, broadcasting, and so forth. When Steve confessed that his <em>true</em> passion was the study of romantic relationship problems such as jealousy, betrayal, and deception, Mac asked Steve, &#8220;Have you ever thought about going into the field?&#8221; Steve admitted that he didn&#8217;t even know what &#8220;the field of communication&#8221; was. When Mac told him, &#8220;You could spend your life studying and teaching about close relationships,&#8221; Steve suddenly realized that the field of communication&#8212;not the law&#8212;was his calling.</p>
<box title="COMMUNICATION AT WORK" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx1-1" block_type="bx1-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_12" block_type="page_start">12</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p50" block_type="bx1-txt"><strong>Studying communication fosters real-life skills that are valuable in the workplace. Whether you&#8217;re a nurse, an author and businesswoman like Facebook COO Sheryl Sandberg, or an athlete, knowing how to competently communicate can make or break your success.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-6" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-7" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_11_P04.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Hero Images/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-7" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-8" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_11_P03.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Imaginechina via AP Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-8" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-9" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_11_P05.jpg"/>
<asset_source>John Rhodes/Fort Worth Star-Telegram/MCT via Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p51" block_type="txt">For some of you, the communication class you&#8217;re taking (for which you are reading this book) will be your only exposure to the field. For others, this class&#8212;and other courses in communication&#8212;may inspire you to become communication majors. You might even experience the same thing Joe and Steve did: the realization that you want to devote your life to studying and teaching communication. But regardless of whether you take one communication class, make communication your college major, or build a career involving communication, learning about communication connects you to a scholarly field that dates back thousands of years.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-4" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="12">
<section-metadata><section-title>A Brief History of Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p52" block_type="txt-ni">The field of communication is undeniably modern, with its attention to topics like social media, online relationships, and the effects of video games. But it has ancient roots. By understanding a little about the field&#8217;s history, you can see how the concepts and practices you&#8217;ll learn about in this book evolved from the past into their present-day forms.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_13" block_type="page_start">13</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p53" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Communication in Antiquity.</strong></phrase> Communication is an academic discipline that goes back thousands of years and traverses many different cultures. For example, one of the earliest books ever written&#8212;the maxims of the Egyptian sage Ptahhotep (2200 <phrase block_type="small">B.C.E.</phrase>)&#8212;offers suggestions for improving your communication (Horne, 1917). In this ancient guidebook, Ptahhotep encourages people to be truthful, kind, and tolerant in their communication. He urges readers to practice active listening, especially in situations in which people lack experience, because &#8220;to not do so is to embrace ignorance.&#8221; He also emphasizes mindfulness in using language, noting that &#8220;good words are more difficult to find than emeralds.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p54" block_type="txt">Almost 2,000 years after Ptahhotep, the communication tradition known as rhetoric emerged. <termref term="Rhetoric">Rhetoric</termref> is the theory and practice of persuading others through speech (Dues &#38; Brown, 2004), and it became a formal discipline of study in ancient Greece and Rome (Kennedy, 1999). In Greece, Socrates and his student Plato were among the first to debate the nature of rhetoric. Socrates thought of rhetoric not as a philosophy but as a practical skill that people could gain through experience (Kennedy, 1999). Socrates and Plato also knew that people could use communication skills in unethical as well as ethical ways, and they argued strongly against using words to manipulate or exploit others. But it was Aristotle&#8212;perhaps the best-known ancient Greek scholar&#8212;who taught that ethical persuasion required a speaker to demonstrate credibility, provide logical reasoning, and appeal to the emotions of listeners. As you&#8217;ll learn in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch17.xml">Chapter 17</link>, Aristotle&#8217;s teachings are still very relevant today in understanding how to develop a persuasive speech.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p55" block_type="txt">The study of rhetoric was also a concern of ancient Romans. Statesman and orator Cicero noted three practical objectives of public speaking: to instruct, to persuade, and to honor (Clarke, 1953). These goals are still discussed in modern public-speaking courses as informative, persuasive, and special occasion speeches. Cicero also outlined the five requirements of speech crafting and presentation still in use today: invention (reasoning out truth to make your case compelling), arrangement (organizing the information you want to present), style (selecting suitable words to convey the information), memory (knowing your subject and remembering your words), and delivery (controlling your body and voice when presenting your speech). In <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch13.xml">Chapters 13</link>&#8211;<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch17.xml">17</link>, you&#8217;ll learn how these requirements guide the preparation and delivery of speeches.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p56" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Communication in the Early 20th Century.</strong></phrase> Throughout the era stretching from ancient Rome to the close of the 19th century, communication scholars stayed focused on rhetoric. In the 1900s, however, scholars&#8212;stimulated by philosophical interest in the human mind and behavior&#8212;began studying forms of communication other than rhetoric, across a broad range of disciplines (Knapp, Daly, Albada, &#38; Miller, 2002). For example, in 1927, political scientist Harold Lasswell detailed the four persuasive aims of governmental propaganda: to create hatred against the enemy, to preserve friendship with allies, to gain the cooperation of neutral parties, and to demoralize the enemy. Harvard business professor Elton Mayo examined the effects of coworker interactions on productivity, giving rise to the human relations movement and the recognition that supportiveness is crucial for competent workplace communication (Roethlisberger &#38; Dickson, 1939). Psychologist Jean Piaget (1926) analyzed the role that children&#8217;s ability to <em>perspective-take</em> (see things from others&#8217; viewpoint) played in shaping their communication. By World War II, dozens of scholars in several different disciplines were studying communication and communication-related topics, such as the effect of environments on interaction, empathy, and conflict.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_14" block_type="page_start">14</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p57" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Communication after World War II.</strong></phrase> Immediately following World War II, interest in the field of communication exploded, mostly owing to the use of mass media propaganda during the war. Countries on each side had harnessed film and radio to send messages on a massive scale to their respective populations, convincing them that their cause was just and that the enemy was &#8220;evil.&#8221; With so many professors wanting to research communication, and so many students wanting to learn about it, universities began creating dedicated communication departments. Some schools housed communication studies researchers alongside rhetorical scholars, creating departments focused on speech communication.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p58" block_type="txt">By the early 1970s, dozens of communication and speech communication departments existed in the United States. Colleges and universities taught classes in the traditional areas of public speaking and rhetoric, but they also introduced new areas, such as mass media effects, communication in relationships, group discussion, and organizational communication. As the discipline became further unified, it attracted even more interest among scholars and students. Topics of interest diversified further. By the end of the 20th century, nonverbal communication, gender and communication, communication across cultures, health communication, and communication technologies became standard offerings in undergraduate curricula at hundreds of American colleges and universities, and institutions outside the United States began to offer communication classes as well.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p59" block_type="txt">Today, tens of thousands of students around the world graduate each year with majors in communication, and millions more take communication classes. These students learn about cutting-edge research, examining such things as how others&#8217; online posts about you influence people&#8217;s perception of you (discussed in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link>), verbal aggression and cyberbullying (<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml">Chapter 5</link>), how to work productively in a virtual group (<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch11.xml">Chapter 11</link>), and how to deal with speech anxiety (<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch15.xml">Chapter 15</link>). Armed with a broad knowledge of communication theory and practical skills, students majoring in communication go on to pursue careers in areas as diverse as human resource management, public relations, sales, marketing, sports broadcasting, media production, news media, advertising, community relations, and political consulting. To see how being skilled in communication may apply to your career path, see <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-tab-1">Table 1.1</link>.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx6-1" block_type="bx6">
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-tab-1" block_type="table" caption-placement="top">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tab-label">TABLE 1.1</phrase></strong> <strong>CAREERS IN COMMUNICATION</strong><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p60"><sup>2</sup></link></table_caption>
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-9" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-10" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_T01a.jpg"/>
</figure></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-19" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p305" block_type="bl-first">Sales</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p306" block_type="bl-mid">Human Resources</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p307" block_type="bl-mid">Insurance</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p308" block_type="bl-mid">Real Estate</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p309" block_type="bl-last">Entrepreneur</p></li>
</list></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-20" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p310" block_type="bl-first">Develop strong verbal and written communication, interpersonal, and analytical skills.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p311" block_type="bl-mid">Seek leadership roles in other campus organizations.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p312" block_type="bl-last">Learn to work well on a team.</p></li>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-10" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-11" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_T01b.jpg"/>
</figure></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-21" type="unordered" block_type="orangebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p313" block_type="bl-first">Public Relations</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p314" block_type="bl-mid">Advertising</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p315" block_type="bl-mid">Marketing</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p316" block_type="bl-last">Creative Directing</p></li>
</list></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-22" type="unordered" block_type="orangebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p317" block_type="bl-first">Develop excellent writing and public-speaking skills.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p318" block_type="bl-mid">Serve as public relations officer of an organization.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p319" block_type="bl-last">Develop a portfolio of writing samples, ad campaigns, and other relevant work.</p></li>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-11" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-12" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_T01c.jpg"/>
</figure></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-23" type="unordered" block_type="greenbullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p320" block_type="bl-first">Writing</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p321" block_type="bl-mid">Editing</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p322" block_type="bl-mid">Copywriting</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p323" block_type="bl-mid">Publishing</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p324" block_type="bl-last">Broadcasting</p></li>
</list></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-24" type="unordered" block_type="greenbullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p325" block_type="bl-first">Take courses in journalism, broadcasting, public relations, and advertising.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p326" block_type="bl-mid">Develop excellent interpersonal, presentation, and research skills.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p327" block_type="bl-last">Work for campus or local newspaper, radio station, or television station.</p></li>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-12" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-13" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_T01d.jpg"/>
</figure></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-25" type="unordered" block_type="orangebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p328" block_type="bl-first">Community Affairs</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p329" block_type="bl-mid">Campaigning</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p330" block_type="bl-mid">Lobbying</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p331" block_type="bl-mid">Social Services</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p332" block_type="bl-mid">Prosecution</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p333" block_type="bl-mid">Defense</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p334" block_type="bl-last">Nonprofit or Public Interest</p></li>
</list></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-26" type="unordered" block_type="orangebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p335" block_type="bl-first">Develop strong research skills and attention to detail.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p336" block_type="bl-mid">Participate in debate or forensic team to hone communication skills.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p337" block_type="bl-last">Take courses in conflict management, and develop negotiation skills.</p></li>
</list></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-13" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-14" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_T01e.jpg"/>
</figure></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-27" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p338" block_type="bl-first">Teaching</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p339" block_type="bl-mid">Research</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p340" block_type="bl-mid">Information/Library Science</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p341" block_type="bl-last">Administration and Student Support Services</p></li>
</list></td>
<td><list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-28" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p342" block_type="bl-first">Develop strong interpersonal communication and public-speaking skills.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p343" block_type="bl-mid">Get involved in campus leadership roles in residence halls, student unions/activities, programming boards, orientation, admissions, etc.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p344" block_type="bl-last">Learn to work well with a variety of people.</p></li>
</list></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p60" block_type="fn"><sup>2</sup> <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-tab-1">Table 1.1</link> data from &#8220;What Can I Do with This Major?&#8221; retrieved from <link href="http://whatcanidowiththismajor.com/major/communication-studies/">http://whatcanidowiththismajor.com/major/communication-studies/</link></p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_15" block_type="page_start">15</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-5" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="16">
<section-metadata><section-title>Types of Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_16" block_type="page_start">16</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p61" block_type="txt">As the preceding history illustrates, communication is a diverse field with a rich past. Although many specific topics are currently being studied and taught (such as doctor-patient communication, information flow within organizations, and deception), the field as a whole can be divided into four broad types: mediated communication (<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link>), interpersonal communication (<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch09.xml">Chapters 9</link>&#8211;<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch10.xml">10</link>), small group communication (<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch11.xml">Chapters 11</link>&#8211;<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch12.xml">12</link>), and public communication (<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch13.xml">Chapters 13</link>&#8211;<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch17.xml">17</link>). Throughout this book, we explore the differences and connections between these types.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p62" block_type="txt"><termref term="Mediated communication">Mediated communication</termref> is separated (&#8220;mediated&#8221;) by some type of technological device. You use mediated communication when you make phone calls, tweet, send text messages or e-mails, use FaceTime or Skype, and post messages online. As you&#8217;ll see later in this book, mediated communication is best used to meet certain types of goals. For example, text messaging is fine for planning a meeting location for your study group (instrumental goal). However, you probably wouldn&#8217;t want to use texting to resolve a disagreement with your romantic partner (relationship goal).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p63" block_type="txt"><termref term="Interpersonal communication">Interpersonal communication</termref> is communication between two people in which the messages exchanged have a significant impact on the participants&#8217; thoughts, emotions, behaviors, and relationship. Through interpersonal communication, you build, maintain, and end bonds with your friends, family members, lovers, and other relationship partners.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p64" block_type="txt"><termref term="Small group communication">Small group communication</termref> involves three or more interdependent persons who share a common identity (such as membership on a team) and who communicate to achieve common goals or purposes. For example, a group might come together to complete a class project, organize a fund-raiser, or produce music. Small group communication involves unique challenges, such as the need to coordinate group members&#8217; responsibilities, build group unity, clarify expectations, and accommodate members&#8217; diverse communication styles.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p65" block_type="txt"><termref term="Public communication">Public communication</termref> is the process of preparing and delivering a message to an audience to achieve a specific purpose (also known as public speaking). An example of this would be a speech you will probably have to give for this class. (This may sound scary, but don&#8217;t worry&#8212;we have advice in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch15.xml">Chapter 15</link> to manage your anxiety.) You might also need to communicate publicly in other situations, such as giving a talk to a youth group or presenting a project idea to your coworkers by videoconference.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p66" block_type="txt">These four types of communication differ in terms of their main purpose, the number of people involved, and their nature (linear, interactive, or transactional). Yet they also are <em>connected</em> to one another&#8212;in history and in current practice. Specifically, in all four types, people use messages to generate meanings. In addition, all four types are affected by the communicators&#8217; view of themselves, perceptions of others, cultural background and listening skills, and use of verbal and nonverbal communication. (We will explore these areas together in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml">Chapters 2</link>, <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">4</link>, <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml">5</link>, <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch06.xml">6</link>, and <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch07.xml">7</link>.) In addition, you can use the four types of communication to pursue self-presentation, instrumental, and relationship goals.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_17" block_type="page_start">17</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p67" block_type="txt">Perhaps most important, the choices you make when using any type of communication strongly influence the outcomes you experience. When you make good choices, you&#8217;re more likely to get positive outcomes. When you make poor choices, negative outcomes often follow. What does it mean to make &#8220;good&#8221; choices and communicate &#8220;well&#8221;? We tackle that question in the next section.</p>
<box title="DOUBLE TAKE" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx3-1" block_type="bx3-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p68" block_type="bx-v3-tc"><strong>MEDIATED</strong> <image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-15" alt="image" src="images/and1.jpg"/> <strong>PUBLIC COMMUNICATION</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p69" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Whether you&#8217;re sending a text or making a speech, different types of communication are often connected. In addition to what is pointed out below, what connections can you make between the different types of communication you participate in each day?</strong></p>
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-untab-2" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-14" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-16" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_11_P06.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Klaus Vedfelt/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-17" alt="image" src="images/and.jpg"/></td>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-15" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-18" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_11_P07.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Hill Street Studios/Blend Images/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-3" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="18">
<section-metadata><section-title>Communication Competence</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_18" block_type="page_start">18</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p70" block_type="pul"><strong>Communication is a choice. How you choose to phrase your messages, exhibit facial expressions, and even approach a conflict is up to you. Each time you make such a choice, you have the opportunity to strive for competence. This can help you set the stage for success in your own life.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p71" block_type="txt-ni">Cesar Chavez transformed the lives of thousands by persuading powerful people to act on behalf of the poorest laborers in America.<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p72"><sup>3</sup></link> How? He mastered the art of <em>communication competence</em>: the ability to consistently interact with others in an appropriate, effective, and ethical fashion. A compelling public speaker, Chavez rallied migrant laborers to organize strikes protesting horrific work conditions in the fields, eventually leading to the creation of the United Farm Workers (UFW) organization. He was equally skilled at adapting his language to lawmakers, communicating the plight of farmworkers in poignant terms to those who controlled the laws governing them. Although landowners attacked him and his fellow workers with shotguns and dogs, he remained committed to ethical communication, never lashing back at those who subjected him and others to violence. His competence ultimately paid off with a profound outcome: new laws ensuring better working conditions and higher wages for field laborers.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p72" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p71"><sup>3</sup></link>All information regarding Cesar Chavez is excerpted from the California Department of Education (n.d.) and the County of Los Angeles Public Library (n.d.).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p73" block_type="txt">Chavez&#8217;s communication competence extended to his interpersonal communication as well. For example, after delivering a speech in Washington, D.C., Chavez spied UFW members who had been volunteering to help with the event. He veered toward them, even as his bodyguards tried to force him toward his car. Chavez shook the workers&#8217; hands, saying, &#8220;I noticed how you stayed here all day and worked so hard. It is because of you there is a movement. I may be the one who does the speaking, but it is you who make the movement what it is!&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p74" block_type="txt">Cesar Chavez received many honors, including the &#193;guila Azteca&#8212;the highest civilian award in Mexico&#8212;and the U.S. Presidential Medal of Freedom. His legacy is about justice, nonviolence, and help for the needy. It&#8217;s also proof that communication can bring about change.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p75" block_type="txt">Communication is the means through which you achieve your goals (Burleson, Metts, &#38; Kirch, 2000). But it is the <em>competence</em> of your communication that determines the <em>quality</em> of your outcomes. Competent communicators report higher levels of educational and professional achievement, more satisfaction with their relationships (including happier marriages), and better psychological and physical health (Spitzberg &#38; Cupach, 2002).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p76" block_type="txt">Throughout the book, we explore the knowledge and skills necessary for strengthening your competence in all types of communication. In this chapter, we lay the foundation for your learning by explaining how to achieve communication competence.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_19" block_type="page_start">19</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-16" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-19" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_P08.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>Cesar Chavez&#8217;s ability to adapt his language to connect with both migrant laborers and lawmakers was crucial for his success in the United Farm Workers organization. How does your manner of speaking change according to the person receiving your message?</strong></caption>
<asset_source>&#169; Jason Laure/The Image Works</asset_source>
</figure>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-6" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="19">
<section-metadata><section-title>Understanding Communication Competence</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p77" block_type="txt-ni"><termref term="Communication competence">Communication competence</termref> means consistently communicating in ways that are <em>appropriate</em> (your communication follows accepted norms), <em>effective</em> (your communication helps you achieve your goals), and <em>ethical</em> (your communication treats people fairly) (Spitzberg &#38; Cupach, 1984; Wiemann, 1977).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p78" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Appropriateness.</strong></phrase> <termref term="Appropriateness">Appropriateness</termref> is the degree to which your communication matches expectations regarding how people &#8220;should&#8221; communicate. In any setting, norms govern what people should and shouldn&#8217;t say, and how they should and shouldn&#8217;t act. For example, telling jokes or personal stories about your love life isn&#8217;t appropriate during a job interview, but it might be appropriate when you&#8217;re hanging out with close friends who know you and your sense of humor. Competent communicators understand when such norms exist and adapt their communication accordingly.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p79" block_type="txt">We judge how appropriate our communication is through <termref term="self-monitoring">self-monitoring</termref>: the process of observing our own communication and the norms of the situation in order to make appropriate communication choices. Some individuals closely monitor their own communication to ensure they&#8217;re acting in accordance with situational expectations (Giles &#38; Street, 1994). Known as <em>high self-monitors,</em> they prefer situations in which clear expectations exist regarding how they&#8217;re supposed to communicate, and they possess both the ability and desire to alter their behaviors to fit into any type of social situation (Oyamot, Fuglestad, &#38; Snyder, 2010). In contrast, <em>low self-monitors</em> don&#8217;t assess their own communication or the situation (Snyder, 1974). They prefer encounters in which they can &#8220;act like themselves&#8221; by expressing their values and beliefs, rather than abiding by norms (Oyamot et al., 2010). As a consequence, high self-monitors are often judged as more adaptive and skilled communicators than low self-monitors (Gangestad &#38; Snyder, 2000).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_20" block_type="page_start">20</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p80" block_type="txt">One of the most important choices you make related to appropriateness is when to use mobile devices and when to put them away. Certainly, cell phones and tablets allow us to quickly and efficiently connect with others. However, when you&#8217;re interacting with people face-to-face, the priority should be your conversation with them; if you prioritize your device over the person in front of you, you run the risk of being perceived as inappropriate. <em>This is not a casual choice</em>: research documents that simply having cell phones out on a table&#8212;but not using them&#8212;during face-to-face conversations significantly reduces perceptions of relationship quality, trust, and empathy, compared to having conversations with no phones present (Przybylski &#38; Weinstein, 2012). To avoid such negative judgments, put your mobile devices away at the beginning of the interaction.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p81" block_type="txt">Competent communicators also know that overemphasizing appropriateness can backfire. If you <em>always</em> adapt your communication to what others want, you may end up making poor choices. For example, you might give in to peer pressure (Burgoon, 1995). Think of a friend who always does what others want and never argues for his own desires. Is he a competent communicator? No, because he&#8217;ll probably seldom achieve goals that are important to him. What about the boss who tells employees that their work is fine even when it isn&#8217;t? Is she competent? No, because she&#8217;s withholding information her employees need to improve their job performance. Competence means striking a healthy balance between appropriateness and other important considerations, such as achievement of goals and the obligation to communicate honestly.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_21" block_type="page_start">21</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx5-2" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p82" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>When Piper Chapman began her one-year sentence at a women&#8217;s prison in <em>Orange Is the New Black</em>, her idea of appropriateness quickly changed as she assimilated to her new surroundings. How do you deal with situations in which what you deem as appropriate doesn&#8217;t line up with what&#8217;s occurring around you?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-17" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-20" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_P09.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Jessica Miglio/&#169; Netflix/courtesy Everett Collection</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p83" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Effectiveness.</strong></phrase> <termref term="Effectiveness">Effectiveness</termref> is the ability to use communication to accomplish the three types of goals discussed earlier (self-presentation, instrumental, and relationship). Sometimes you have to make trade-offs&#8212;prioritizing certain goals over others, even if you want to pursue all of them. For instance, to collaborate effectively with groups, you have to know when to stay on task and when to socialize. Say that you and several other students form an intramural softball team to compete in a campus league. At the first team meeting, you may want to come across as athletic, funny, and likable (self-presentation goal) and begin building friendships with others on the team (relationship goal). But if you don&#8217;t focus your communication during the meeting on creating a practice schedule (instrumental goal), the team won&#8217;t be ready to play its first game. <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch12.xml">Chapter 12</link> discusses how you can be an effective leader and communicator in such situations.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p84" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Ethics.</strong></phrase> <termref term="Ethics">Ethics</termref> is the set of moral principles that guide your behavior toward others (Spitzberg &#38; Cupach, 2002). At a minimum, you are ethically obligated to avoid intentionally hurting others through your communication. By this standard, communication that&#8217;s intended to erode a person&#8217;s self-esteem, that expresses intolerance or hatred, that intimidates or threatens others&#8217; physical well-being, or that expresses violence is unethical and therefore incompetent (Parks, 1994).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p85" block_type="txt">However, to be an ethical communicator, you must go beyond simply not doing harm. During every encounter&#8212;whether it&#8217;s interpersonal, a small group, or a public presentation&#8212;you need to treat others with respect and communicate with them honestly, kindly, and positively (Englehardt, 2001). As you&#8217;ll see in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link>, mediated communication presents unique challenges for ethical communication. To help you make ethical choices in all situations, consider the guidelines in the National Communication Association&#8217;s Credo for Ethical Communication (1999) in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-18">Figure 1.4</link>.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx4-4" block_type="bx4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p86" block_type="bx4-txt">Questions of right and wrong arise whenever people communicate. Ethical communication is fundamental to responsible thinking, decision making, and the development of relationships and communities within and across contexts, cultures, channels, and media. . . . Therefore we, the members of the National Communication Association, endorse and are committed to practicing the following principles of ethical communication:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-2" type="unordered" block_type="darkgreenbullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p87" block_type="bl-first">We advocate truthfulness, accuracy, honesty, and reason as essential to the integrity of communication.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p88" block_type="bl-mid">We endorse freedom of expression, diversity of perspective, and tolerance of dissent to achieve the informed and responsible decision making fundamental to a civil society.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p89" block_type="bl-last">We strive to understand and respect other communicators before evaluating and responding to their messages.</p></li>
</list>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-3" type="unordered" block_type="greenbullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p90" block_type="bl-first">We promote access to communication resources and opportunities as necessary to fulfill human potential and contribute to the well-being of families, communities, and society.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p91" block_type="bl-mid">We promote communication climates of caring and mutual understanding that respect the unique needs and characteristics of individual communicators.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p92" block_type="bl-last">We condemn communication that degrades individuals and humanity through distortion, intimidation, coercion, and violence, and through the expression of intolerance and hatred.</p></li>
</list>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-4" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p93" block_type="bl-first">We are committed to the courageous expression of personal convictions in pursuit of fairness and justice.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p94" block_type="bl-mid">We advocate sharing information, opinions, and feelings when facing significant choices while also respecting privacy and confidentiality.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p95" block_type="bl-last">We accept responsibility for the short- and long-term consequences for our own communication and expect the same of others.</p></li>
</list>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-18" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="1.4" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 1.4</strong></phrase> <strong>NCA CREDO FOR ETHICAL COMMUNICATION</strong></caption>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-21" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_F04.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Ecelop/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p96" block_type="txt">In communication situations that are simple, comfortable, and pleasant, it&#8217;s easy to behave appropriately, effectively, and ethically. True competence, however, develops when you consistently communicate competently across <em>all</em> situations that you face&#8212;even ones that are complex, uncertain, and unpleasant. A critical goal of this book is to equip you with the knowledge and skills you need to handle those more challenging communication situations. For example, the <link href="#choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx7-1">How to Communicate: Competent Conversations</link> feature on pages 24&#8211;25 asks you to adapt your understanding of communication competence to an unpleasant encounter.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-7" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="22">
<section-metadata><section-title>Putting Competence into Practice</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_22" block_type="page_start">22</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p97" block_type="txt">Competent communicators know how to translate their knowledge into <termref term="communication skills">communication skills</termref><strong>&#8212;</strong>repeatable goal-directed behaviors and behavioral patterns that they routinely practice (Spitzberg &#38; Cupach, 2002). Throughout this book, we provide you with skills you can use in all of the communication challenges you&#8217;ll face in life, so you can produce positive outcomes. To illustrate, consider two of the most important skills you&#8217;ll need in your communication toolbox: knowing when and how to use mediated communication competently, and knowing how to appropriately, effectively, and ethically interact with people whose cultural backgrounds differ from your own. As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link> discusses, using mediated communication competently means making wise choices regarding when to communicate online versus off, recognizing the three Ps of mediated communication (powerful, public, and permanent), and adapting your messages to ensure clarity. In a similar fashion, <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link> will teach you intercultural competence: how to appropriately adapt your communication to other communicators, effectively balance their goals with your own, and treat them with the same dignity and respect that you want for yourself.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_23" block_type="page_start">23</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p98" block_type="txt">Of course, to use your knowledge and skills to improve your communication, you must also be motivated to do so. If you do not believe your communication needs improvement, or if you believe that competence is unimportant or no more than simple common sense, your competence will be difficult, if not impossible, to refine. But if you are strongly motivated to improve your communication, you can master the knowledge and skills necessary to develop competence.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-4" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="23">
<section-metadata><section-title>Choices and Connections</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p99" block_type="pul"><strong>When you&#8217;re communicating, everything you say and do counts&#8212;and is connected to what comes after. There are no &#8220;take-backs&#8221; or do-overs. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s so important to know how to make good communication choices.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p100" block_type="txt-ni">In the 2014 film <em>Wild</em> (one of Steve&#8217;s fave films ever), Reese Witherspoon plays Cheryl Strayed, a woman who solo hikes the Pacific Coast Trail, trying to overcome the emotional devastation of her mother&#8217;s death. Throughout her journey, Cheryl recalls encounters with her mother, whose choice to adopt an always-cheery attitude was both inspirational and irritating: &#8220;What&#8217;s wrong with you?&#8221; &#8220;I&#8217;m happy&#8212;happy people sing!&#8221; &#8220;Why are you happy&#8212;we have <em>nothing</em>, Mom, <em>nothing</em>!&#8221; &#8220;We&#8217;re rich in love!&#8221; But toward the end of the film, Cheryl recalls <em>the</em> most memorable of her mother&#8217;s messages: &#8220;There is a sunrise and a sunset every day&#8212;you can <em>choose</em> to put yourself in the way of beauty!&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p101" block_type="txt">Each of us can experience a metaphorical sunrise or sunset every day of our lives&#8212;those brief moments of opportunity where we can watch something unfold before us that is breathtaking and awe-inspiring. It can happen when you&#8217;re having a casual conversation with a new acquaintance and you suddenly sense a special kinship between you&#8212;that a deep friendship may emerge. It can happen when you&#8217;re on a team and everything begins to click, and you have the thrill of knowing that you&#8217;re going to have an incredible, winning season. Or it can happen while speaking in front of prospective clients when you realize that your presentation is coming together exactly as you&#8217;d hoped&#8212;and that you&#8217;re going to acquire this account.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p102" block_type="txt">Though these sunrise/sunset examples are just brief moments, they illustrate two serious points that together form the central theme of this book. First, within each of these sunrise/sunset moments, what empowers us is <em>choice</em>. We have the <em>choice</em> to put ourselves in any situation, and the <em>choice</em> to communicate in whatever way we wish once we&#8217;re in it. And second, the choices that we make are powerfully connected to the outcomes that follow.</p>
<box title="HOW TO COMMUNICATE &#124; Video Skills" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx7-1" block_type="bx7-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_24" block_type="page_start">24</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p103" block_type="bx7-h"><strong>COMPETENT CONVERSATIONS</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p104" block_type="bx7-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-22" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> One way to improve your communication competence is by adapting your messages to others&#8217; behaviors. Learn how to navigate difficult conversations by going to LaunchPad at <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong> and completing the <strong>How to Communicate video scenario</strong> for <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml">Chapter 1</link> to practice your skills.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p105" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>CONSIDER THIS:</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p106" block_type="bx7-txt">Your professor assigns you to work with Jacob, your ex&#8217;s best friend. When you and your ex were dating, Jacob was friendly and supportive, and the two of you got along well. But the breakup was ugly, and you and Jacob haven&#8217;t talked since. As you meet with Jacob to brainstorm ideas, there&#8217;s obvious tension. You decide to break the ice and ask him how he&#8217;s doing. Jacob responds with an icy &#8220;Fine,&#8221; then says, &#8220;So, have you destroyed any new lives recently?&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p107" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>WHAT WOULD YOU DO?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p108" block_type="bx7-txt">The following advice illustrates how competent communication skills can keep the encounter productive. As you watch the video, consider how the dialogue reflects each element of competence. Then, test your knowledge of key skills, and create your own responses to the <strong>What if? video prompts</strong>.</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-19" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-23" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_HTC_1.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;I don&#8217;t think this is the right time or place to talk about this. If you want to hang out and talk after class, that would be fine.&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p110" block_type="mn3-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-24" alt="image" src="images/1.jpg"/> <strong>KEEP YOUR COMMUNICATION APPROPRIATE,</strong> given the setting, by not responding angrily to Jacob&#8217;s taunt and by offering an alternative encounter for personal discussion.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_25" block_type="page_start">25</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p111" block_type="mn3-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-25" alt="image" src="images/2.jpg"/> <strong>COMMUNICATE EFFECTIVELY</strong> by keeping your conversation focused on the task at hand and by encouraging Jacob to do the same.</p>
</box>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-20" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-26" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_HTC_2.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;I&#8217;ve got a couple of ideas for the project, but I&#8217;d like tohear your ideas first.&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p113" block_type="mn3-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-27" alt="image" src="images/3.jpg"/> <strong>MAKE YOUR MESSAGES ETHICAL</strong> by treating Jacob with kindness and respect, despite his rudeness.</p>
</box>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-21" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-28" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_01_HTC_2a.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;I know you&#8217;re really angry with me, and I admire you for that, because it shows you&#8217;re loyal and devoted to your friend. But I&#8217;m hoping we can put the past behind us for the sake of the project. What do you think?&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p115" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-29" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> WHAT IF? But what if things don&#8217;t work out as shown? Test your ability to adapt your communication by watching the What if? videos and planning a response for each situation.</strong></p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-5" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p116" block_type="nl-first">What would you say when Jacob attempts to end the encounter by saying, &#8220;I have no interest in talking to you&#8212;whether it&#8217;s now or later&#8221;?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p117" block_type="nl-last">How would you get Jacob&#8217;s focus off the past when he says, &#8220;Yeah, I can see why you&#8217;d want to leave the past behind. That&#8217;s what you do, isn&#8217;t it: destroy people, bail, and then say, &#8216;Can&#8217;t we leave the past behind?&#8217;&#8221;</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_26" block_type="page_start">26</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx5-3" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p118" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>In <em>Wild</em>, Cheryl (Reese Witherspoon) recalls her mother <em>choosing</em> to be happy, which serves as a reminder to Cheryl that she has the <em>choice</em> to end the downward spiral her life was on after her mother&#8217;s death. We are similarly empowered by choice when we communicate with others. Thinking back, how have some of your communication choices impacted the outcomes you experienced?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-fig-22" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-30" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_11_P10.jpg"/>
<asset_source>20TH CENTURY FOX/THE KOBAL COLLECTION</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-8" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="26">
<section-metadata><section-title>Communication Choices</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p119" block_type="txt-ni">How do your communication choices affect the outcomes you experience? Take something as simple as how you respond to an angry text message from a family member. If you fire back an equally hostile response, the situation escalates, and the two of you are now fighting. What&#8217;s more, the conflict will likely spread to other family members, as each person weighs in on what happened and takes sides in the battle. Think about what might happen if you respond competently instead. For example, you take the time to craft a message asking why the other person is upset, making sure to avoid sarcastic or accusatory responses. Then you calmly explain how you see the situation, reassuring him or her of your love and respect. These choices are far less likely to lead to a fight or involve others in the conflict.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p120" block_type="txt">The fact that your communication choices affect your outcomes means your communication is <em>irreversible</em>. When you post a message online, send a text or tweet, leave a voice-mail message, or express a thought out loud during a group meeting, you set in motion the series of outcomes that follow. Once you&#8217;ve communicated something, you can&#8217;t take it back. That&#8217;s why it&#8217;s important to think carefully before you communicate, asking yourself, &#8220;Is what I&#8217;m about to say going to lead to outcomes I want?&#8221; If the answer is no, then you&#8217;ll want to revise your message.</p>
<box title="MAKING COMMUNICATION CHOICES" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-bx2-1" block_type="bx2-v2-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_27" block_type="page_start">27</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p121" block_type="bx-v2-txt"><strong>TIME FOR PAYBACK?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p122" block_type="bx-v2-txt"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>1</strong></phrase> <strong>CONSIDER THE DILEMMA</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p123" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">You dated Riley for over a year. You were in love and thought the two of you might even get married someday. But last week you discovered that Riley had been cheating on you for the last two months. You were so furious and hurt that you broke it off, and you haven&#8217;t spoken with Riley since. Riley has been texting and e-mailing you, begging forgiveness, but you haven&#8217;t responded.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p124" block_type="bx2-txt">One night you&#8217;re studying with your roommate when you get a text from Riley. But instead of being another apology, it&#8217;s a request. Riley let you borrow a USB drive last week, which apparently contains all of Riley&#8217;s notes for an important project, and Riley&#8217;s hard drive just crashed&#8212;making the USB drive the only copy of these materials. Riley wants to come by and get it. You&#8217;re just about to text &#8220;OK&#8221; when your roommate interjects, &#8220;Are you insane!? After what Riley did to you? You should throw it away and tell Riley you can&#8217;t find it.&#8221; The more you think about it, the more the idea appeals to you. You&#8217;re still angry and sad, and you want to make Riley suffer! This would be a little payback. Just then, Riley texts you again, &#8220;Do u have my drive? I really need it. Please text me back.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p125" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>2</strong></phrase> <strong>CONNECT THE RESEARCH</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p126" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">There&#8217;s no question that betrayal in a close relationship is one of the worst experiences you can have. Unfortunately, some people respond to betrayal by seeking revenge. Revenge comes in many forms, most of which are as unethical and destructive as the behavior triggering the vengeance. Canadian researchers Susan Boon, Vicki Deveau, and Alishia Alibhai (2009) found that vengeful partners commonly exact their revenge online, by posting negative photos of their lovers on Facebook or blogging about their lovers&#8217; deficient sexual attributes. In extreme cases, vengeance may involve sabotaging partners at work so that they get fired, or de-enrolling them from their college or university.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p127" block_type="bx2-txt">Partners who seek revenge report a host of motives for doing so, but the most common involve a desire to &#8220;have power over a partner&#8221; and &#8220;to make the partner suffer&#8221; (Boon et al., 2009). People seeking revenge often presume they will feel better once &#8220;justice has been served.&#8221; However, research by communication scholar Stephen Yoshimura (2007) examining the aftermath of revenge suggests that people not only continue to feel angry about the betrayal but also feel remorseful and anxious about repercussions from their vengeful acts. So although you may be tempted to seek vengeance in the wake of a betrayal, keep this in mind: not only is such behavior unethical (two wrongs do not make a right), but you may suffer even more if you behave in this way.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p128" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>3</strong></phrase> <strong>COMMUNICATE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p129" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">Before making a communication choice, consider the facts of the situation, and think about the revenge research. Also, reflect on what you&#8217;ve learned so far about the connections between communication choices and outcomes (pp. 26&#8211;28), ethics (p. 21), and communication competence (pp. 19&#8211;21). Then answer these questions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-6" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p130" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">Is it ethical to throw away the USB drive and tell Riley you can&#8217;t find it?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p131" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">If you follow your roommate&#8217;s suggestion, what will be the outcomes? Will you feel better? Will your relationship with Riley be improved? What about the long-term consequences of your choice?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p132" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">What are you going to text Riley?</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_28" block_type="page_start">28</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p133" block_type="mn-v6-h"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-31" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p134" block_type="txt">Of course, communication (by definition) involves interaction with others, and the choices <em>they</em> make influence your outcomes as well. But you can&#8217;t control how others choose to behave toward you&#8212;only how you behave toward them. Consequently, the best&#8212;and only&#8212;path you have for improving your outcomes is to take control of your communication and improve your choices. When you recognize that your communication is a choice and then elect to communicate appropriately, effectively, and ethically, you&#8217;ll have done all that you can to foster satisfying communication outcomes in your personal and professional lives. This book shows you how to make competent communication choices in a wide range of situations&#8212;even when others do not.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec2-9" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="28">
<section-metadata><section-title>Communication Connections</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p135" block_type="txt-ni">In addition to recognizing the link between communication choices and outcomes, your communication competence will be boosted by learning the connections that exist between the different types of communication. Yes, communicating face-to-face is different from interacting online, just as conversing within a group is different from presenting in front of an audience. Yet many similar skills connect them. Consider, for example, what it means to be a good listener. It matters little whether you&#8217;re listening to an audience member&#8217;s question following a presentation or Skyping with your sister who is overseas. The characteristics that constitute being a good listener (discussed in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml">Chapter 7</link>) transcend communication type and context. Becoming a competent communicator means understanding the connections between different forms of communication, as well as the skills that are unique to each.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p136" block_type="txt">Throughout this book, we will provide you with numerous examples illustrating the connections between different communication types. For instance, you&#8217;ll see how determining your communication purpose is important whether you&#8217;re planning a group meeting or preparing a speech, realize how the skills used for managing interpersonal conflict can help when problems arise in teams, and discover that sharing appropriate and relevant information about yourself (known as <em>self-disclosure</em>) is important for both creating small group bonds and establishing rapport with an audience during a speech.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p137" block_type="txt">But perhaps even more important than these specific points of connection is the fact that <em>your communication and your communication skills connect you to other human beings</em>. Communication is your primary vehicle for exchanging meaning, achieving goals, connecting with others emotionally, and building personal and professional relationships with others.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p138" block_type="txt">The importance of communication for connecting you to others makes it essential that you base your communication choices on the best knowledge you have. No one would consider making a decision about a college major, a future career, or major purchases without first gathering the most trustworthy information available. Communication should be no different. That&#8217;s where this book&#8212;and the class you&#8217;re taking&#8212;come in. We (your authors: Steve and Joe) will provide you with the best research, theory, and practical skills training that the field of communication has to offer. As you absorb this knowledge and start applying these skills in your own life, you&#8217;ll position yourself to make the best communication choices. As a result, you&#8217;ll boost the odds of creating positive outcomes in your personal and professional lives, including healthy and satisfying connections with others.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_29" block_type="page_start">29</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-5" block_type="cr-h" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="30">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER 1 REVIEW</section-title></section-metadata>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-6" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="30">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER RECAP</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_30" block_type="page_start">30</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-7" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p139" block_type="cr-bl-v0"><termref term="Communication">Communication</termref> is the process through which people use <strong>messages</strong> to generate meanings within and across <strong>contexts</strong>, cultures, <strong>channels</strong>, and <strong>media</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p140" block_type="cr-bl-v0">You can use communication to help you achieve three types of goals: <termref term="self-presentation">self-presentation</termref>, <termref term="instrumental">instrumental</termref>, and <termref term="relationship">relationship</termref>. Various <em>communication models</em> (<termref term="linear">linear</termref>, <termref term="interactive">interactive</termref>, and <termref term="transactional">transactional</termref>) help you understand how this communication takes place.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p141" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Although the field of communication began with the study of <termref term="rhetoric">rhetoric</termref> in ancient Greece, today it is composed of four main types: <termref term="mediated">mediated</termref>, <termref term="interpersonal">interpersonal</termref>, <termref term="small group">small group</termref>, and <termref term="public communication">public communication</termref>.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p142" block_type="cr-bl-v0"><termref term="Communication competence">Communication competence</termref> determines the quality of your communication and is a combination of <termref term="appropriateness">appropriateness</termref>, <termref term="effectiveness">effectiveness</termref>, and <termref term="ethics">ethics</termref>.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p143" block_type="cr-bl-v0">There are two key axioms to keep in mind when building your communication skills: the communication choices you make are connected to the outcomes that follow, and different types of communication are connected to each other in fundamental ways.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p144" block_type="cr-txt-ni"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-32" alt="image" src="images/launchpad.jpg"/> LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> offers unique video scenarios and encourages self-assessment through adaptive quizzing. Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong> to get access.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p145" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-33" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> LearningCurve adaptive quizzes</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p146" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-34" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> How to Communicate video scenarios</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p147" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-35" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> Video clips that illustrate key concepts</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-7" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="30">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p148" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p27">Communication, p. 5</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p149" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p29">Message, p. 6</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p150" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p29">Interaction, p. 6</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p151" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p30">Contexts, p. 6</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p152" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p31"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-36" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Channel, p. 6</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p153" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p32">Media, p. 6</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p154" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p34">Self-presentation goals, p. 6</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p155" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p35">Instrumental goals, p. 7</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p156" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p36">Relationship goals, p. 7</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p157" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p40"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-37" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Linear communication model, p. 7</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p158" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p40">Sender, p. 8</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p159" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p40">Receiver, p. 8</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p160" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p40"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-38" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Noise, p. 8</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p161" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p42">Interactive communication model, p. 9</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p162" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p42">Feedback, p. 9</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p163" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p42">Fields of experience, p. 9</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p164" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p45"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-39" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Transactional communication model, p. 10</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p165" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p54">Rhetoric, p. 13</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p166" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p62">Mediated communication, p. 16</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p167" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p63">Interpersonal communication, p. 16</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p168" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p63">Small group communication, p. 16</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p169" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p65">Public communication, p. 16</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p170" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p77">Communication competence, p. 19</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p171" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p78">Appropriateness, p. 19</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p172" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p79">Self-monitoring, p. 19</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p173" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p83">Effectiveness, p. 21</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p174" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p84">Ethics, p. 21</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p175" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch1-p97">Communication skills, p. 22</link></p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-8" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="31">
<section-metadata><section-title>POP QUIZ</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_31" block_type="page_start">31</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p176" block_type="cr-wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-img-40" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> Looking for more review questions? <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you master key concepts from this chapter. Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-question-1" number="1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p177" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Which of the following is <em>not</em> one of the five features that define communication?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-8" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p178" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Contexts</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p179" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Ethics</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p180" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Channel</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p181" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Media</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-question-2" number="2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p182" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">If you convince your sister to lend you her car by describing your clean driving record and devotion to speed limits, you are accomplishing what type of goal?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p183" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Rhetorical</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p184" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Relationship</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p185" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Self-presentation</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p186" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Instrumental</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-question-3" number="3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p187" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">According to the &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; model, there aren&#8217;t senders or receivers; instead, participants constantly exchange verbal and nonverbal messages and feedback to collaboratively create meaning.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p188" block_type="cr-ll-v1">transactional</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p189" block_type="cr-ll-v1">linear</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p190" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">interactive</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p191" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">instrumental</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-question-4" number="4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p192" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Which feature of competent communication requires you to treat others with respect and communicate with them honestly, kindly, and positively?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-11" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p193" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Effectiveness</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p194" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Appropriateness</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p195" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Ethics</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p196" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Connections</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-question-5" number="5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p197" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Repeatable goal-directed behaviors and behavioral patterns that you routinely practice and that reflect knowledge of competent communication are known as &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-12" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p198" block_type="cr-ll-v1">communication skills</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p199" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">communication competence</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p200" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">fields of experience</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p201" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">feedback</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-sec1-9" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch1" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="31">
<section-metadata><section-title>ACTIVITIES</section-title></section-metadata>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-list-13" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p202" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Tracking Your Media Meter</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-exp4-1" block_type="mn4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p203" block_type="cr-wl-txt">For more activities, visit LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> at <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p204" block_type="cr-txt">As a way to compare how you use different communication media, create a log of your communication patterns across various media for just one day. Track how often you text, tweet, e-mail, post, call, talk face-to-face, and so on. For each communication encounter, include a brief note regarding what it was about. Then, analyze your log based on the following questions: Which communication media did you use most often? Why? What guided your decision in choosing certain media over others? Do certain media seem more intimate or less personal than others? Were some more enjoyable or more demanding? How do you think your choice of communication media influenced the outcomes you experienced?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p205" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Exploring Competent Communication</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch1-p206" block_type="cr-txt">Call to mind a recent communication encounter that you found difficult or problematic. This could be a conflict, an awkward interaction, or an instance in which you regretted what you said or someone misinterpreted you. With a partner, recall exactly what you said and what happened as a result. Now, revisit the components of competence discussed on pages 19&#8211;21. What aspects of your communication were appropriate, effective, or ethical? Which were not? What could you have done to be more competent in the situation? How would that have changed the outcomes you experienced? What does this tell you about the benefits or limits of competent communication?</p></li>
</list>
</section>
</chapter>
</manuscript>