<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<manuscript xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" manuscript-id="02" name="" title="MCC_Chapter_02_DJHrev" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/digfir_manuscript.xsd">
<chapter number="2" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-chapter-2" title="2: Self and Perception" start-numbering-at="2" numbered="true">
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="32">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_32" block_type="page_start">32</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p1" block_type="chapter_number">2</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p2" block_type="chapter_title">Self and Perception</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p3" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">F</phrase>or much of her career she has been number one in the world. She has 21 Grand Slam titles and is far from finished. She has been known to taunt opponents after beating them&#8212;condescendingly patting them on the back&#8212;and defends such behaviors by saying, &#8220;I&#8217;m there to do a job, not make friends.&#8221; But she&#8217;s also a woman who has struggled with negative body image and overcome the prejudiced perception of those who wanted nothing more than for her to quit.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p4" block_type="co-txt">Serena Williams grew up in Compton, California, the area of Los Angeles made famous by rappers for its poverty and violence. Rather than compete in the junior tennis tournaments, Williams&#8217;s father, Richard, trained Serena and her sister Venus in isolation&#8212;having them work on tennis fundamentals and practice by hitting against men. When she turned pro at age 14, Serena Williams had power few had ever seen. Now in her 30s, she still hits serves topping triple digits.<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p5"><sup>1</sup></link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p5" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p4"><sup>1</sup></link>Opener adapted from Rodrick (2013).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p6" block_type="co-txt">Despite her physical strength, Williams has struggled with negative self-image throughout her life, a challenge made worse by constantly comparing herself against others. &#8220;It wasn&#8217;t easy growing up,&#8221; she notes, &#8220;because I was thicker. Most women athletes are thin. I didn&#8217;t really know how to deal with it. I had to come to terms with loving myself&#8221; (Bronner, 2015).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p7" block_type="co-txt">Williams also overcame the prejudice of people who perceived her as not having the right to play. In 2001, she won the prestigious Indian Wells tournament. During the trophy ceremony, many in the mostly white crowd booed and shouted racial slurs. She cried in the locker room after. &#8220;I felt I had lost the biggest game ever&#8212;the fight for equality.&#8221; Serena boycotted the tournament for fourteen years, but then decided to return in 2015. Forced to drop out because of an injury, she found herself at a gas station at Indian Wells. &#8220;A parent came up to me and said, &#8216;my kid loves you.&#8217; His kid was 11-years-old. I thought it was great. This is a little person who has a life and goes to school and has friends and he&#8217;s a fan. That&#8217;s when I knew I had made the right decision to return&#8221; (Bronner, 2015).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_33" block_type="page_start">33</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-1" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-1" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>John Angelillo/UPI/Landov</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_34" block_type="page_start">34</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p8" block_type="co-h"><strong>CHAPTER OUTLINE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p9" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-1"><strong>The Nature of Self</strong> 34</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p10" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-2"><strong>Presenting Your Self</strong> 41</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p11" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-3"><strong>Perceiving Others</strong> 43</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p12" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-4"><strong>Forming Impressions</strong> 49</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p13" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-5"><strong>Improving Your Perception</strong> 52</link></p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p14" block_type="co-txt">Serena Williams is far and away the most dominant player in tennis today. When asked whether she thinks Williams is the best player <em>ever</em>, Billie Jean King&#8212;one of the greatest tennis players herself&#8212;said simply, &#8220;Yes. I think we all do&#8221; (Ledbetter, 2015). In 2015, Williams made the &#8220;Daring&#8221; list in <em>Harper&#8217;s Bazaar</em> magazine, celebrating &#8220;incredible risk-taking, trailblazing women.&#8221; But beneath all the fierceness, complexity, and determination, Williams&#8217;s strength comes from her capacity for critical self-reflection. &#8220;Physically you need to be great, emotionally you need to be stable and I need to have a good connection with my spirituality. You can be down in life, but you can overcome things based on the way you think and how you set your frame of mind&#8221; (Bronner, 2015).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p15" block_type="co-txt">Few (if any!) of us have the athletic prowess of Serena Williams. But we share with her the ability to critically look within ourselves, see what hampers us, and change our mindsets in ways that optimize our potential. We also have the ability to understand how others perceive us, how we see them, and how these impressions shape our behaviors. By combining these two elements&#8212;critical self-reflection and an understanding of perception&#8212;you set the stage for successful communication in your own life. In this chapter, you&#8217;ll learn:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p16" block_type="bl-v0-f">The nature of self and its impact on communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p17" block_type="bl-v0-mid">How you present yourself to others, online and off</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p18" block_type="bl-v0-mid">The perception process and common errors made in it</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p19" block_type="bl-v0-mid">Ways to form impressions of others</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p20" block_type="bl-v0-mid">The importance of perception-checking and empathy</p></li>
</list>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-1" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="34">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Nature of Self</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p21" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-2" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <strong><link href="http://macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p22" block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>Your &#8220;self&#8221; isn&#8217;t just one thing but many: who you think you are as a person; what your values, attitudes, and beliefs are; and how you feel about your self-worth. Because all of these factors influence how you communicate, the first step to improving your communication is to understand your self.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p23" block_type="txt-ni">Who are you? You may answer this question by describing your personality&#8212;funny, friendly, or intense&#8212;or perhaps by explaining what you do: musician, athlete, or techie. You may even identify the various roles you play: &#8220;I&#8217;m Grace&#8217;s daughter,&#8221; &#8220;I&#8217;m a nursing student,&#8221; or &#8220;I&#8217;m the fry cook at Randy&#8217;s Grill.&#8221; Serena Williams sees herself as &#8220;tennis player.&#8221; As she described in a 2015 <em>Harper&#8217;s Bazaar</em> interview, &#8220;Some people are born to do certain things, and I think I was born to do tennis.&#8221; But who you are&#8212;your <em>self&#8212;</em>isn&#8217;t a single thing that can be captured in a simple statement. Instead, the <termref term="self">self</termref> is an evolving blend of three components: self-awareness, self-concept, and self-esteem. Your self shapes how you communicate, whether online or off, with friends or in groups, and even before audiences.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-1" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="35">
<section-metadata><section-title>Self-Awareness</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_35" block_type="page_start">35</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p24" block_type="txt-ni"><termref term="Self-awareness">Self-awareness</termref> is the ability to view yourself as a unique person, distinct from your surrounding environment, and to reflect on your thoughts, feelings, and behaviors&#8212;in short, asking yourself, &#8220;Who am I?&#8221; (Rochat, 2003).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p25" block_type="txt">But self-awareness isn&#8217;t only about inward analysis. You also look outward, to others, and compare yourself to them. Through <termref term="social comparison">social comparison</termref>, you assign meaning to others&#8217; behaviors and then compare their behaviors against your own. Think of times you&#8217;ve wondered about your own speaking abilities after seeing a classmate deliver a stellar presentation, or pondered your interpersonal skills after watching a sibling comfort a friend. When you stack up favorably against people you admire, you think well of yourself (&#8220;I&#8217;m as fast as the runner who broke the school record last year!&#8221;). When you don&#8217;t compare favorably, you think less of yourself (&#8220;Why can&#8217;t I be as funny as my brother?&#8221;). This was the heart of Serena Williams&#8217;s struggle with her own body image: the fact that she constantly compared herself to her sister Venus, whom she deeply admired. As she describes, &#8220;Especially growing up with Venus, who&#8217;s so tall and slim and model-like, and me, I&#8217;m thick and hips and everything!&#8221; (Rodrick, 2013).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p26" block_type="txt">When communicating, you are always self-aware, constantly considering your thoughts, feelings, and behaviors. But to improve your communication, you must routinely practice <termref term="critical self-reflection">critical self-reflection</termref>, a special kind of self-awareness that focuses on evaluating and improving your communication. To engage in critical self-reflection, consider these five questions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-2" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p27" block_type="nl-f">What am I thinking and feeling?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p28" block_type="nl-m">Why am I thinking and feeling this way?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p29" block_type="nl-m">How am I communicating?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p30" block_type="nl-m">How are my inner thoughts and feelings affecting my communication?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p31" block_type="nl-l">How can I improve my thoughts, feelings, and communication?</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p32" block_type="txt">The goal of critical self-reflection is to enhance your communication. By routinely practicing critical self-reflection when faced with challenging situations, you will achieve a deeper understanding of the factors that influence your communication choices, allowing you to make better decisions and achieve improved outcomes as a result. For instance, say your brother discloses symptoms of a serious medical condition to you. But when you tell him to see the doctor, he laughingly dismisses your suggestion. You feel your anger rise, and you want to shout that he never listens and he&#8217;s a stubborn fool! If in such situations you&#8217;re able to critically reflect on your thoughts, feelings, and behaviors, you&#8217;ll be more likely to adapt your communication in ways that bring about desired outcomes. In this situation, you might realize, &#8220;I&#8217;m angry at his response because I&#8217;m <em>worried</em> about him and want him to be OK.&#8221; This realization would lead you to say, &#8220;I&#8217;m sorry; it&#8217;s just that I love you very much and am concerned. How about <em>I</em> call and make the appointment for you, and we can drive over together? What days and times work best for you?&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_36" block_type="page_start">36</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-2" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="36">
<section-metadata><section-title>Self-Concept</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p33" block_type="txt-ni">If self-awareness asks the question, &#8220;Who am I?&#8221; <termref term="self-concept">self-concept</termref> is the answer&#8212;that is, your overall assessment of who you are (&#8220;I&#8217;m a &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; person&#8221;). Your self-concept is based on the beliefs, attitudes, and values you have about yourself. <em>Beliefs</em> are convictions that certain things are true (&#8220;I&#8217;m a caring person&#8221;). <em>Attitudes</em> are evaluations (&#8220;I&#8217;m satisfied with my fitness level&#8221;). <em>Values</em> are enduring principles that guide your behaviors (&#8220;I think it&#8217;s morally wrong to lie&#8221;). Your beliefs, attitudes, and values are often intertwined. For example, if you think that communicating honestly is important (value), you likely also view yourself as an honest person (belief) and evaluate your honest communication positively (attitude). Understanding your beliefs, attitudes, and values and how they may differ from those of others helps you adapt your communication to anyone with whom you are interacting.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p34" block_type="txt">Early in life, the people who matter most to you&#8212;parents, siblings, teachers&#8212;help define your self-concept. Their reactions to you serve as a type of mirror in which you begin to see yourself as others see you (Cooley, 1902). For example, when Steve was young, his folks routinely emphasized his musical ability, so he came to think of himself as a musician. In a similar fashion, Joe&#8217;s parents constantly praised his academic achievements, causing Joe to see himself as a scholar.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p35" block_type="txt">As you age, the range of people who help shape and maintain your self-concept broadens to include friends, lovers, and coworkers. In fact, according to <termref term="Self-Verification Theory">Self-Verification Theory</termref> (Swann, Chang-Schneider, &#38; Angulo, 2007), you often choose your relational partners based on how well they support your self-concept. If you see yourself as an aspiring anime artist, you&#8217;ll probably choose friends, dating partners, and even roommates who support and reinforce this view&#8212;for instance, by praising your work (Swann &#38; Pelham, 2002). This holds true even for negative self-concepts: if you think you&#8217;re shallow or obsessive, you&#8217;ll likely be drawn to people who support this view (Swann, Hixon, &#38; De La Ronde, 1992).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p36" block_type="txt">Your self-concept often leads to <termref term="self-fulfilling prophecies">self-fulfilling prophecies</termref>, predictions you make about interactions that cause you to communicate in ways that make those predictions come true. Say your boss assigns you to a new team whose members strike you as especially creative and intelligent. If you think you&#8217;re not as talented as they are, you may predict that they&#8217;ll ignore your contributions to group discussions. As a result of this prediction, you remain quiet during the first team meeting. The other group members interpret your silence as a desire not to contribute and begin excluding you from the discussion. Later, you tell yourself, &#8220;See! I knew they wouldn&#8217;t want my input!&#8221; But if you saw yourself as creative and smart, you might predict that the team would welcome your contributions. You would then offer your ideas confidently, and the others would likely make a point of including you in discussions.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx4-1" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-2" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="2.1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 2.1</strong></phrase> <strong>SELF-CONCEPT ROAD MAP</strong></caption>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-3" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_02_F01.jpg"/>
<caption>Developing your self-concept is like a road trip&#8212;it takes place over time and is shaped by the people you meet and the experiences you have along the way.</caption>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-3" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="37">
<section-metadata><section-title>Self-Esteem</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_37" block_type="page_start">37</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p37" block_type="txt-ni"><termref term="Self-esteem">Self-esteem</termref> is the overall value you assign to yourself. Whereas self-awareness asks, &#8220;Who am I?&#8221; and self-concept is the answer to that question, self-esteem is the follow-up query, &#8220;Given who I am, what&#8217;s my evaluation of my worth?&#8221; Self-esteem strongly shapes your communication, relationships, and general outlook on life. People with high self-esteem report greater life satisfaction, communicate more positively with others, and experience more happiness in their relationships than do people with low self-esteem (Fox, 1997). They also show greater leadership ability, athleticism, and academic performance (Fox, 1992).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_38" block_type="page_start">38</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p38" block_type="txt">According to <termref term="Self-Discrepancy Theory">Self-Discrepancy Theory</termref>, your self-esteem is determined by how you compare to two mental standards (Higgins, 1987). The first standard is your <em>ideal self</em>&#8212;all the qualities (mental, physical, emotional, material, spiritual) you want to possess. The second standard is your <em>ought self</em>&#8212;the person you think others want you to be. Ought self stems from expectations of your family, friends, colleagues, and romantic partners, plus the culture you grow up in. You experience high self-esteem when your self-concept matches your ideal and ought selves (&#8220;I&#8217;m the kind of person I want to be&#8221; and &#8220;I&#8217;m the kind of person others wish me to be&#8221;). By contrast, you may suffer low self-esteem if your self-concept is inferior to your ideal and ought selves. You can work on improving your self-esteem by following these steps:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-3" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p39" block_type="nl-f"><em>Assess your self-esteem</em>. List the beliefs, attitudes, and values that make up your self-concept. Review the list, and determine whether you view yourself positively or negatively.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p40" block_type="nl-m"><em>Analyze your ideal self</em>. Who do you wish you were? If this ideal self is attainable, how could you become this person?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p41" block_type="nl-m"><em>Analyze your ought self</em>. Who do others want you to be? What would you have to do to become this person?</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_39" block_type="page_start">39</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p42" block_type="nl-m"><em>Revisit and redefine your standards</em>. If your ideal and ought selves are realistic and reachable, move to step 5. If they&#8217;re not (e.g., you&#8217;d love to be a multimillionaire by age 20, but it&#8217;s not likely you&#8217;ll get there), redefine your standards so that they are realistic and reachable. Frame your new standards as a list of goals.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p43" block_type="nl-l"><em>Create an action plan</em>. List the actions necessary to reach your ideal and ought selves. Establish a realistic time line&#8212;perhaps several months or years. Then carry out this action plan, checking your progress as you go.</p></li>
</list>
<box title="DOUBLE TAKE" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx3-1" block_type="bx3-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p44" block_type="bx-v3-tc"><strong>IDEAL <image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-4" alt="image" src="images/VS1.jpg"/> OUGHT SELF</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p45" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Your self-esteem is determined by how closely your ideal and ought selves align. In which situation do you think the student&#8217;s ideal and ought selves are more closely matched? Why?</strong></p>
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-untab-1" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-3" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-5" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Blend Images/VEER/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-6" alt="image" src="images/VS.jpg"/></td>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-5" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-7" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P03.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Kevin C. Cox/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure></td></tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-4" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="39">
<section-metadata><section-title>Culture, Gender, and Self</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p46" block_type="txt-ni">Engaging in critical self-reflection, pondering your self-concept, and assessing your self-esteem likely aren&#8217;t new activities. After all, many people spend time looking inward to get a better sense of their selves. What&#8217;s more, your self seems to be natural and innate: you were born a certain kind of person, and that&#8217;s just who you are. But without even realizing it, how you think about your self&#8212;and how you communicate that self to others&#8212;are shaped by powerful outside forces. Two of the most influential outside forces are culture and gender.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p47" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Culture and Self.</strong></phrase> In this text, we define <termref term="culture">culture</termref> broadly and inclusively, as an established, coherent set of beliefs, attitudes, values, and practices shared by a large group of people (Keesing, 1974). Culture includes many types of large-group influences, such as nationality, ethnicity, religion, gender, sexual orientation, physical abilities, and age. You learn your culture from parents, teachers, religious leaders, peers, and the mass media (Gudykunst &#38; Kim, 2003).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p48" block_type="txt">Culture influences your communication in many ways, as <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link> discusses in detail. But when it comes to your view of self, whether you grew up in an individualistic or collectivistic culture is highly influential. If you were raised in an <termref term="individualistic culture">individualistic culture</termref>, you likely learned that individual goals matter more than group goals. People in individualistic cultures are encouraged to focus on themselves and their immediate family (Hofstede, 1998), and individual achievement is praised as the highest good. Countries with individualistic cultures include the United States, New Zealand, and Sweden (Hofstede, 2001).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p49" block_type="txt">If you were raised in a <termref term="collectivistic culture">collectivistic culture</termref>, you were probably taught the importance of belonging to groups that look after you in exchange for your loyalty (Hofstede, 2001). In collectivistic cultures, the goals, needs, and views of the group matter more than those of individuals, and the highest good is cooperation with others. For example, in China&#8212;a country with a collectivistic culture&#8212;there is no direct translation for the concept of &#8220;doing your own thing&#8221; (Hofstede, 2001). Other collectivistic cultures include Guatemala, Pakistan, and Taiwan.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p50" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Gender and Self.</strong></phrase> <termref term="Gender">Gender</termref> is the set of social, psychological, and cultural attributes that characterize a person as male or female (Canary, Emmers-Sommer, &#38; Faulkner, 1997). Your concept of gender forms over time through interactions with others. Thus, it&#8217;s distinct from the biological sex organs you are born with, which distinguish you anatomically as male or female. As an example of the distinction between gender and sex, <termref term="transgender persons">transgender persons</termref> possess a strong sense of gendered self-identity (male/female) that doesn&#8217;t correspond to the biological sex they were born with. Immediately after birth, you begin a lifelong process of gender socialization, in which societal norms define and assign appropriate behavior for each gender. Within current American culture, for example, many girls are taught that the most important aspects of self include compassion and sensitivity to one&#8217;s own and others&#8217; emotions (Lippa, 2002). Many boys are taught that the most important aspects of self are assertiveness, competitiveness, and independence. As a result, women and men within the culture form very different views of self (Cross &#38; Madson, 1997). Women tend to see themselves as connected to others; men, as separate from others.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_40" block_type="page_start">40</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx5-1" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p51" block_type="bx-v1-txt"><strong>In 2015, Olympic athlete Caitlyn Jenner publicly announced her new identity on <em>20/20</em> with Diane Sawyer and, a few months later, in a cover story for <em>Vanity Fair</em>. Her television documentary, <em>I Am Cait</em>, showed audiences her process of reinventing relationships with friends and family and discovering her new status as a role model for the transgender community. While her publicity mobilized national conversations about gender dysphoria and transgender rights, Caitlyn has been criticized for not being able to understand the struggle of trans men and women who do not share her race or celebrity status.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-6" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-8" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P04.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Larry Busacca/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-2" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="41">
<section-metadata><section-title>Presenting Your Self</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_41" block_type="page_start">41</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p52" block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>Every time you communicate with others, you present a version of your self to them. Sometimes this represents who you really are; other times you may hide your true self. In either case, the self you present is the &#8220;you&#8221; people know. If you want people to see you in a certain way, it&#8217;s essential to learn how to present your self skillfully.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p53" block_type="txt-ni">Anne Burrell is a rock star in the world of chefs. Easily identifiable from her shock of white-blond hair, charisma, humor, and quirkiness, she draws millions of viewers to her Food Network shows <em>Secrets of a Restaurant Chef</em> and <em>Worst Cooks in America</em>. But in May 2012, Anne&#8217;s image was challenged when writer and television personality Ted Allen outed her as a lesbian. During an interview on Sirius XM radio, host Romaine Patterson joked to Allen about Burrell, saying, &#8220;I have the biggest crush on her . . . whether or not she&#8217;s a lesbian, I don&#8217;t care.&#8221; Allen responded, &#8220;I&#8217;m not going to put a label on Anne, but she is dating a woman right now. You&#8217;ve got some competition.&#8221; Afterwards, many fans expressed surprise, noting that Burrell had never presented herself publicly as a lesbian. But Burrell herself was quick to embrace the disclosure, releasing a statement confirming her sexual orientation and noting that she is in a committed relationship with a woman. Food Network executives supported her &#8220;new&#8221; self-presentation as well, commenting, &#8220;We&#8217;re always looking to broaden the diversity of our hosts, and we work hard to find talent that has the expertise, charisma, and broad appeal necessary to work on our air&#8221; (Michelson, 2011).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_42" block_type="page_start">42</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx5-2" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p54" block_type="bx-v1-txt"><strong>When celebrity chef Anne Burrell was publicly outed, she had to make a decision about how to reconcile her public and private selves. Are there areas of your private self you would need to reconcile if they became public? How would you manage that?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-7" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-9" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P05.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Angela Pham/BFAnyc/Sipa USA/Newscom</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p55" block_type="txt">In addition to your <em>private self</em>&#8212;the combination of your self-awareness, self-concept, and self-esteem&#8212;you also have a <em>public self</em>: the self you present to others (Fenigstein, Scheier, &#38; Buss, 1975). You actively create your public self through your communication and behavior.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p56" block_type="txt">Sometimes your private and public selves mirror each other. At other times, such as when Ted Allen outed Anne Burrell, it can seem as though your private and public selves are different. But regardless of the nature of your private self, people form impressions about you based on the public self you present. People know and judge the &#8220;you&#8221; who communicates with them&#8212;not the &#8220;you&#8221; you keep inside. Thus, managing your public self is a crucial part of being a competent communicator.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-5" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="42">
<section-metadata><section-title>Creating Faces and Masks</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p57" block_type="txt-ni">The positive self you want others to see and believe is your <termref term="face">face</termref> (Goffman, 1955). Face doesn&#8217;t just happen; you actively create and present it through your communication. Your face can be anything you want it to be: perky and upbeat, cool and levelheaded, cynical and detached.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p58" block_type="txt">You create different faces for different situations. Sometimes your face is a <termref term="mask">mask</termref>: an outward presentation designed to cover private aspects of your self (Goffman, 1955). For example, suppose you have an interview coming up for a new job. The night before, you find out someone close to you has died. When you meet with your potential new boss, you act upbeat, engaging, and competent&#8212;even though you want to curl up on the floor and cry. Sometimes you adopt masks to protect others. Paramedics often do this when they talk in calm, comforting tones to keep severely injured accident victims from going into shock.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-6" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="42">
<section-metadata><section-title>Losing Face</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p59" block_type="txt-ni">When you create a certain face (or a mask) and then do something that contradicts it, you <em>lose face</em> (Goffman, 1955). People may perceive you as phony and may feel betrayed by your actions. Losing face can also cause you to experience <termref term="embarrassment">embarrassment</termref>&#8212;feelings of shame, humiliation, and sadness. For example, when Steve was in high school, he competed at a state public-speaking tournament. During the final qualifying round, he suddenly blanked in the middle of his speech. As he stood there silently for several seconds, feeling and looking incompetent in front of his audience, he contradicted his face of &#8220;confident, competitive public speaker.&#8221; The result was embarrassment that he remembers to this day.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-7" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="43">
<section-metadata><section-title>Maintaining Face</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_43" block_type="page_start">43</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p60" block_type="txt-ni">Losing face is painful for everyone involved, so maintaining face during communication is critical. For example, when Ted Allen outed Anne Burrell, Burrell succeeded in maintaining her face by immediately acknowledging what happened and noting her commitment to her partner. What&#8217;s more, the Food Network executives helped her maintain face by making it clear that they considered her lesbian identity to be a welcome part of their diverse network.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p61" block_type="txt">How can you maintain your face? First, use words and actions consistent with the face you&#8217;re trying to create. If you tell members of a project team that you&#8217;re excited to hear everyone&#8217;s input, be sure to demonstrate this by actively listening when each member offers suggestions instead of tuning out and texting your friends. Second, make sure your communication meshes with others&#8217; existing knowledge about you. If you&#8217;re giving a speech about the dangers of listening to loud music through headphones and you walked into class blasting music through your earbuds, you won&#8217;t be able to maintain face. Finally, try to anticipate and manage events that could contradict your face. If you tell your dating partner that you haven&#8217;t been in contact with your ex, you won&#8217;t want a post from him or her to pop up on your Facebook Timeline.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p62" block_type="txt">Of course, everyone falls from grace on occasion. But remember, most people want you to maintain face because your face is the positive, public &#8220;you&#8221; with whom they&#8217;re most familiar. So when something happens that causes you to lose face, promptly acknowledge that the event happened, admit responsibility for any of your actions that contributed to the event, apologize for your actions and for disappointing others, and move to maintain your face again. Apologies are fairly successful at reducing people&#8217;s negative impressions and the anger that may have been triggered&#8212; especially when such apologies avoid excuses that contradict what people know really happened (Ohbuchi &#38; Sato, 1994). People who consistently deny their inconsistencies or who blame others for their lapses are judged much more harshly.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-3" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="43">
<section-metadata><section-title>Perceiving Others</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p63" block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>Along with your view of self, your perception of others determines how you communicate. Although it may seem as though your view of other people is both accurate and objective, it is anything but. Understanding the process of perception will help you avoid errors that might cause you to communicate incompetently.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p64" block_type="txt-ni">Despite the fact that she&#8217;s one of the greatest tennis players ever, people&#8217;s perceptions of Serena Williams span the gamut, from admiration as a role model to adulation as a hero to denunciation as a disgrace (because of her angry outbursts). At the Indian Wells tournament in 2001, the crowd viewed a triumphant Williams as undeserving&#8212;even though she clearly won the match&#8212;and booed and taunted her as a result. This incident reminds us that <em>all</em> communication arises from <termref term="perception">perception</termref>: the process of selecting, organizing, and interpreting information from your senses. Simply put, perception is the gateway to the world around you, and what you &#8220;see&#8221; through this gateway determines the communication path you&#8217;ll pursue as you walk through it.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_44" block_type="page_start">44</p>
<box title="MAKING COMMUNICATION CHOICES" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx2-1" block_type="bx2-v2-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p65" block_type="bx-v2-txt"><strong>DISTORTING ONLINE SELF-PRESENTATION</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p66" block_type="bx-v2-h1a"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>1</strong></phrase> <strong>CONSIDER THE DILEMMA</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p67" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">Tired of the local dating scene, you join an online matchmaking service. As you craft your profile, your friends encourage you to &#8220;spin&#8221; your self-presentation. &#8220;Make yourself three inches taller,&#8221; says one, and another encourages you to &#8220;change your age and say you have a master&#8217;s degree.&#8221; When you protest that this isn&#8217;t honest, they say, &#8220;Don&#8217;t worry about it&#8212;everyone does it! Besides, do you want to meet people or not?&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p68" block_type="bx2-txt">After a couple of weeks, you connect with Jordan, who seems to be your soul mate. You two have everything in common, from tastes in movies and music, to religious and political beliefs. Excited to meet offline, you arrange a lunch date.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p69" block_type="bx2-txt">Jordan proves to be even more desirable in person than online. As you enjoy lunch together, you cover many topics, including your educations, your families, and your life dreams. It is clear that the attraction you shared online exists offline as well. As lunch ends, you tell Jordan, &#8220;I&#8217;d really like to see you again.&#8221; However, Jordan frowns and says, &#8220;I have to be honest. Although I&#8217;ve really enjoyed our date, I&#8217;m a little confused. You&#8217;re not exactly how I thought you&#8217;d be, based on your profile. I mean, as we were talking, you said you are still in school. But that isn&#8217;t what your description says. Is there stuff you just haven&#8217;t told me, or did you make things up for your profile?&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p70" block_type="bx-v2-h1a"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>2</strong></phrase> <strong>CONNECT THE RESEARCH</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p71" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">People often present themselves online in ways that amplify positive characteristics, such as warmth and friendliness, while masking characteristics they think are undesirable or unattractive (Gosling, Gaddis, &#38; Vazire, 2007). This is especially true on online dating sites. More than a quarter of online matchmaking members report having lied in their profiles to present themselves as more attractive (Brym &#38; Lenton, 2001).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p72" block_type="bx2-txt">Communication scholar Jeffrey Hall and colleagues surveyed over 5,000 online dating service users to examine the specific ways in which they misrepresented themselves (Hall, Park, Song, &#38; Cody, 2010). Although both men and women lied about their ages (making themselves younger), men were more likely than women to lie about income and educational levels, whereas women were more likely to lie about their weight.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p73" block_type="bx2-txt">Of course, distorting your online self-presentation is ultimately self-defeating if you wish to form off line relationships. Researchers found that 86 percent of dating site users reported having met others who they felt had misrepresented their physical attractiveness (Gibbs, Ellison, &#38; Heino, 2006), and in such situations, they typically felt &#8220;lied to&#8221; (Ellison, Heino, &#38; Gibbs, 2006).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p74" block_type="bx2-txt">So, while distorting your self-presentation online is both tempting and commonplace, if your goal is to forge an offline connection, you should present yourself authentically online. Otherwise, people may judge you as dishonest, and that can end a promising relationship before it even begins.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p75" block_type="bx-v2-h1a"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>3</strong></phrase> <strong>COMMUNICATE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p76" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">Before making a communication choice, consider what the research tells you about online self-presentation. Also factor in what you have learned about face (pp. 42&#8211;43), embarrassment (p. 42), and apologies (p. 43). Then answer these questions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-4" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p77" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">Was it ethical to post distorted information in your dating profile? Why or why not?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p78" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">If you were Jordan, what would you be thinking and feeling in this situation?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p79" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">What are you going to say to Jordan?</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="MAINTAINING FACE" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx1-1" block_type="bx1-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p80" block_type="bx-v1-txt"><strong>People in the public eye, including sports figures, entertainers, and politicians, frequently encounter challenges for which maintaining their public face is crucial to their success. But maintaining face is not only important for the famous; how do you use communication to maintain your face on a daily basis?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-8" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-10" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P06.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Bloomberg/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-9" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-11" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P07.jpg"/>
<asset_source>David A. Smith/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-10" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-12" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P08.jpg"/>
<asset_source>YIN BOGU/Xinhua/Landov</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-8" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="45">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Perception Process</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_45" block_type="page_start">45</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p81" block_type="txt-ni">Perception occurs when you do the following:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-5" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p82" block_type="nl-f"><em>Select</em> information to focus your attention on</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p83" block_type="nl-m"><em>Organize</em> the information into an understandable pattern, such as words, phrases, ideas, or images</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p84" block_type="nl-l"><em>Interpret</em> the meaning of the pattern</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_46" block_type="page_start">46</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p85" block_type="txt">Each step in the perception process influences the others: the information you select determines how you organize it, your mental organization of information shapes how you interpret it, and your interpretation of information influences how you mentally organize it. (See <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-11">Figure 2.2</link>.) Let&#8217;s take a closer look at each step.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx4-2" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-11" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="2.2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 2.2</strong></phrase> <strong>THE PERCEPTION PROCESS</strong></caption>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-13" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_02_F02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Alexandr III/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p86" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Step 1: Select Information.</strong></phrase> During the first step of perception, <termref term="selection">selection</termref>, you focus your attention on certain sights, sounds, tastes, touches, or smells in your environment. One estimate suggests that even though your senses take in 11 million bits of information per second, you select only about 40 bits to pay attention to (Wilson, 2002). With so much information out there, how do you decide what to select? You&#8217;re more likely to focus on something when it is visually or audibly stimulating, deviates from your expectations, or is viewed as important (Fiske &#38; Taylor, 1991).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p87" block_type="txt">Consider what this means for your communication. If you&#8217;re attending a presentation and the speaker talks in a dramatic, impassioned way, you&#8217;re more likely to pay attention than if the presenter had spoken in a monotone and stood passively behind the lectern. If Tom, a team member who&#8217;s usually talkative, sits silently during a meeting, he&#8217;ll defy your expectations&#8212;so you&#8217;ll notice him. And if you hear your child start to cry in an adjacent room, you&#8217;ll likely consider the situation important and focus your attention on it.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p88" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Step 2: Organize the Information into a Pattern.</strong></phrase> Once you&#8217;ve selected something to focus your attention on, you structure the information you receive through your senses into a coherent pattern in your mind. This is the second step of the perception process, known as <termref term="organization">organization</termref> (Fiske &#38; Taylor, 1991). For example, once your attention is drawn to Tom (the unusually quiet group member), you begin to observe all that he is doing&#8212;his posture, facial expressions, bodily movements, and lack of comments&#8212;and organize it within your mind as a coherent package: &#8220;This is how Tom is acting right now.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p89" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Step 3: Interpret the Pattern.</strong></phrase> As you organize the information you&#8217;ve selected into a coherent pattern, you engage in the third step of perception: <termref term="interpretation">interpretation</termref>, or assigning meaning to the information you&#8217;ve selected. You call to mind familiar information that&#8217;s relevant, and use that information to make sense of what you&#8217;re hearing and seeing. Borrowing on the previous example, this is the stage of perception in which you would assign meaning to the behaviors of Tom that you have focused your attention on: &#8220;When people who are usually talkative are suddenly quiet, they often have something on their minds. Tom is being unusually quiet. Maybe Tom is upset about something.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_47" block_type="page_start">47</p>
<box title="FUNDAMENTAL ATTRIBUTION ERROR" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx1-2" block_type="bx1-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p90" block_type="ph-v0-cap"><strong>The morning rush at a coffee shop can be equally frustrating for customers and employees. Think about how their interactions might change if they considered external, rather than internal, attributions for one another&#8217;s behaviors.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-12" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-14" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P09.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Bloomberg via Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-9" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="47">
<section-metadata><section-title>Attributions and Perceptual Errors</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p91" block_type="txt-ni">Following the perception process, you often want explanations for why things are happening the way they are (&#8220;Why is Tom not talking during the meeting?&#8221;). These explanations are known as <termref term="attributions">attributions</termref>. Two types of attributions are commonplace. One is that <em>external</em> factors or events&#8212;things outside the person&#8212;caused the person&#8217;s behavior (&#8220;Tom just heard that his dad is sick, so he&#8217;s thinking about that instead of taking part in the meeting&#8221;). The other is that <em>internal</em> factors&#8212;personality, character, emotions&#8212;caused the person to act as he or she did (&#8220;Tom is a moody jerk, and that&#8217;s why he&#8217;s not contributing&#8221;).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_48" block_type="page_start">48</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p92" block_type="txt">Given the number of people you communicate with each day, it&#8217;s not surprising that you occasionally form invalid attributions. One common mistake is the <termref term="fundamental attribution error">fundamental attribution error</termref>, the tendency to attribute others&#8217; behaviors to internal rather than external forces (Heider, 1958). You make the fundamental attribution error because when you communicate with others, they&#8212;not the surrounding factors that may be causing their behavior&#8212;dominate your perception. As a result, when you make judgments about why someone is acting a certain way, you overestimate the influence of the person and underestimate the influence of external factors (Heider, 1958; Langdridge &#38; Butt, 2004).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p93" block_type="txt">The fundamental attribution error is the most prevalent of all perceptual errors (Langdridge &#38; Butt, 2004). For example, communication scholar Alan Sillars and his colleagues found that during conflicts between parents and teens, both parties typically fall prey to the fundamental attribution error (Sillars, Smith, &#38; Koerner, 2010). Parents commonly attribute teens&#8217; communication to &#8220;lack of responsibility&#8221; and &#8220;desire to avoid the issue,&#8221; whereas teens attribute parents&#8217; communication to &#8220;desire to control my life.&#8221; Similar patterns have been observed during marital conflicts, with spouses typically blaming each other for the fight and attributing negative partner behaviors to internal causes: for example, &#8220;He&#8217;s so stubborn!&#8221; and &#8220;She&#8217;s so picky!&#8221; (Sillars, Roberts, Leonard, &#38; Dun, 2000).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p94" block_type="txt">A related error is the <termref term="actor-observer effect">actor-observer effect</termref>, the tendency to make external attributions regarding your own behaviors (Fiske &#38; Taylor, 1991). During encounters with others, you tend to focus on external factors&#8212;especially the people you&#8217;re interacting with. Therefore, you tend to identify these external factors as causing your behavior. This is particularly prevalent during unpleasant interactions. For example, if you&#8217;re giving a speech and the audience doesn&#8217;t pay attention, you might get angry and feel that such anger is a justifiable reaction to audience members&#8217; rudeness rather than a lack of self-control on your part.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p95" block_type="txt">However, when your actions result in success, you tend to take credit for the success by making an internal attribution (&#8220;The audience paid attention because I&#8217;m a skilled speaker&#8221;). This tendency is known as the <termref term="self-serving bias">self-serving bias</termref> (Fiske &#38; Taylor, 1991). By crediting yourself for your successes, you feel better about who you are and the skills you possess.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p96" block_type="txt">Your attributions directly influence how you communicate with others and the outcomes that result. For example, imagine that your partner forgets to pick up your dry cleaning on the way home from work. If you attribute your partner&#8217;s forgetfulness to work pressures and a hectic schedule (external causes), you&#8217;ll probably communicate in a supportive way (&#8220;I know how busy you are&#8212;I should&#8217;ve texted you a reminder&#8221;). But if you make internal attributions (&#8220;my partner is self-centered and inconsiderate&#8221;), you&#8217;ll likely communicate in a destructive way (&#8220;I&#8217;m sure you&#8217;d remember if it were <em>your</em> stuff that needed picking up!&#8221;).</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-4" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="49">
<section-metadata><section-title>Forming Impressions</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_49" block_type="page_start">49</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p97" block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>Whenever you meet people, you paint pictures in your mind of who they are and what you think of them. These images can be positive or negative, long lasting or subject to change. However, they act as a powerful guide in shaping your communication, for better or for worse.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p98" block_type="txt-ni">Although it&#8217;s hard to believe now, Joe was a competitive distance runner in college. Grueling training runs in the heat and humidity of southeast Texas bonded him and his fellow teammates, helping them overcome differences in their ethnic backgrounds, personalities, lifestyles, and worldviews. But just as they were forming more positive impressions of one another, the runners as a group were perceived differently by other students on campus. At the time, long-distance running was only just starting to gain popularity in the United States. Students who didn&#8217;t understand the sport viewed the athletes as freaks. Who in their right mind, after all, would run 20 miles a day&#8212;in Texas?! The runners&#8217; scrawny physiques even led some people to say they were malnourished, creating further skepticism about the sport. Yet many of these same critics were shocked to see how much pizza the runners put away in the dining hall as they loaded up on carbohydrates before a race.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p99" block_type="txt">Like those who judged the distance runners, you also use the perception process to form <termref term="impressions">impressions</termref> of others: mental images of who people are and how you feel about them. All aspects of the perception process shape your impressions: the information you select to focus your attention on, the way you organize this information, the interpretations you make, and the attributions you create.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p100" block_type="txt">Because the perception process is complex and everyone organizes and interprets information differently, impressions vary widely. Some take shape quickly: you hear a politician giving a speech and take an immediate dislike to him. Other impressions form slowly, over a series of encounters. Some are intensely positive: &#8220;Long-distance runners are amazingly dedicated and disciplined!&#8221; Others are neutral. Some are negative: &#8220;Long-distance runners are freaks!&#8221; Let&#8217;s look at some ways you form impressions.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-10" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="49">
<section-metadata><section-title>Gestalts</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p101" block_type="txt-ni">One way you form impressions of others is to construct a <termref term="Gestalt">Gestalt</termref>, a general impression of a person that&#8217;s positive or negative. You identify a few traits about the person and then arrive at a judgment (&#8220;I like you&#8221; or &#8220;I don&#8217;t like you&#8221;). For example, audience members begin forming impressions of you the moment you begin a speech. Your clothing, posture, facial expressions, and opening remarks generate an overall impression that can instantly enhance or undermine your credibility.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_50" block_type="page_start">50</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p102" block_type="txt">Gestalts form rapidly and require relatively little mental or communicative effort. This makes them useful for encounters in which you must make quick judgments about others based on limited information. Imagine you need to hire someone and have dozens of r&#233;sum&#233;s to review. Although r&#233;sum&#233;s don&#8217;t reflect the sum total of what the applicants are like, the Gestalts you create based on them will help you decide whom to interview (&#8220;This r&#233;sum&#233; is well crafted, has no typos, and highlights skills relevant to this job. I <em>like</em> her already!&#8221;).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p103" block_type="txt">A disadvantage of Gestalts is that they can distort how you interpret information you later learn about people. Think about someone for whom you&#8217;ve formed a strongly positive Gestalt. Now imagine discovering that this person cheated on his taxes. Because of your positive Gestalt, you may dismiss the significance of this behavior (&#8220;He probably made an innocent mistake&#8221;). This tendency is known as the <termref term="halo effect">halo effect</termref>.</p>
<box title="THE POWER OF GESTALTS" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx1-3" block_type="bx1-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p104" block_type="bx-v1-txt"><strong>One way to understand the power of Gestalts is to consider how you feel about controversial public figures. For example, do you have a strong opinion about the individuals pictured here? Chances are you don&#8217;t personally know any of them, but you still form strong Gestalts about them. Consider how this same process works for people you meet in person or online.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-13" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-15" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Scott Olson/Getty Images;</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-14" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-16" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P12.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Michael Karas/North Jersey/Landov;</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-15" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-17" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P11.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Emily Berl/The New York Times/Redux</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_51" block_type="page_start">51</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p105" block_type="txt">The counterpart of the halo effect is the <termref term="horn effect">horn effect</termref>, the tendency to negatively interpret the behavior of people for whom you&#8217;ve formed negative Gestalts. Call to mind someone you can&#8217;t stand. Now imagine that this person has cheated on her taxes. Chances are, you&#8217;ll chalk up her behavior to bad character or lack of values (&#8220;I knew she was a cheat!&#8221;).</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-11" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="51">
<section-metadata><section-title>Algebraic Impressions</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p106" block_type="txt-ni">A second way to form impressions is to develop <termref term="algebraic impressions">algebraic impressions</termref>&#8212;analyzing the positive and negative things you learn about someone to calculate an overall impression, then updating this impression as you learn new information (Anderson, 1981). It&#8217;s similar to solving an algebraic equation, whereby you add and subtract different values to compute a final result. However, when forming algebraic impressions, you don&#8217;t place an equal value on every piece of information you receive. Instead, information that&#8217;s important, unusual, or negative is usually weighted more heavily than information that&#8217;s trivial, typical, or positive (Kellermann, 1989). This happens because people tend to believe that important, unusual, or negative information reveals more about a person&#8217;s &#8220;true&#8221; character than does other information (Kellermann, 1989).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p107" block_type="txt">Of course, other people form algebraic impressions of you, too. So, when you&#8217;re communicating&#8212;whether in person or online, with a friend or in front of an audience&#8212;be mindful of what important, unusual, or negative information you share about yourself. This information will have a particularly strong effect on others&#8217; impressions of you.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p108" block_type="txt">Algebraic impressions are more accurate than Gestalts because you take time to form them and you consider a wider range of information. They&#8217;re also more flexible. You can update your algebraic impression every time you receive new information about someone. For instance, you discover through Facebook that the cool classmate you went on a date with yesterday has political views much different from your own. Accordingly, you become a bit cautious about pursuing a romantic relationship with this person while remaining open to seeing where things will lead.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-12" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="51">
<section-metadata><section-title>Stereotypes</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p109" block_type="txt-ni">A final way to form impressions is to categorize people into a social group (such as their race, age, or gender) and then evaluate them based on information you have related to this group. This is known as <termref term="stereotyping">stereotyping</termref> (Bodenhausen, Macrae, &#38; Sherman, 1999). Stereotypes take the subtle complexities that make people unique and replace them with blanket assumptions about their character and worth based solely on their social group affiliations. Stereotyping is difficult to avoid because it&#8217;s the most common way we form impressions (Bodenhausen et al., 1999). Why? Social-group categories can be the first things you notice about others when you meet them. So you often perceive people in terms of their social group before it&#8217;s possible to make any other impression (Devine, 1989).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_52" block_type="page_start">52</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p110" block_type="txt">Stereotyping often leads to flawed impressions. In one workplace study, male supervisors who stereotyped women as &#8220;the weaker sex&#8221; perceived female employees&#8217; work performance as deficient and gave women low job evaluations&#8212;regardless of the women&#8217;s actual job performance (Cleveland, Stockdale, &#38; Murphy, 2000). A separate study examining college students&#8217; perceptions of professors found a similar biasing effect for ethnic stereotypes. Euro-American students who stereotyped Hispanics as &#8220;laid-back&#8221; perceived Hispanic professors who set high expectations for classroom performance as &#8220;colder&#8221; and &#8220;more unprofessional&#8221; than Euro-American professors who set identical standards (Smith &#38; Anderson, 2005).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p111" block_type="txt">Despite claims of being the most democratic and equalizing mass medium, the Internet actually enables stereotyping. During online communication, people don&#8217;t have the nonverbal cues and other information that can distinguish someone as a unique individual. As a result, people communicating online are more likely than those communicating face-to-face to form stereotypical impressions of others (Lea &#38; Spears, 1992; Spears, Postmes, Lea, &#38; Watt, 2001; P. Wallace, 1999).</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx5-3" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p112" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Because stereotyping fails to consider the intricate complexities that distinguish individuals from broad group affiliations, it often leads to flawed impressions. To avoid an overreliance on stereotypes, always adapt your communication to the person, not the group.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-16" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-18" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P13.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Chris Carlson/AP Images</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p113" block_type="txt">Though stereotypes are used to form impressions, they should not reflect rigid attitudes toward groups and their members. This is known as <em>prejudice</em> and can cause you to communicate in destructive and unethical ways. See <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link> (pp. 94&#8211;96) to learn more about prejudice and how you can overcome it.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-5" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="52">
<section-metadata><section-title>Improving Your Perception</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p114" block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>Even though perception and impression formation occur in specific ways, they are not unchangeable processes. You can improve your perception and impressions by critically questioning your own judgments and routinely considering the feelings, needs, and viewpoints of others.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p115" block_type="txt-ni">As we have emphasized throughout this chapter, accurate perception is key if you wish to bolster the competence of your communication. Two skills can help you improve your perception and the resulting communication choices you make: perception-checking and empathy.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_53" block_type="page_start">53</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-13" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="53">
<section-metadata><section-title>Perception-Checking</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p116" block_type="txt-ni"><termref term="Perception-checking">Perception-checking</termref> is a five-step process for testing your impression of someone and avoiding errors in judgment. (See <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-17">Table 2.1</link>.) Whenever you&#8217;re in a situation in which having clear, accurate perceptions of others is a must, follow these steps. First, review your knowledge about the person. Your impression of this individual is only as accurate as the information you have. Never presume that you know the &#8220;truth&#8221; about someone.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx6-1" block_type="bx6">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p117" block_type="bx6-h">TABLE 2.1</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p118" block_type="bx6-t"><strong>PERCEPTION-CHECKING</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p119" block_type="bx6-txt"><strong>SITUATION</strong> Imagine that you are working on a group project for your communication class. Your group leader, Heather, doesn&#8217;t take suggestions from other members and only moves forward with her own ideas. What steps should you take before confronting Heather about her leadership style?</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-17" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-19" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_02_T01.jpg"/>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p120" block_type="bx6-txt"><strong>TAKE AWAY</strong> Instead of jumping to conclusions, it&#8217;s important to remember that both internal and external attributions affect a person&#8217;s behavior. Once you understand that the external pressure to keep her academic scholarship is causing Heather to control the group, you can more competently approach improving communication within the group.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p121" block_type="txt">Second, assess attributions you&#8217;ve made about this individual. Avoid attributing the person&#8217;s behavior exclusively to internal causes. Remember that all behavior stems from a blend of internal and external forces.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p122" block_type="txt">Third, question your impression. Make sure you&#8217;re not basing it solely on a Gestalt or a stereotype.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p123" block_type="txt">Fourth, share your impression with the individual. Present it as &#8220;here&#8217;s my viewpoint,&#8221; not as the &#8220;right&#8221; or &#8220;only&#8221; perspective.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p124" block_type="txt">Fifth, check your impression with the person: &#8220;Do you see it the same way?&#8221; As communication teachers, we can&#8217;t count the number of times students have asked us, &#8220;Do you think he meant this?&#8221; or &#8220;Do you think she was trying to . . . ?&#8221; We always say, &#8220;Why don&#8217;t you ask them?&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p125" block_type="txt">Mastering perception-checking takes practice, but the effort is worthwhile. Perception-checking helps you make fewer communication blunders. It also enables you to tailor your communication to people as they really are. Thus, your messages become more sensitive and effective. Ultimately, others will see you as a more competent communicator if you use perception-checking.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec2-14" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="53">
<section-metadata><section-title>Empathy</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p126" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-20" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <strong><link href="http://macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p127" block_type="txt-ni">Empathy is among the most valuable tools for communicating more effectively with others (Campbell &#38; Babrow, 2004). The word <em>empathy</em> comes from the Greek word <em>empatheia</em>, meaning &#8220;feeling into.&#8221; When you experience <termref term="empathy">empathy</termref>, you &#8220;feel into&#8221; others&#8217; thoughts and emotions, making an attempt to identify with them (Kuhn, 2001).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p128" block_type="txt">Empathy consists of two components: perspective-taking and empathic concern (Davis, 1994). <em>Perspective-taking</em> is the ability to see things from other people&#8217;s point of view without necessarily experiencing their emotions (Duan &#38; Hill, 1996). <em>Empathic concern</em> means becoming aware of how other people are feeling and experiencing compassion for them (Stiff, Dillard, Somera, Kim, &#38; Sleight, 1988). For example, imagine your friend John texts you that his boyfriend just broke up with him. In experiencing empathy for your friend, you would put yourself in his shoes and call to mind instances in which a romantic partner left you. Then you&#8217;d envision the emotional pain and turmoil you&#8217;ve felt on such occasions, and use these memories to feel compassion toward John.</p>
<box title="HOW TO COMMUNICATE &#124; Video Skills" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx7-1" block_type="bx7-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_54" block_type="page_start">54</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p129" block_type="bx7-h"><strong>EMPATHY FOR A GROUP MEMBER</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p130" block_type="bx7-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-21" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> One way to improve your communication competence is by adapting your messages to others&#8217; behaviors. Learn how to express empathy by going to LaunchPad at <strong><link href="http://macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong> and completing the <strong>How to Communicate video scenario</strong> for <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link> to practice your skills.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p131" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>CONSIDER THIS:</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p132" block_type="bx7-txt">You&#8217;re assigned to lead a group project for a class. One team member, Alex, has missed two of the first three meetings. When you meet with Alex to discuss this, you discover that she has a three-year-old she is raising as a single mother and that she is working full-time to put herself through school. She genuinely wants to contribute to the project but is struggling to juggle all of the competing demands in her life.</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-18" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-22" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_02_HTC_1.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;We&#8217;ve missed you at the last couple of meetings . . . I am concerned about how you&#8217;re doing personally. Is everything OK? . . . I&#8217;m here to listen if you need someone to talk to.&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p133" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>WHAT WOULD YOU DO?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p134" block_type="bx7-txt">The following advice illustrates how to express empathy for Alex&#8217;s situation while still keeping the group&#8217;s goals in mind. As you watch the video, consider how the dialogue reflects perspective-taking and empathic concern. Then, test your knowledge of key skills, and create your own responses to the <strong>What if? video prompts.</strong></p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p136" block_type="mn3-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-23" alt="image" src="images/1.jpg"/> <strong>OPENLY EXPRESS CONCERN</strong> for Alex as a person, not just as a group member.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_55" block_type="page_start">55</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p137" block_type="mn3-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-24" alt="image" src="images/2.jpg"/> <strong>LEGITIMIZE HER SITUATION,</strong> letting her know that feeling overwhelmed when faced with such demands is perfectly under standable.</p>
</box>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-19" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-25" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_02_HTC_2.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;I can&#8217;t even imagine dealing with all that you&#8217;ve got going on right now. It&#8217;s totally understandable that you&#8217;re feeling stressed.&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p139" block_type="mn3-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-26" alt="image" src="images/3.jpg"/> <strong>REAFFIRM THE IMPORTANCE</strong> of her contribution, making it clear that you want her to stay in the group.</p>
</box>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-20" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-27" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_02_HTC_2a.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;The insights you&#8217;ve contributed to the project so far have been awesome. We don&#8217;t ant to lose you as a group member. What can we do to help you out, so we can make this work as a team?&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p141" block_type="bx7-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-28" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> <strong>WHAT IF? But what if things don&#8217;t work out as shown? Test your ability to adapt your communication by watching the What if? videos and planning a response for each situation.</strong></p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-6" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p142" block_type="nl">How would you respond to Alex when she says, &#8220;Why would I talk to you about my problems? It&#8217;s not like we&#8217;re friends or anything.&#8221;</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p143" block_type="nl">What can you do to show empathic concern when Alex says, &#8220;Yes, you&#8217;re right: you can&#8217;t imagine, or understand, what I&#8217;m going through.&#8221;</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_56" block_type="page_start">56</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p144" block_type="txt">We often think of empathy as an automatic process beyond our control, something we either feel or don&#8217;t feel (Schumann, Zaki, &#38; Dweck, 2014). Consequently, we excuse ourselves from being empathic toward people we dislike or don&#8217;t get along with. But recent research suggests that whether we feel empathy toward others depends largely on our <termref term="empathy mindset">empathy mindset</termref>&#8212;our beliefs about whether empathy is something that can be developed and controlled (Schumann et al., 2014). People that view empathy as developable and controllable are capable of feeling empathy for a broad range of others&#8212;even during challenging communication contexts such as an interpersonal conflict, an argument about political beliefs, or a grief story told by someone we perceive as completely different from us (Schumann et al., 2014). Those who believe empathy is an uncontrollable, natural response have difficulty experiencing empathy within such challenging encounters.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_57" block_type="page_start">57</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p145" block_type="txt">But experiencing empathy isn&#8217;t enough. You must also convey your empathy to others. To do so, let others know you&#8217;re genuinely interested in listening to them (&#8220;I&#8217;m here to listen if you want to talk&#8221;). Tell them you think their views are valid and understandable (&#8220;I can totally understand why you would feel that way&#8221;). Express your concern about them (&#8220;I care about you and am worried that you&#8217;re not OK&#8221;). And finally, share with them your own emotions regarding their situation (&#8220;I feel terrible that you&#8217;re going through this&#8221;).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p146" block_type="txt">When expressing empathy, avoid using &#8220;I know&#8221; messages (&#8220;I know just how you feel&#8221;). Even if you make such comments with kind intentions, the other person will likely be skeptical, particularly if they suspect that you don&#8217;t or can&#8217;t feel as they do. For example, when people suffer a great loss&#8212;such as the death of a loved one&#8212;many don&#8217;t believe that anyone else could feel the depth of anguish they&#8217;re experiencing. Saying &#8220;I know how you feel&#8221; isn&#8217;t helpful under these conditions. To see how you can competently display empathy, see <link href="#choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx7-1">How to Communicate: Empathy for a Group Member</link> on pages 54&#8211;55.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p147" block_type="txt">Competently conveying empathy isn&#8217;t just something to be strived for as a matter of principle; it&#8217;s a recommendation packed with practical benefits (Goldstein, Vezich, &#38; Shapiro, 2014). When others perceive you as empathic, they&#8217;re also more likely to perceive you as someone they can relate to, more likely to like you, and more likely to help you when you are in need.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-bx5-4" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p148" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>When you express empathy to others, be sure you validate their feelings and share your concern for them, but also&#8212;perhaps most important&#8212;really listen to what they need, and offer to help any way you can. After all, if the roles were reversed, isn&#8217;t that what you would want from others?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-fig-21" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-29" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_02_P14.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Helder Almeida/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-6" block_type="cr-h" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="58">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER 2 REVIEW</section-title></section-metadata>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-7" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="58">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER RECAP</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_58" block_type="page_start">58</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-7" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p149" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Your <termref term="self">self</termref> is an evolving blend of three components: <termref term="self-awareness">self-awareness</termref>, <termref term="self-concept">self-concept</termref>, and <termref term="self-esteem">self-esteem</termref>. These shape how you communicate in all situations and contexts.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p150" block_type="cr-bl-v0">The positive self you want others to see and believe is your <termref term="face">face</termref>; your face is a <termref term="mask">mask</termref> when you hide parts of it. To avoid <termref term="embarrassment">embarrassment</termref>, work on maintaining your face.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p151" block_type="cr-bl-v0"><termref term="Perception">Perception</termref> is how you view the world around you. You use <termref term="attributions">attributions</termref> to explain why things happen.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p152" block_type="cr-bl-v0">There are many ways to form <termref term="impressions">impressions</termref> of others, including constructing <termref term="Gestalts">Gestalts</termref>, forming <termref term="algebraic impressions">algebraic impressions</termref>, and <termref term="stereotyping">stereotyping</termref>.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p153" block_type="cr-bl-v0">You can improve your perception by practicing <termref term="perception-checking">perception-checking</termref> and <termref term="empathy">empathy</termref>.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p154" block_type="cr-txt-ni"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-30" alt="image" src="images/launchpad.jpg"/> LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> offers unique video scenarios and encourages self-assessment through adaptive quizzing. Go to <strong><link href="http://macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong> to get access.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p155" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-31" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> LearningCurve adaptive quizzes</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p156" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-32" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> How to Communicate video scenarios</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p157" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-33" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> Video clips that illustrate key concepts</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-8" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="58">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p158" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p23">Self, p. 34</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p159" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p23">Self-awareness, p. 35</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p160" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p25"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-34" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Social comparison, p. 35</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p161" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p26">Critical self-reflection, p. 35</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p162" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p33">Self-concept, p. 36</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p163" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p35">Self-Verification Theory, p. 36</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p164" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p36"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-35" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Self-fulfilling prophecies, p. 36</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p165" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p37">Self-esteem, p. 37</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p166" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p38">Self-Discrepancy Theory, p. 38</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p167" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p47">Culture, p. 39</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p168" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p48">Individualistic culture, p. 39</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p169" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p49">Collectivistic culture, p. 39</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p170" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p50">Gender, p. 39</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p171" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p50">Transgender persons, p. 39</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p172" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p57"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-36" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Face, p. 42</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p173" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p58"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-37" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Mask, p. 42</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p174" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p59">Embarrassment, p. 42</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p175" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p64">Perception, p. 45</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p176" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p86">Selection, p. 46</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p177" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p88">Organization, p. 46</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p178" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p89">Interpretation, p. 46</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p179" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p91">Attributions, p. 47</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p180" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p92">Fundamental attribution error, p. 48</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p181" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p94">Actor-observer effect, p. 48</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p182" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p95"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-38" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Self-serving bias, p. 48</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p183" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p99">Impressions, p. 49</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p184" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p99">Gestalt, p. 49</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p185" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p103"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-39" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Halo effect, p. 51</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p186" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p105"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-40" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Horn effect, p. 51</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p187" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p106"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-41" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Algebraic impressions, p. 51</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p188" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p109">Stereotyping, p. 51</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p189" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p116">Perception-checking, p. 53</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p190" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p127"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-42" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Empathy, p. 53</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p191" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch2-p144">Empathy mindset, p. 57</link></p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-9" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="59">
<section-metadata><section-title>POP QUIZ</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_59" block_type="page_start">59</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p192" block_type="cr-wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-img-43" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> Looking for more review questions? <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you master key concepts from this chapter. Go to <strong><link href="http://macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-question-1" number="1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p193" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">According to Self-Discrepancy Theory, you are more likely to experience high self-esteem if &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-8" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p194" block_type="cr-ll-v1">your self-concept matches your ideal and ought selves</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p195" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">you prioritize your ought self over your ideal self</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p196" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">your relational partners support your self-concept</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p197" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">you strive for your most idealistic self at all times</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-question-2" number="2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p198" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">What is the difference between your face and a mask?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p199" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Your face is private, composed of your deeply held beliefs.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p200" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">A mask covers the private aspects of your self.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p201" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">You can have only one face but several masks.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p202" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">You recover from embarrassment by creating a new mask.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-question-3" number="3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p203" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">The overwhelming tendency of people to attribute others&#8217; behaviors to internal rather than external forces is known as &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p204" block_type="cr-ll-v1">self-serving bias</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p205" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">stereotyping</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p206" block_type="cr-ll-v1">actor-observer effect</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p207" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">fundamental attribution error</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-question-4" number="4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p208" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Which of the following impressions form over time?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-11" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p209" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Halo effect</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p210" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Horn effect</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p211" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Algebraic</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p212" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Gestalts</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-question-5" number="5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p213" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Which of the following is <em>not</em> one of the five steps of <em>perception-checking</em>?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-12" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p214" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Review your knowledge about the person</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p215" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Compare your impressions with a neutral source</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p216" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Question your impression</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p217" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Check your impression with the person</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-sec1-10" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch2" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="59">
<section-metadata><section-title>ACTIVITIES</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-exp4-1" block_type="mn4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p218" block_type="cr-wl-txt">For more activities, visit LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> at <strong><link href="http://macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-list-13" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p219" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Applying Self-Discrepancy Theory</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p220" block_type="cr-txt">Revisit Higgins&#8217;s Self-Discrepancy Theory on page 38, and consider how it applies to you and your feelings about your self. Then, write a brief paper describing your self-esteem: Overall, how do you feel about your self? Briefly explain your self-concept, your ideal self, and your ought self. Where did your ideal and ought selves come from? When you compare them to your self-concept, are there any self-discrepancies? If not, how is the lack of discrepancies related to your self-esteem? If there <em>are</em> discrepancies, how might they be overcome? Be specific. If you resolved these discrepancies, would your self-esteem improve? Why or why not?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p221" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Recovering from Embarrassment</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch2-p222" block_type="cr-txt">Either individually or in groups, find an example of an embarrassing moment from a TV show, Web series, or movie. (You can revisit Goffman&#8217;s discussion of face and embarrassment on pp. 42&#8211;43.) If possible, find a clip online to share with your class; if not, describe it in detail. How did the character communicate in response to his or her embarrassment? Did he or she maintain face? Now consider the three practices suggested for maintaining face, and the recommendations for recovering from losing face. Based on these, how would you evaluate the character&#8217;s handling of the situation? What specific advice would you give to him or her on how to better recover from losing face?</p></li>
</list>
</section>
</chapter>
</manuscript>
