<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<manuscript xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" manuscript-id="03" name="" title="MCC_Chapter_03_DJHrev" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/digfir_manuscript.xsd">
<chapter number="3" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-chapter-3" title="3: Mediated Communication" start-numbering-at="3" numbered="true">
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="60">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_60" block_type="page_start">60</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p1" block_type="chapter_number">3</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p2" block_type="chapter_title">Mediated Communication</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p3" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">S</phrase>itting at an Arizona Diamondback baseball game, the Alpha Chi Omega sorority sisters were doing something commonplace in this day and age: holding their phones at arm&#8217;s length, taking selfies while posing with hotdogs and churros. But this ordinary act drew extraordinary interest from the sportscasters commentating on the game. For almost two minutes, the television cameras switched between the selfie-shooting women and the play on the field. And when the focus was on the women, the broadcasters made mocking remarks, such as,<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p4"><sup>1</sup></link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p4" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p3"><sup>1</sup></link>Content that follows adapted from White and Hwang (2015).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p5" block_type="co-txt">&#8220;Do you have to make faces when you take selfies?&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p6" block_type="co-txt">&#8220;That&#8217;s the best one of the 300 pictures I&#8217;ve taken of myself today.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p7" block_type="co-txt">&#8220;Can we do an intervention?&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p8" block_type="co-txt">The video footage quickly went viral, prompting tweets, blog postings, and national news coverage. Opinions about the selfie session were varied. Many social media postings reflected harsh stereotypes, suggesting that the women were vain and self-centered, and didn&#8217;t appreciate the game of baseball.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p9" block_type="co-txt">But they also had a host of defenders. One sports editor, Tanya Bondurant (2015), directly chastised the <em>sportscasters</em> for engaging in selfie-shaming, writing:</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p10" block_type="co-ext">Welcome to 2015, gentlemen. Everyone is on their phone all the time. Baseball is a game with a lot of breaks and using that downtime to capture a fun moment with your friends shouldn&#8217;t make you the topic of a two-minute call-out. It just makes you a human in the 21st century.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p11" block_type="co-txt">Indeed, posting selfies is a common practice for maintaining an online presence. In 2015, the hashtags #me and #selfie accompanied over 200 million Instagram photo postings. Celebrities and sports figures fill their social media feeds with selfies as a way of letting fans into their lives. Actor James Franco (2013) believes selfies are meaningful &#8220;tools of communication.&#8221; He goes on to observe:</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p12" block_type="co-ext">I am actually turned off when I look at an account and don&#8217;t see any selfies, because I want to know whom I&#8217;m dealing with. In our age of social networking, the selfie is the new way to look someone right in the eye and say, &#8220;Hello, this is me.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p13" block_type="co-txt">Although selfies are an integral part of how we communicate online, the act of taking and posting selfies influences perceptions others may form of us and our messages. Just as the Arizona Diamondbacks&#8217; broadcasters misperceived the young women at the game, we, too, can be misunderstood. Communicating through text messages, tweets, video chat, and the many other ways available to connect with others online presents unique challenges.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p14" block_type="co-txt">In the wake of the controversy, Alpha Chi Omega turned what could have been an enduring embarrassment into a charitable triumph. When the Diamondbacks offered the sorority free tickets to a future game, they politely declined. Instead, they asked that the tickets be donated to a local nonprofit supporting victims of domestic violence. They were then invited to appear on <em>The Ellen DeGeneres Show</em>, where Ellen surprised the women with a &#36;10,000 donation to support their charity work.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_61" block_type="page_start">61</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-1" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-1" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Fabrice Caffrini/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_62" block_type="page_start">62</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p15" block_type="co-h"><strong>CHAPTER OUTLINE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p16" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-1"><strong>What Is Mediated Communication?</strong> 62</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p17" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-2"><strong>Self-Presentation and Mediated Communication</strong> 68</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p18" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-3"><strong>Challenges of Mediated Communication</strong> 74</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p19" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-4"><strong>Using Mediated Communication Competently</strong> 80</link></p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p20" block_type="co-txt">We won&#8217;t all go viral or be invited onto <em>The Ellen DeGeneres Show</em> for shooting selfies with friends at a game. But like the women of Alpha Chi Omega, we live our lives immersed in technology, and the devices we use play a major role in how we communicate with others. Understanding how various media affect your communication will help you communicate more competently. In this chapter, you&#8217;ll learn:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p21" block_type="bl-f">The functions and characteristics of mediated communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p22" block_type="bl-m">Ways to present your identity through mediated communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p23" block_type="bl-m">The challenges of using mediated communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p24" block_type="bl-l">Guidelines for competently using mediated communication</p></li>
</list>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-1" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="62">
<section-metadata><section-title>What Is Mediated Communication?</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p25" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-2" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p26" block_type="pul"><strong>Technology is so prevalent in our lives, it is easy not to think about it much. Phone, laptop, app&#8212;what does it matter? Indeed, technology helps with everything from family chats to late-night study sessions, but it also has unique considerations of its own. For starters, technology changes your communication, including what kind of feedback you receive and how you process it.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p27" block_type="txt-ni">Think about all the ways you communicate each day. How much do you talk to other people in person or on the phone? How many texts and tweets do you send? How often do you check in or post selfies and comments to social networking sites? Chances are, you do most of your communicating through communication technologies&#8212;texting, Instagram, Facebook, Twitter, Periscope, FaceTime, Vine, Snapchat, WhatsApp, or any of the hundreds of sites, apps, and tools that become available each day (and that often disappear just as quickly!).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p28" block_type="txt">Many of your waking hours are likely spent on the phone and computer&#8212;often at the same time. When you use these technologies to talk, text, post, tweet, e-mail, and chat, you engage in <termref term="mediated communication">mediated communication</termref>: communication with others that is separated, or &#8220;mediated,&#8221; by some type of technological device.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec2-1" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="62">
<section-metadata><section-title>Types of Mediated Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p29" block_type="txt-ni">The phrase <em>mediated communication</em> may make you think about &#8220;the media&#8221;&#8212;that is, online news and entertainment sites, video games, television channels, movies, radio stations, newspapers, and magazines. These are examples of <termref term="mass media">mass media</termref>: mediated communication vehicles that involve the sending of messages from content creators to huge, relatively anonymous audiences (Chaffee &#38; Metzger, 2001). The content in such media is created for public consumption and is mostly one-directional; that is, you don&#8217;t directly interact with anyone by reading or watching this content.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_63" block_type="page_start">63</p>
<box title="USING MEDIATED COMMUNICATION" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx1-1" block_type="bx1-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p30" block_type="bx1-txt"><strong>Every text, tweet, post, video, pin, or note you send through mediated channels (whether personal, professional, or for fun) is as much of a communication choice as the words you use in a face-to-face conversation. How much do you consider the functions and characteristics of your messages before sending them?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-2" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-3" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Csondy/iStock/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-3" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-4" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P04.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Take A Pix Media/agefotostock</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-4" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-5" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P03.jpg"/>
<asset_source>PYMCA/UIG via Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p31" block_type="txt">Although mass media are an important area of research for communication scholars, this chapter focuses on <termref term="social media">social media</termref>, which enable communicators to directly send and receive messages in real time or across time intervals to manage their personal and professional relationships. At work, for instance, most interactions take place over e-mail, texts, or phone calls. Many businesses use Skype (or other videoconferencing systems) to conduct employment interviews. Daily communication with friends, family, and romantic partners happens through social media&#8212;dropping parents a quick &#8220;Hi&#8221; by text message or catching up with friends through Facebook or video chat. As a student, you might participate in online discussion groups and make online presentations for classes. For an overview of the differences between mass media and social media, see <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-tab-1">Table 3.1.</link></p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx6-1" block_type="bx6">
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-tab-1" block_type="table" caption-placement="top">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tab-label">TABLE 3.1</phrase></strong> <strong>DIFFERENCES BETWEEN MASS MEDIA &#38; SOCIAL MEDIA</strong><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p32"><sup>1</sup></link></table_caption>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p32" block_type="txt-ni"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-tab-1"><sup>1</sup></link>Adapted from Chaffee &#38; Metzger (2001). VLADGRIN/Shutterstock</p>
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-5" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-6" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_03_T01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>VLADGRIN/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec2-2" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="63">
<section-metadata><section-title>Functions of Mediated Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p33" block_type="txt-ni">Even though the specific platforms, sites, and apps you use to communicate via social media change constantly, there are still established ways in which these tools meet your communication needs. As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch01.xml">Chapter 1</link> discusses, communication helps you meet three types of goals, and these apply to mediated communication as well:</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_64" block_type="page_start">64</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-2" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p34" block_type="bl-f"><em>Instrumental goals</em> are the practical objectives you want to achieve or tasks you want to accomplish. This includes using social media to find information, coordinate schedules, and confirm reservations. For example, college students find social posts to be the easiest way to get information about upcoming social events (Quan-Haase &#38; Young, 2010).</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p35" block_type="bl-m"><em>Relationship goals</em> include how you build, maintain, or terminate bonds with others. This is a popular way to use social media, allowing you to get in touch with people you haven&#8217;t spoken to in a while, share your own news, and even block or defriend people you aren&#8217;t close to anymore. Such tools are often at the center of our social lives. In the Alpha Chi Omega example discussed in our chapter opener, for instance, the women at the ball game weren&#8217;t taking and posting the selfies to celebrate <em>themselves</em> but to share the fun they were having at the game with friends and sorority sisters who weren&#8217;t able to attend.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p36" block_type="bl-l"><em>Self-presentation goals</em> involve presenting yourself in certain ways so that others view you as you want them to. Through photos, updates, posts, and comments, you create a public self. As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link> discusses, a <em>public self</em> is the self you present to others (Fenigstein, Scheier, &#38; Buss, 1975). In this chapter, we&#8217;ll explore how you use <em>online self-presentation</em> to create that self.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_65" block_type="page_start">65</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p37" block_type="txt">In addition to fulfilling such goals, mediated communication serves two other important functions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-3" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p38" block_type="bl-f"><em>Participating in professional and public communities</em> means you can engage with people outside your intimate networks of family and friends. For example, you could use e-mails or tweets to express your concerns about proposed new laws to government officials. Or you could deliver a virtual presentation to work team members at offsite locations. (We&#8217;ll discuss more about delivering speeches online in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch15.xml">Chapter 15</link>.) Using social media in a community-based fashion includes heightening public awareness of important causes, a practice known as <termref term="hashtag activism">hashtag activism</termref>. One notable example is #bringbackourgirls, which called public attention to the terrorist activity of Boko Haram in Nigeria.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p39" block_type="bl-m"><em>Alleviating boredom</em> through social media is a common experience (Quan-Haase &#38; Young, 2010). People often seamlessly integrate mediated communication into the less stimulating moments of their lives. You might text with coworkers during slow work shifts (&#8220;Are you as bored as I am?&#8221;) or chat online with friends when you need a break from studying.</p></li>
</list>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec2-3" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="65">
<section-metadata><section-title>Characteristics of Mediated Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p40" block_type="txt-ni">Since mediated communication serves different functions, you have choices in the types of media you use to communicate with others. Imagine that you&#8217;ve just received a great job offer. Would you share the good news with your roommate in person or through a text message? In either format, your message is essentially the same: &#8220;I got the job!&#8221; But the characteristics of your communication&#8212;including how you interact with your roommate, the nonverbal cues exchanged, and how long your message endures&#8212;will differ depending on the media device or app you choose.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p41" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Synchronous versus Asynchronous Communication.</strong></phrase> When you talk with someone face-to-face, you&#8217;re engaged in <termref term="synchronous communication">synchronous communication</termref>: a back-and-forth exchange of messages that occurs in real time. Some media devices enable synchronous communication, including phone conversations, instant messages, and videoconferences. By contrast, in <termref term="asynchronous communication">asynchronous communication</termref>, time lapses exist between messages. When you use e-mail, send a text message, or post to a social media site, a delay occurs before a response arrives or you may get no response at all.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_66" block_type="page_start">66</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p42" block_type="txt">Synchronous communication is best used when you&#8217;re communicating difficult or complicated messages. For example, you may want to use the phone or video chat to tell your family that you won&#8217;t be coming home for the holidays as planned. If you text them with the news, they may think you&#8217;re insensitive or incompetent (&#8220;What kind of daughter cancels holiday plans through a text?&#8221;). However, synchronous communication requires all the communicators to be available at the same time. That&#8217;s not always possible, especially when people live in different time zones or have conflicting work or life schedules. In these situations, asynchronous communication may be your only choice for sending and receiving messages. It is also appropriate for nonurgent, quick, and simple messages, such as letting a friend know you&#8217;re running a few minutes late for a lunch date.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p43" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Restriction of Nonverbal Information.</strong></phrase> Communicating face-to-face with others provides immediate access to <em>nonverbal</em> cues, such as facial expressions and tone of voice, which help you understand other people&#8217;s thoughts and feelings. When your roommate responds with a smile and a high-five after you tell her you got a new job, she clearly feels happy for you. As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch06.xml">Chapter 6</link> explains, nonverbal behaviors are undeniably an important part of your communication with others.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p44" block_type="txt">In mediated communication&#8212;especially those forms that involve text only&#8212;you get little or no nonverbal information. According to the <termref term="cues-filtered-out model">cues-filtered-out model</termref>, in this type of communication, many of the cues vital for making sense of messages are not available; they are &#8220;filtered out&#8221; (Culnan &#38; Markus, 1987). This makes mediated communication more difficult to understand than face-to-face communication. If you&#8217;re e-mailing or texting with someone, it&#8217;s almost impossible to tell if he or she is being sarcastic or sincere. In one study, 27 percent of respondents agreed that e-mail is likely to result in miscommunication of the senders&#8217; intended meaning, and almost 54 percent agreed that it&#8217;s relatively easy to misinterpret an e-mail message (Rainey, 2000). To help minimize such confusion, communicators use acronyms (LOL, SMH), emoticons, or emoji to convey their intent more clearly. But even these symbols are a poor substitute for the nonverbal cues available when communicating face-to-face.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p45" block_type="txt">The fact that nonverbal information is restricted during most mediated communication doesn&#8217;t necessarily mean that the interaction is less important or personal. According to <termref term="social information processing theory">social information processing theory</termref> (Walther, 1992), people communicating through social media compensate for the lack of nonverbal cues by taking more care when choosing their words. The result is that mediated communication, though &#8220;cue filtered,&#8221; can be just as personal as face-to-face interaction (Walther &#38; Parks, 2002).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_67" block_type="page_start">67</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx5-1" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p46" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>To help neutralize the cues-filtered-out model, a common practice is to use emoticons or emoji (like the ones shown here) to provide some nonverbal cues about the message&#8217;s intent. In what types of scenarios do you use such images to clarify the meaning of your text messages?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-7" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-8" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P05.jpg"/>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p47" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Message Life Span.</strong></phrase> A basic principle of communication is that there are no &#8220;take-backs&#8221; or do-overs. Everything you say becomes part of the permanent record of your relationship with others. So when you snap at your parents or insert a tasteless joke into a speech, you can&#8217;t turn back time and erase your error.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p48" block_type="txt">This is especially true in mediated communication. Every time you send a digital message (text, e-mail, tweet, video, or post), it stays in your account <em>and</em> in the accounts of those who received it. It also stays in the servers of companies hosting the accounts. Deleting a text, an e-mail, a post, or the entire account doesn&#8217;t make the information go away. Anyone with the right access can find it. Even apps that promote disappearing messages or pictures (like Snapchat) can be easily saved with a little know-how.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p49" block_type="txt">Digital messages thus have a long life span and are easily searchable, retrievable, and replicable (boyd, 2007). Why does this matter? One reason is because many employers check job applicants&#8217; social media profiles to get a sense of what the applicant is really like. Some even ask for applicants&#8217; passwords to closely examine their accounts (Garber, 2012). Although that is an extreme (and possibly illegal) case, it is commonplace for employers to Google potential new hires. If you Google your own name, what comes up? Search engines can easily find your digital trail and deliver it to anyone who wants it. Be mindful when sending text messages and e-mails or posting online, because you&#8217;re creating an enduring record of your communication that is easy to find and to share.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_68" block_type="page_start">68</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-2" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="68">
<section-metadata><section-title>Self-Presentation and Mediated Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p50" block_type="pul"><strong>Take a moment to think about how you&#8217;re dressed today. Are you wearing casual clothes or something more professional? You select your clothing to make a specific impression, based on what you&#8217;ll be doing and who you&#8217;ll be seeing. Likewise, when you select photos, post updates, and share information online, you create an impression that influences how others see you.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p51" block_type="txt-ni">If you have a social media account, look at your profile: the photos, status updates, or links you&#8217;ve posted and your list of friends. What does all this say about you? Are you fun and outgoing? A hard partier? Deeply philosophical? A humanitarian? A shopaholic? In a study of almost 400 Facebook profiles, researchers found that 92 percent of users posted a personal photograph, 83 percent made their wall public, and 55 percent indicated their sexual orientation (Nosko, Wood, &#38; Molema, 2010). You could learn a lot about someone just from that information alone!</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p52" block_type="txt">When you set up a social media profile, you make a series of decisions about how to present your self. Such choices determine your online <em>face</em>, or the positive self you want others to see (Goffman, 1955). Creating your online face is an important part of your online self-presentation, and it requires as much careful planning and management as does your in-person self-presentation.</p>
<box title="DOUBLE TAKE" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx3-1" block_type="bx3-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p53" block_type="bx3-t-c1"><strong>ONLINE FACE</strong> <image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-9" alt="image" src="images/and1.jpg"/> <strong>SELF-PRESENTATION</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p54" block_type="bx3-txt"><strong>Imagine you saw the images below posted to two new acquaintances&#8217; Facebook pages. Based on the photos, what would you perceive about the online face each is presenting? Why?</strong></p>
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-tab-2" numbered="false" number="false" block_type="">
<tbody>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-8" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-10" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P06.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Ed Jones/Staff/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-11" alt="image" src="images/and.jpg"/></td>
<td><figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-9" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-12" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P07.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Ross Gilmore/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure></td>
</tbody>
</table>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_69" block_type="page_start">69</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec2-4" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="69">
<section-metadata><section-title>Creating Your Online Face</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p55" block_type="txt-ni">Scholars studying mediated communication suggest that three elements largely determine your online face: your posted content, your e-mail and screen names, and your friends and professional connections.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p56" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Posted Content.</strong></phrase> Everything you post online communicates information about who you are and how you wish to be seen. A status update like, &#8220;Monster trucks one night, demolition derby the next&#8212;Gotta love the county fair!&#8221; or a tweet that reads, &#8220;&#36;1 oysters until 7 pm at Harpers&#8212;come hang with the gang!&#8221; communicates powerful messages about your tastes, interests, and social identity (you&#8217;re a &#8220;country&#8221; person; you&#8217;re a &#8220;foodie&#8221;). The same goes for posting, sharing, and tagging photographs and videos.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p57" block_type="txt">Online faces are far from objective, however. People post content to amplify positive personality characteristics, such as warmth, friendliness, and extraversion (Vazire &#38; Gosling, 2004). For instance, photos on social networking sites typically show groups of friends, giving the impression that the person in the profile is likable, fun, and popular (Ellison, Steinfield, &#38; Lampe, 2007). These positive and highly selective depictions of self generally work. When viewing someone&#8217;s profile, you tend to believe what you see and form the same impressions about the person that he or she intended (Gosling, Gaddis, &#38; Vazire, 2007).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p58" block_type="txt">Of course, it&#8217;s not just what you post about yourself that determines your online face&#8212;it&#8217;s also the content that others post about you. Research shows that when friends, family members, coworkers, or romantic partners post information about you, their content shapes others&#8217; perceptions of you even more powerfully than your own postings do&#8212;especially when their postings contradict your self-description (Walther, Van Der Heide, Kim, Westerman, &#38; Tong, 2008).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p59" block_type="txt">Why do others&#8217; posts have so much power? When evaluating someone&#8217;s online description, you consider the <termref term="warranting value">warranting value</termref> of the information presented&#8212;that is, the degree to which the information is supported by other people and outside evidence (Walther, Van Der Heide, Hamel, &#38; Schulman, 2009). Information that was obviously crafted by the person, that isn&#8217;t supported by others online, or that can&#8217;t be verified offline has <em>low warranting value</em>. For example, people may not trust an online profile in which you describe yourself as fun and outgoing when there are no posted comments from others to support your description. But your profile information has <em>high warranting value</em> if the social media feed has photos of you in social settings and relevant posted comments from others (<em>&#8220;You were SO MUCH fun to hang with last night!&#8221;</em>) (Walther et al., 2009).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p60" block_type="txt">The research on warranting value suggests that you need to manage online content posted by others that contradicts the self you want to present&#8212;even if you think such content is cute or funny. If you want to track what others are posting about you, set up a Google Alert or regularly search for your name and other identifying keywords. If anyone posts information about you that doesn&#8217;t match how you want to be seen, politely ask that person to delete it. For more on managing your online face, see <link href="#choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx7-1">How to Communicate: Removing an Embarrassing Post</link> on pages 70&#8211;71.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_70" block_type="page_start">70</p>
<box title="HOW TO COMMUNICATE &#124; Video Skills" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx7-1" block_type="bx7">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p61" block_type="bx7-h"><strong>REMOVING AN EMBARRASSING POST</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p62" block_type="bx7-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-13" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> One way to improve your communication competence is by adapting your messages to others&#8217; behaviors. Learn how to manage your online self-presentation by going to LaunchPad at <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong> and completing the <strong>How to Communicate video scenario</strong> for <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml">Chapter 3</link> to practice your skills.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p63" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>CONSIDER THIS:</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p64" block_type="bx7-txt">While hanging out with friends, you imitate how your boss flirts with customers, totally unaware that your friend Tim is shooting a video of your performance. The next day, you&#8217;re horrified to discover that Tim has posted the video online. You want him to take it down immediately, and ask him to meet with you right away.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p65" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>WHAT WOULD YOU DO?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p66" block_type="bx7-txt">To maintain a positive relationship, you&#8217;ll want to avoid sending a text message simply demanding that Tim remove the post. Instead, arrange to meet face-to-face or over the phone to talk about the post. As you complete the video activity, consider how the dialogue protects the in-person and the online face. Then, test your knowledge of key skills, and create your own responses to the <strong>What if? video prompts</strong>.</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-10" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-14" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_03_HTC_1.jpg"/>
<caption>&#8220;I saw that you posted a video of me imitating how my boss flirts with some of her customers . . . I&#8217;m so embarrassed.&#8221;</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p68" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-15" alt="image" src="images/1.jpg"/> <strong>BE SPECIFIC.</strong> Describe the exact post and your feelings about it. Avoid attacking or blaming language.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_71" block_type="page_start">71</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p69" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-16" alt="image" src="images/2.jpg"/> <strong>EXPLAIN WHY IT MATTERS TO YOU.</strong> State the personal impact of the post and other potential consequences.</p>
</box>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-11" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-17" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_03_HTC_2.jpg"/>
<caption>&#8220;I&#8217;m really worried that my boss will see it and be hurt. I also feel like it makes me look mean.&#8221;</caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p71" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-18" alt="image" src="images/3.jpg"/> <strong>POLITELY REQUEST</strong> that the post be removed. Use language that saves face for your friend.</p>
</box>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-12" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-19" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_03_HTC_2a.jpg"/>
<caption>&#8220;I know you meant no harm by it, but I would like for you to remove it.&#8221;</caption>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p73" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-20" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> <strong>WHAT IF? But what if things don&#8217;t work out as shown? Test your ability to adapt your communication by watching the What if? videos and planning a response for each situation.</strong></p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-1" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p74" block_type="bx7-nl-first">When Tim downplays your feelings&#8212;&#8220;I don&#8217;t see why you&#8217;re mad about it. No one knows who you&#8217;re imitating, and it&#8217;s funny&#8221;&#8212;how can you still maintain your online face?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p75" block_type="bx7-nl-last">What can you say if Tim reminds you of a time you embarrassed him? &#8220;You weren&#8217;t too concerned about being &#8216;mean&#8217; when you posted a photo of me passed out after AgFest last year.&#8221;</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_72" block_type="page_start">72</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx5-2" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p76" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Your online self-presentation is also influenced by the people you follow, the tags you use, and the posts you like. One advantage of social media is that these markers make it easy for you to find and follow people with similar interests.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-13" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-21" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P08.jpg"/>
<asset_source><link href="http://www.facebook.com">facebook.com</link></asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p77" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>E-mail and Screen Names.</strong></phrase> The name you use for your e-mail address, online profiles, or Web site tells others how you want to be perceived (Baym, 2010). Although it is tempting to underestimate their impact, these names create powerful impressions. On dating Web sites, for example, screen names that are playful or represent physical traits (&#8220;Fun2bwith,&#8221; &#8220;Blueeyes&#8221;) are rated by viewers as attractive (Whitty &#38; Buchanan, 2010). Neutral screen names (&#8220;0257&#8221;) or names suggesting wealth (&#8220;Silverspoon&#8221;) convey a sense that the individual is boring or arrogant (Whitty &#38; Buchanan, 2010).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p78" block_type="txt">However, what works for one site may not be a good idea in other contexts. You wouldn&#8217;t want to use your dating profile name (&#8220;Fun2bwith&#8221;) for an e-mail address on a job application. For example, Joe maintains a professional identity through his academic e-mail address (<link href="mailto:joseph.ortiz@scottsdalecc.edu">joseph.ortiz@scottsdalecc.edu</link>), which states his full name and the school where he teaches. But in fantasy baseball forums, his screen name&#8212;joeStros13&#8212;reflects a more casual identity. Steve does the same thing within online audio circles he belongs to that celebrate turntables, vinyl records, and tubed amplifiers: there, he is &#8220;The Analog Kid&#8221; (in honor of one of his favorite Rush songs). Carefully choose screen names based on the audience to which you are trying to appeal.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p79" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Friends and Professional Connections.</strong></phrase> Lists of your friends on Facebook, your professional connections on LinkedIn, and your followers on Twitter can also give impressions about your social status, political ideology, and other interests (Donath &#38; boyd, 2004). For example, if you&#8217;re linked to people who post frequently about animal rights, someone looking at your profile might assume that this cause is important to you, too. Even the number of friends listed on your profile creates impressions. In one study, individuals with about 300 friends on Facebook were viewed as more likable than those with 100 friends or a lot more than 300 friends (Tong, Van Der Heide, Langwell, &#38; Walther, 2008). Why? Having &#8220;too few&#8221; Facebook friends made people seem unpopular. Having &#8220;too many&#8221; made them appear to spend too much time online or seem indiscriminate in their choice of friends.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_73" block_type="page_start">73</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx4-1" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-14" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="3.1" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-22" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_03_F01.jpg"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 3.1</strong></phrase> <strong>THE 3</strong> <image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-23" alt="image" src="images/3p.jpg"/><strong>&#8217;S OF MANAGING YOUR ONLINE FACE</strong></caption>
<asset_source>WinMaster/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec2-5" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="73">
<section-metadata><section-title>Managing Your Online Face</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p80" block_type="txt-ni">Given how much communication occurs through social media, it&#8217;s essential to competently manage your online face. This can be especially challenging if your social media followers are a diverse mix of family, coworkers, friends, and perhaps even professors (Rui &#38; Stefone, 2013). Keeping in mind the three Ps of mediated communication&#8212;<em>powerful</em>, <em>public</em>, and <em>permanent</em>&#8212;can help you do just that.<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p81"><sup>2</sup></link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p81" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p80"><sup>2</sup></link>Personal communication with authors, May 13, 2008. This material was developed specifically for this text and published with permission of Dr. Malcolm Parks; it may not be reproduced without written consent of Dr. Parks and the authors.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p82" block_type="txt">Mediated communication is <em>powerful</em> in shaping others&#8217; impressions of you. When you communicate with others through social media, they&#8217;re more likely to think that your communication reflects your &#8220;true&#8221; self than they would be if you communicated face-to-face (Shedletsky &#38; Aitken, 2004). For example, if you e-mail a job application to a potential employer and don&#8217;t include a proper subject line, greeting, or message, they could conclude that you&#8217;re unprofessional.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_74" block_type="page_start">74</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p83" block_type="txt">Mediated communication is <em>public</em>. Always assume that the self you present to others through social media is going to be viewed by a much larger audience than you intended. E-mails, texts, tweets, photos, videos, comments, and status updates can be downloaded, saved, edited, copied, captured, and forwarded by recipients to others. Even if you have privacy settings enabled, there&#8217;s nothing stopping authorized friends from downloading posts and photos and distributing them to others.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p84" block_type="txt">Mediated communication is <em>permanent</em>. Blog posts, status updates, tweets, photos, and e-mails don&#8217;t &#8220;go away&#8221; when you send or delete them; they are saved by recipients and stored on servers and can be retrieved later. Assume that anything and everything you and others post about you online may still be available long into the future.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p85" block_type="txt">Keeping the three Ps of mediated communication in mind will help you create and maintain the online face you want others to see. Additionally, there are unique challenges for maintaining positive face when you communicate online in work groups&#8212;known as <em>virtual teams</em>&#8212;and when you deliver online presentations. <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch11.xml">Chapter 11</link> (Small Group Communication) considers specific skills for communicating in virtual teams, and <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch15.xml">Chapter 15</link> (Delivering Your Speech) addresses steps for making online presentations.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-3" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="74">
<section-metadata><section-title>Challenges of Mediated Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p86" block_type="pul"><strong>Sometimes it just happens. Without thinking, you send a sarcastic or rude message, forgetting about how it might affect the person receiving it. Although technology is convenient and useful, it also makes it easier to make poor communication choices, such as using harsh language, lying, and even harassing.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p87" block_type="txt-ni">In the movie <em>Catfish</em>, New York photographer Nev Schulman meets Megan Faccio through Facebook. He quickly falls for her, attracted by her photos and apparent musical talent. Over eight months, they develop an online romance through messages, e-mails, and phone calls. An aspiring singer, Megan impresses Nev with files she sends of her music. But Nev&#8217;s infatuation with Megan soon cools when he finds that her cover of the country standard &#8220;Tennessee Stud&#8221; was lifted from another artist on YouTube. When Nev finally decides to visit Megan at her home in rural Ishpeming, Michigan, what he discovers is a web of lies and fantasy. There is no Megan. She is the creation of another woman named Angela who pieced together a fictional Megan from the pictures, interests, and music of other people&#8217;s online profiles.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p88" block_type="txt">Nev fell for a common pitfall of mediated communication: people misrepresenting who they are for personal gain or satisfaction. In fact, online deception is so common that since 2012, Nev has been the host of <em>Catfish</em> on MTV, a television show in which he helps people find out if their online relationships are based on reality or lies. More often than not, the relationships are based on some form of deception. (Additionally, some people believe Nev himself to be deceptive&#8212;claiming he made up the scenario for the movie and none of it was real.)</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_75" block_type="page_start">75</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx5-3" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p89" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>MTV&#8217;s show <em>Catfish</em> chronicles one of the most common challenges of mediated communication: people using deception to lie about their identity and intentions when forming relationships online. Have you ever interacted with someone online who turned out to be not what he or she seemed?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-15" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-24" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P09.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; MTV/Courtesy: Everett Collection</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p90" block_type="txt">The harsh truth is that some people use mediated communication to lie, deceive, harass, and bully. Of course, these challenges aren&#8217;t limited to mediated messages, but certain characteristics of such communications make them especially likely to be used in this way.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec2-6" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="75">
<section-metadata><section-title>Causes of Mediated Communication Challenges</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p91" block_type="txt-ni">The limited amount of nonverbal information available in mediated communication, especially social media, can impact behavior in two ways: communicating in a more unconstrained or open fashion, and experiencing difficulty in feeling empathy.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p92" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Online Disinhibition.</strong></phrase> When using mediated communication, especially text-only social media, people often feel free to say things&#8212;good and bad&#8212;that they&#8217;d never say to someone face-to-face. This effect is known as <termref term="online disinhibition">online disinhibition</termref> (Suler, 2004). As noted earlier, much of mediated communication is <em>asynchronous</em>&#8212;you don&#8217;t interact with others in real time but exchange messages that are read and responded to later. When you&#8217;re communicating asynchronously, it&#8217;s almost as if time gets magically suspended (Suler, 2004). You know you&#8217;ll get responses to your messages, but you can choose when (and whether) to view those responses. This can make you more willing to openly express emotions that you might otherwise conceal if you knew you&#8217;d get an immediate response.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_76" block_type="page_start">76</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p93" block_type="txt">Mediated communication also provides a sense of <em>invisibility</em>. When you&#8217;re not sharing physical space with your communication partners, you feel as if they can&#8217;t really see or hear you. This makes you feel detached from the consequences of your messages. This sense is enhanced when you use screen names or identities that aren&#8217;t traceable to your offline self.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p94" block_type="txt">Even if you don&#8217;t mean to, online disinhibition increases the likelihood that you will use language that is more harsh, profane, rude, and blunt than what you&#8217;d normally use. Similarly, when receiving messages via social media, you should expect others to use language that is more direct and unedited than what they would use when talking face-to-face.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p95" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Empathy Deficits.</strong></phrase> As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link> discusses, <em>empathy</em> is the ability to &#8220;feel into&#8221; others&#8217; thoughts and emotions. When nonverbal cues are restricted, it can be hard to experience empathy. That&#8217;s because the same part of your brain that controls empathy also monitors nonverbal feedback (Goleman, 2006). During face-to-face encounters, you constantly track feedback from others as you watch their facial expressions, eye contact, and gestures, and listen to their tone of voice. This feedback enables you to feel empathy for them&#8212;to imagine what they&#8217;re thinking and feeling about your communication.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p96" block_type="txt">When you see or hear people react negatively to something you&#8217;re saying, you can instantly modify your communication to turn the interaction in a more positive direction. So if you say to your roommate, &#8220;Hey, let&#8217;s invite all our friends over this weekend for a <em>Game of Thrones</em> marathon! We can watch all of season 3,&#8221; and, in response, she rolls her eyes and says, &#8220;Oh, great,&#8221; in a sarcastic tone of voice, you know to ask what&#8217;s wrong. When she expresses concerns about the work involved in hosting such an extended party, you two have the opportunity to talk it over and agree to a compromise, like inviting fewer friends for just one night to watch a movie instead.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p97" block_type="txt">Now consider what happens when you don&#8217;t get nonverbal feedback during communication&#8212;such as when you&#8217;re texting, e-mailing, tweeting, or posting online. If you can&#8217;t perceive others&#8217; immediate nonverbal feedback, you can&#8217;t experience empathy and adjust your communication accordingly (Goleman, 2007). You might be confused by a WhatsApp message from your roommate saying, &#8220;oh, great;)&#8221; to your idea about the <em>Game of Thrones</em> marathon. In this situation, you are less able to <em>perspective-take</em>&#8212;that is, to see the situation and your communication from your partner&#8217;s point of view. Is your roommate excited? Sarcastic? Annoyed?</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p98" block_type="txt">This experience can lead to <termref term="empathy deficits">empathy deficits</termref>: a dramatic reduction in your ability to experience the other person&#8217;s feelings. Consequently, you may express yourself in blunt, tactless, and inappropriate ways&#8212;like &#8220;shouting&#8221; by using capitalized words or communicating things you&#8217;d never say over the phone or face-to-face. For example, you assume that your roommate&#8217;s text means she&#8217;s dismissing your idea for a <em>Game of Thrones</em> marathon, and you reply, &#8220;FINE! You don&#8217;t have to be involved!!!&#8221; Complicating matters further, people on the receiving end of your communication have the same deficit. Their online messages are less sensitive and less tactful as well, even if they don&#8217;t mean it any more than you do.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_77" block_type="page_start">77</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_78" block_type="page_start">78</p>
<box title="MAKING COMMUNICATION CHOICES" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx2-1" block_type="bx2-v2-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p99" block_type="bx2-t"><strong>WHY DIDN&#8217;T YOU AT LEAST TEXT ME?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p100" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>1</strong></phrase> <strong>CONSIDER THE DILEMMA</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p101" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">It was only a weekend trip, but Peyton&#8217;s leaving still bothered you. The two of you were inseparable since you started dating four weeks ago. Adding to your uneasiness was the thought of Peyton traveling to Las Vegas&#8212;aka &#8220;Sin City.&#8221; As you part ways at the airport, you wave your phone and say, &#8220;Don&#8217;t forget to stay in touch.&#8221; &#8220;Of course!&#8221; Peyton replies.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p102" block_type="bx2-txt">Shortly after Peyton&#8217;s scheduled arrival time, you send a text: &#8220;Did you make it in ok?&#8221; No response. After waiting 30 minutes, you send another text, &#8220;Hey, make it to Vegas?&#8221; An hour later, Peyton finally texts back, &#8220;yes, flt was on time. Training til 5. Call then.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p103" block_type="bx2-txt">The day passes quickly as you run errands and study. When you finally notice the time, it&#8217;s after 7:00 p.m. and Peyton still hasn&#8217;t called. Since Las Vegas is in your same time zone, you&#8217;re certain the training is done by now. Around 8:30 p.m. you text Peyton, &#8220;Still training? What&#8217;s going on?&#8221; No response. When you try to call, Peyton&#8217;s voice mail greets you immediately. You don&#8217;t leave a message.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p104" block_type="bx2-txt">Just after midnight your phone rings. It&#8217;s Peyton. &#8220;I&#8217;m sorry I didn&#8217;t call earlier. We went to dinner and ended up walking the strip afterwards, and . . .&#8221; Angrily you interrupt, &#8220;Yeah, whatever. It&#8217;s not hard to text and let me know. Hope you&#8217;re having a good time. I&#8217;ll talk to you tomorrow,&#8221; and then hang up.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p105" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>2</strong></phrase> <strong>CONNECT THE RESEARCH</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p106" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">Romantic couples use mobile phones to stay in contact, coordinate their plans, and flirt with each other (Miller-Ott, Kelly, &#38; Duran, 2012). When couples cannot be physically together, mobile phones provide ongoing availability for staying connected. But the ongoing availability comes at a price. Phones can be a way of checking up on your partner, and they can create unnecessary interruptions or cause hurt feelings when a text message does not get an immediate reply.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p107" block_type="bx2-txt">Couples experience tension when they lack clear rules about using mobile phones in their relationship (Miller-Ott et al., 2012; Duran, Kelly, &#38; Rotaru, 2011). Rules are mutually understood agreements about the appropriate use of cell phones for communicating with each other. Romantic partners often argue about excessive phone calling and texting or the failure to answer phone calls or texts (Duran et al., 2011). Although they are not written, rules emerge when couples communicate their expectations and preferences about how to use cell phones in the relationship.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p108" block_type="bx2-txt">Negotiating rules is important for keeping couples happy about their ongoing availability and use of cell phones. One study found that romantic couples who mutually agreed that they would not fight through cell-phone conversations or texts reported high relationship satisfaction (Miller-Ott et al., 2012).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p109" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>3</strong></phrase> <strong>COMMUNICATE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p110" block_type="bx2-txt-ni">Before making a communication choice, consider the facts of the situation and the research on rules for using mobile phones in romantic relationships. Also, reflect on what you&#8217;ve learned about synchronous and asynchronous communication (pp. 65&#8211;66), online disinhibition (pp. 75&#8211;76), flaming (p. 79), and mediated communication competence (pp. 80&#8211;83). Then answer these questions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-2" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p111" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">What factors could have influenced Peyton&#8217;s responses to your text messages? How might your self-esteem affect your view of the situation?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p112" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">Would you consider your text messages and phone call excessive? Were Peyton&#8217;s delayed responses disrespectful? If you had negotiated some rules for being in touch before Peyton left, what would be some reasonable expectations?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p113" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">What are you going to say to Peyton the next day?</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx5-4" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p114" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>When you communicate face-to-face, you have the advantage of getting real-time feedback from the other person. But communicating online restricts feedback, which can lead to empathy deficits. This is a common problem at work, where busy schedules and deadlines cause people to use mediated communication channels incompetently.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-16" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-25" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P10.jpg"/>
<asset_source>RUTH FREMSON/The New York Times/Redux Pictures</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec2-7" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="78">
<section-metadata><section-title>Types of Mediated Communication Challenges</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p115" block_type="txt-ni">When people experience online disinhibition and empathy deficits, they&#8217;re more likely to encounter challenges in mediated communication. The most common of these are digital deception, flaming and trolling, and online harassment and cyberbullying.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p116" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Digital Deception.</strong></phrase> Anyone who sends messages that intentionally mislead or create a false belief in recipients is committing <termref term="digital deception">digital deception</termref> (Hancock, 2007). Digital deception can take several forms. One form is <termref term="identity-based digital deception">identity-based digital deception</termref>, whereby someone falsely misrepresents his or her identity or gender (Hancock, 2007). Some people exaggerate or enhance aspects of their identity online. In the movie <em>Catfish</em>, Angela deceived Nev by lying about her name, age, physical appearance, and musical abilities. Although that was a special case, similar deception is common on dating sites, where people exaggerate their education and income levels and lower their weight and age (J. A. Hall, Park, Song, &#38; Cody, 2010).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_79" block_type="page_start">79</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx5-5" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p117" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>In addition to not engaging with anyone trolling or flaming online, you can also take measures to report inappropriate or obscene messages. Most platforms (like Instagram, shown) allow you to report or block users&#8212;an unfortunate but necessary function.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-17" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-26" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P11.jpg"/>
<asset_source><link href="http://www.instagram.com">www.instagram.com</link></asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p118" block_type="txt">Another form of digital deception is <termref term="message-based digital deception">message-based digital deception</termref>, which is the manipulation of information with the intent of misleading recipients (Hancock, 2007). This type of deception can include <termref term="butler lies">butler lies</termref>, which people use to avoid conversation, prevent embarrassment, or simply be polite (Hancock &#38; Toma, 2009). For example, you ignore a friend&#8217;s text but later reply saying, &#8220;just got your message.&#8221; Message-based digital deception also includes serious lies that can devastate personal, social, and work relationships (DePaulo, Kirkendol, Kashy, Wyer, &#38; Epstein, 1996). Examples include texting your spouse that you&#8217;re in a work meeting to cover up an affair, or e-mailing a professor that you missed an assignment due to illness when in fact it&#8217;s just because you were unprepared.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p119" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Flaming and Trolling.</strong></phrase> If you&#8217;ve ever received mediated messages that are hostile, insulting, or profane, you know they can be hurtful. When people say vicious and aggressive things online that they would never say in person, they are <termref term="flaming">flaming</termref>. Flaming is a direct outcome of online disinhibition and empathy deficits: when you feel little empathy toward others and also feel comparatively &#8220;invisible,&#8221; you&#8217;re more likely to communicate in inappropriate, destructive ways.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p120" block_type="txt">To reduce the likelihood of flaming in your own mediated communication, draft text messages, e-mails, and posts and then reread them before sending, asking yourself, &#8220;Would I say the same thing to this person&#8217;s face?&#8221; If your answer is no, then don&#8217;t send the message. Instead, delete it and consider more constructive ways to express your thoughts.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p121" block_type="txt">Some people post flame messages on purpose to start fights, a practice known as <termref term="trolling">trolling</termref>. People troll for their own enjoyment or because they&#8217;re bored (Donath, 1999). Read the comments for popular YouTube videos, and you&#8217;ll see trolling at work (&#8220;My 3-year-old sings and plays better than this sucky band!&#8221;). The best response to trolls is to ignore them. But this is often easier said than done. Trolls can be very disruptive to online communities because their intent is to cause discord, and they will often continue to post until disruption is achieved. When a hostile comment is posted online, it&#8217;s not unusual to see the acronym <em>DNFTT</em> (Do not feed the trolls) soon follow, as a warning not to &#8220;take the bait.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p122" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Online Harassment and Cyberbullying.</strong></phrase> Some texts, e-mails, or postings constitute <termref term="online harassment">online harassment</termref>: mediated messages perceived by the recipient as disturbing, threatening, or obsessive (Walker, Sockman, &#38; Koehn, 2011). For instance, your roommate&#8212;much to your embarrassment and against your direct requests not to&#8212;repeatedly takes pictures of you drinking at parties and then posts them on Instagram. Or a coworker forwards e-mails with sexist humor and images to you at work, even after you ask him to stop. Never ignore this kind of communication. If it happens, directly and clearly ask the person to remove the post or to stop sending the e-mails. If the person refuses, contact people in positions of authority (managers, resident advisers, professors, parents) and ask for advice on what to do.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_80" block_type="page_start">80</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p123" block_type="txt">Online harassment can turn into <termref term="cyberbullying">cyberbullying</termref> if the communication patterns become persistent and are used to exert power over you (Walker et al., 2011; Wolak, Mitchell, &#38; Finkelhor, 2006). Much like face-to-face bullying, cyberbullying is intended to cause social embarrassment, inflict emotional pain, or damage a person&#8217;s reputation. Although cyberbullying largely occurs among teens, it can also happen in the workplace in the form of threatening e-mails or voice mails and sexually charged material (White, 2010). If you believe you&#8217;re being cyberbullied, firmly tell the bully to stop, and keep written records of the offending messages. If the bullying doesn&#8217;t stop, meet with an authority figure (such as a school or human resources administrator) to describe what&#8217;s taking place and to ask for help. Most important, if the bullying has you fearing for your physical safety, immediately report it to local law enforcement. Many states have laws to protect victims of cyberbullying. If you need help with handling cyberbullying, refer to <link href="http://www.stopbullying.gov.">www.stopbullying.gov.</link></p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-4" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="80">
<section-metadata><section-title>Using Mediated Communication Competently</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p124" block_type="pul"><strong>You probably spend a lot of time playing with the various features of a new phone or tablet, but it&#8217;s just as important to learn how to communicate competently using technology. Otherwise, you might make some missteps&#8212;like sending lengthy text messages when a phone call would&#8217;ve been easier, or sounding more aggressive than you intended.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p125" block_type="txt-ni">Among the news media that covered the Alpha Chi Omega selfie controversy was <link href="http://www.AZCentral.com">AZCentral.com</link>, the premier online source for Arizona news and information. The Web site encourages readers to comment and discuss news stories posted on its site. But there&#8217;s one catch. You must use your Facebook account to post comments to AZCentral news stories. Why? Because the news staff wants to remove invisibility and discourage readers from posting flaming comments. And to prevent trolls from creating fake Facebook accounts, AZCentral requires readers to have a profile photo and at least four friends before comments are made visible on its site.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p126" block_type="txt">AZCentral, and other reputable news agencies, want to ensure that public commentary on news stories meets standards for online competence: that the posts are respectful and free of personal attacks. You can demonstrate competence when using social media by observing the following suggestions.<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p127"><sup>3</sup></link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p127" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p126"><sup>3</sup></link>Material for the first four points is published with permission of Dr. Malcolm Parks; it may not be reproduced without written consent of Dr. Parks and the authors.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_81" block_type="page_start">81</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-3" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p128" block_type="nl-v0-f"><termref term="Know when to use mediated communication versus face-to-face">Know when to use mediated communication versus face-to-face</termref>. In many situations, mediated communication is more time efficient than in-person communication. For instance, messaging a friend to remind her of a coffee date makes more sense than dropping by her workplace, and it&#8217;s probably quicker and less disruptive than calling her. But mediated communication is not the best approach for giving in-depth and lengthy explanations, detailing problems, or conveying important decisions. This fact is intuitively known by young adults, who recognize that communicating through mobile devices is less personal and more likely to cause misunderstandings than communicating face-to-face (Pettegrew &#38; Day, 2015).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p129" block_type="nl-v0-mid">Since it isn&#8217;t practical (or necessary) to interact face-to-face on every issue, consider these guidelines in determining the best medium for your message. First, <em>consider the message itself</em>. Handle emotional messages face-to-face. If this isn&#8217;t possible, use synchronous communication (a phone call or video chat) so that you can better monitor and respond to the other person&#8217;s reactions. With complex and difficult messages, consider using more than one medium. For example, hold a meeting to explain work policy changes and then follow up by e-mailing a summary of your main points or additional details to the meeting attendees. Second, <em>consider the recipient of your message</em>. Does he or she prefer certain means of communication? If so, adapt your format accordingly. For instance, your aunt may not respond to an Evite for a graduation party, but she will open an invitation she receives in the mail.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p130" block_type="nl-v0-mid"><termref term="Remember the three Ps">Remember the three Ps</termref>. Always remember that mediated communication is <em>powerful</em>, <em>public</em>, and <em>permanent</em>. The things you say and do online endure. Old e-mails, photographs, videos, messages, and blogs&#8212;all of these may still be accessible years after you first send them. Think before you post.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p131" block_type="nl-v0-mid"><termref term="Practice creating drafts">Practice creating drafts</termref>. Because mediated communication makes it easy to flame, many of us impulsively fire off messages that we later regret. Instead, get into the habit of saving posts, texts, and e-mail messages as drafts. Then revisit the drafts later and edit them as needed for appropriateness and effectiveness. You may be surprised at how a little time can give you perspective on a message. And don&#8217;t forget that sometimes the most competent mediated communication is none at all. If you are reviewing a draft and realize it&#8217;s only going to cause unnecessary damage, delete it.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p132" block_type="nl-v0-mid"><termref term="Use clear language and provide enough detail">Use clear language and provide enough detail</termref>. Without feedback, people often misinterpret mediated messages. To avoid misunderstandings, try to use the clearest words possible. Avoid slang, jargon, and abbreviations unless you know the receiver will understand them and interpret them correctly. This is especially true when giving online presentations or participating in videoconference meetings, when it is important that your audience understand your messages clearly.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_82" block_type="page_start">82</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p133" block_type="nl-v0-mid">In addition, provide enough detail in your messages. In the rush of texting, we often resort to the simplest, shortest messages possible. Take a bit more time to provide enough detail so that the other person has some context for your message. If you text your spouse &#8220;home 2 hrs late,&#8221; he might wonder if something bad has happened. If your text says, &#8220;Still working. Be home 2 hrs late,&#8221; he can relax, knowing that you&#8217;re OK. For more on how to create understandable messages, see <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml">Chapter 5</link>, pages 120&#8211;122.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p134" block_type="nl-v0-fl"><termref term="Always show respect for others">Always show respect for others</termref>. Empathy deficits can make it hard to communicate in sensitive, respectful ways. So when you&#8217;re communicating through social media, put extra energy into <em>perspective-taking</em>, or seeing things from other people&#8217;s point of view, and <em>empathic concern</em>&#8212;becoming aware of how other people are feeling and experiencing compassion for them. As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch02.xml">Chapter 2</link> explains (pp. 53&#8211;57), this will help you experience and express <em>empathy</em> for other people. Demonstrating kindness, caring, and concern in every form of mediated communication will go far to reduce tensions, build rapport, and create more positive outcomes in all your communication.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_83" block_type="page_start">83</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx4-2" block_type="bx4">
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-18" block_type="figure" numbered="true" number="3.2" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="medium" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-27" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_03_F02.jpg"/>
<caption><phrase block_type="fig-label"><strong>FIGURE 3.2</strong></phrase> <strong>PRACTICING COMPETENT COMMUNICATION ONLINE</strong></caption>
<asset_source>Bplanet/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-bx5-6" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p135" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>The convenience of mediated communication sometimes makes it easy to forget its specific challenges and the time it can take to use it competently. Before sending out your next quick text or multitasking between several apps, take a moment to be sure you are sending the message you intend.</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-fig-19" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-28" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_03_P12.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Fancy Collection/SuperStock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p136" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-29" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/><strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_84" block_type="page_start">84</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-5" block_type="cr-h" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="84">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER 3 REVIEW</section-title></section-metadata>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-6" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="84">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER RECAP</section-title></section-metadata>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-4" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p137" block_type="cr-bl-v0">There are two types of <termref term="mediated communication">mediated communication</termref>: <termref term="mass media">mass media</termref> and <termref term="social media">social media</termref>. Social media help you meet your instrumental, relationship, and self-presentation goals.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p138" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Since social media can limit the amount of nonverbal information you receive, the <termref term="social information processing theory">social information processing theory</termref> suggests that you compensate for this by taking more care with the words you choose to use.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p139" block_type="cr-bl-v0">When creating and managing your online face, remember the three Ps of mediated communication for any content you post&#8212;<em>powerful</em>, <em>public</em>, and <em>permanent</em>.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p140" block_type="cr-bl-v0"><termref term="Online disinhibition">Online disinhibition</termref> and <termref term="empathy deficits">empathy deficits</termref> are two possible causes of mediated communication challenges, such as <termref term="digital deception">digital deception</termref>, <termref term="flaming">flaming</termref>, <termref term="trolling">trolling</termref>, <termref term="online harassment">online harassment</termref>, and <termref term="cyberbulling">cyberbulling</termref>.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p141" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Knowing how to competently use mediated communication can help you improve your relationships, your work life, and your online presentation skills.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p142" block_type="cr-txt-ni"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-30" alt="image" src="images/launchpad.jpg"/> LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> offers unique video scenarios and encourages self-assessment through adaptive quizzing. Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong> to get access.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p143" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-31" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> LearningCurve practice quizzes</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p144" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-32" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> How to Communicate video scenarios</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p145" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-33" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Video clips that illustrate key concepts</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-7" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="84">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p146" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p28">Mediated communication, p. 62</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p147" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p29">Mass media, p. 62</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p148" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p31">Social media, p. 63</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p149" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p38">Hashtag activism p. 65</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p150" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p41">Synchronous communication, p. 65</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p151" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p41">Asynchronous communication, p. 66</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p152" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p44">Cues-filtered-out model, p. 66</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p153" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p45">Social information processing theory, p. 66</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p154" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p59">Warranting value, p. 69</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p155" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p92">Online disinhibition, p. 75</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p156" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p98">Empathy deficits, p. 76</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p157" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p116">Digital deception, p. 78</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p158" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p116">Identity-based digital deception, p. 78</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p159" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p118">Message-based digital deception, p. 79</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p160" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p118">Butler lies, p. 79</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p161" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p119">Flaming, p. 79</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p162" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p121">Trolling, p. 79</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p163" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p122">Online harassment, p. 79</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p164" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch03.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch3-p123">Cyberbullying, p. 80</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_85" block_type="page_start">85</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-8" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="85">
<section-metadata><section-title>POP QUIZ</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p165" block_type="cr-wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-img-34" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> Looking for more review questions? <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you master key concepts from this chapter. Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-question-1" number="1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p166" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">If you want to have an important conversation with a family member, you should first try to engage in a real-time conversation, or &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-4" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p167" block_type="cr-ll-v1">asynchronous communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p168" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">synchronous communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p169" block_type="cr-ll-v1">public communication</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p170" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">nonverbal feedback</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-question-2" number="2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p171" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">When evaluating someone&#8217;s online face, which of the following do you consider as part of the content&#8217;s warranting value?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-5" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p172" block_type="cr-ll-v1">If it is supported by others</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p173" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">If it can be verified by alternative sources</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p174" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">If it is obviously crafted by the person posting it</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p175" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">All of the above are correct</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-question-3" number="3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p176" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Which of the following is a main cause of <em>empathy deficits</em>?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-6" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p177" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Increased feeling of online disinhibition</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p178" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Sense of invisibility when online</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p179" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Lack of nonverbal feedback</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p180" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Use of identity-based digital deception</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-question-4" number="4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p181" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95; occurs when people say or do negative things online that they would never do in person.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-7" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p182" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Flaming</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p183" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Butler lie</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p184" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Cyberbullying</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p185" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Deception</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-question-5" number="5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p186" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Which of the following is <em>not</em> one of the chapter&#8217;s suggestions for competently using mediated communication?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-8" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p187" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Avoiding misunderstandings by using clear language and appropriate amounts of detail</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p188" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Creating message drafts and revisiting them later before sending</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p189" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Using perspective-taking and empathic concern when communicating online</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p190" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Limiting mediated communication to a couple of messages per day</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-sec1-9" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch3" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="85">
<section-metadata><section-title>ACTIVITIES</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-exp4-1" block_type="mn4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p191" block_type="cr-wl-txt">For more activities, visit LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> at <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p192" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Analyzing Your Online Face</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p193" block_type="cr-txt">Take one of your online profiles for a social media site&#8212;Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, Google&#43;. Working with a classmate, use the three Ps of mediated communication&#8212;powerful, public, and permanent&#8212;to evaluate each other&#8217;s profile. What face do you perceive your partner to have? Is it accurate? Based on what your partner perceived, how can you improve your profile?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p194" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Flaming and Trolling in Action</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch3-p195" block_type="cr-txt">Look at the discussion thread in the comment section of a recent online news article about a controversial topic (e.g., <link href="http://www.washingtonpost.com">www.washingtonpost.com</link> or <link href="http://www.nytimes.com">www.nytimes.com</link>). Identify any instances of flaming, trolling, or harassment, and analyze how other commenters responded to these posts. Work with a small group of classmates to prepare a group report on how these comments worked with or violated the guidelines for mediated communication competence suggested in this chapter. Present the report in class.</p></li>
</list>
</section>
</chapter>
</manuscript>