<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<manuscript xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" manuscript-id="05" name="" title="MCC_Chapter_05_DJHrev" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../xsd/digfir_manuscript.xsd">
<chapter number="5" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-chapter-5" title="5: Verbal Communication" start-numbering-at="5" numbered="true">
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-1a" block_type="intro" title="Chapter Introduction" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="114">
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_114" block_type="page_start">114</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p1" block_type="chapter_number">5</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p2" block_type="chapter_title">Verbal Communication</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p3" block_type="co-txt-ni"><phrase block_type="dropcap">A</phrase>s a poet, motivational speaker, and actor, Ed Mabrey spends his life carefully crafting his words. His hard work has paid off. Mabrey is a two-time winner of the Individual World Poetry Slam Championship (2007 and 2012).<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p4"><sup>1</sup></link> In this annual competition featuring dozens of the world&#8217;s best performance poets&#8212;each of whom is a champion in his or her home region&#8212;Mabrey and others get to show off their unique talents. Mabrey&#8217;s recent victories have cemented his status as one of the finest performance poets ever: two-time Haiku slam champion, 2012 Poetry Slam Artist of the Year, and four-time National Poetry Slam finalist.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p4" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p3"><sup>1</sup></link>All content that follows adapted from Poetry Slam, Inc. (<link href="http://www.www.poetryslam.com">www.poetryslam.com</link>), and Seattle Poetry Slam (2013).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p5" block_type="co-txt">Poetry slam is the competitive art of performance poetry. Unlike written poetry, which is designed to be read, performance poetry is created to be spoken in front of a live audience. At poetry slams, judges assess poets and award them points. Although slams vary in their rules, most require that the poems be brief and that poets perform without props, costumes, or musical instruments. Poets are judged solely on their choice of words and the emotion with which these words are communicated to the audience.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p6" block_type="co-txt">The poetry performed at slams varies widely in topic&#8212;everything from comedy to social commentary, inner reflection to outward expression of love. Champion Ed Mabrey&#8217;s poetry focuses on his view of world events, his close relationships, and even casual encounters. His poem &#8220;Pursuit of Happyness,&#8221; for example, is about a conversation with a homeless person at a Subway restaurant.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p7" block_type="co-txt">No longer limited to coffee shops or bookstores, poetry slams also exist online. Poetry Slam, Inc., which organizes national and international competitions, hosts a video slam contest, in which poets submit videotaped performances and have online audience members vote for the one they like best. A recent winner of the video slam was Kait Rokowski, who provided a blistering performance regarding gender roles and sexual assault (you can see Kait&#8217;s poem on YouTube).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p8" block_type="co-txt">But despite the diversity among poets, poetic content, and medium, the common theme that runs throughout performance poetry is the importance of carefully choosing clear, honest, and understandable language packed with powerful meaning. Poets seeking to win slams can&#8217;t just craft language into small, elegant poems. They must verbally communicate their creations to audiences in a competent fashion. Although poetry slams are highly competitive&#8212;poets intensely vie with one another for points and tenths of points&#8212;they are ultimately about celebrating the communicative power of the spoken word. As poet Allan Wolf describes, &#8220;The points are not the point; the point is poetry.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_115" block_type="page_start">115</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-1" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-1" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P01.jpg"/>
<asset_source>AP Photo/Bebeto Matthews</asset_source>
</figure>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_116" block_type="page_start">116</p>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-exp1-1" block_type="mn1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p9" block_type="co-h"><strong>CHAPTER OUTLINE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p10" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-1"><strong>The Nature of Verbal Communication</strong> 116</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p11" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-2"><strong>Verbal Communication Skills</strong> 119</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p12" block_type="co-toc"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-3"><strong>Verbal Communication Challenges</strong> 127</link></p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p13" block_type="txt-ni">You may not be a performance poet like Ed Mabrey or Kait Rokowski, facing audiences and judges who evaluate you through points, but you are judged just the same, every single day, on the words you choose. If you competently communicate to others, you&#8217;re awarded &#8220;points&#8221; in the form of people liking you, being influenced by you, or judging you to have desirable skills&#8212;like being &#8220;an amazing speaker&#8221; or &#8220;a skilled conversationalist.&#8221; Regardless of your rhyme or reason, your words pack a potent punch in shaping others&#8217; impressions of you. As a consequence, it&#8217;s important to understand the power of verbal communication and how to use it competently. In this chapter, you&#8217;ll learn:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-1" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p14" block_type="bl-f">The four defining features of language</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p15" block_type="bl-m">Strategies for creating understandable messages and taking responsibility for your words</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p16" block_type="bl-m">How to use language that avoids gender bias and is mindful of cultural differences</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p17" block_type="bl-m">Ways to manage the challenging aspects of verbal communication</p></li>
</list>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-exp2-1" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p18" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-2" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-1" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="116">
<section-metadata><section-title>The Nature of Verbal Communication</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p19" block_type="pul"><strong>Whenever you write, speak, sign, tweet, or text, you&#8217;re using language to convey meaning to others. But the words you choose also communicate powerful messages about who you are in relation to your listeners. Understanding how verbal communication works will help you use language more competently in every area of your life.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p20" block_type="txt-ni">Your days are filled with verbal communication. You talk with your professor during her office hours, then text your roommate to see if you can get a ride home. You e-mail group members about an upcoming project, then give a speech in front of your communication class. You chat with coworkers after your shift, then Skype with your partner stationed overseas. Through all of these exchanges, you employ <termref term="verbal communication">verbal communication</termref>&#8212;the use of spoken or written language to interact with others. Because language is the basis of verbal communication, understanding the nature of language is key for improving your verbal communication skills. Language has four defining features: it is symbolic, it is governed by rules, it conveys meaning, and it is intertwined with culture.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-1" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="116">
<section-metadata><section-title>Language Is Symbolic</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p21" block_type="txt-ni">When Steve was in sixth grade, his friend Ed would play an annoying word game with people. Ed would point to a table and say, &#8220;What&#8217;s that?&#8221; The unwitting victim would answer, &#8220;It&#8217;s a table, duh!&#8221; Ed would say, &#8220;No, that&#8217;s just the <em>word</em> we use to represent it. What is it <em>really</em>?&#8221; The person would pause, then respond, &#8220;Oh, I see. OK, it&#8217;s wood and metal and plastic.&#8221; &#8220;No,&#8221; Ed would laugh, &#8220;those are just <em>words</em> that we use to <em>represent</em> what it is. What is it <em>really</em>?&#8221; About this time the person would get fed up with Ed&#8217;s game and walk away.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_117" block_type="page_start">117</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p22" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Ed&#8217;s game illustrates the first defining feature of language: it is symbolic. When items are used to represent other things, they are considered <termref term="symbols">symbols</termref>. In verbal communication, words are the primary symbols used to represent people, objects, events, and ideas (Foss, Foss, &#38; Trapp, 1991). Thus, the word <em>table</em> refers to an object with a flat surface and legs to support it. You could just as well call it a &#8220;cotknee&#8221; or some other term. If you did, nothing about the actual object would change&#8212;just its name. As psychologist Erich Fromm noted, words only point to our experience of the world; they are not the experience. All languages are collections of symbols in the form of words people use to communicate.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-2" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="117">
<section-metadata><section-title>Language Is Governed by Rules</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p23" block_type="txt-ni">Two types of rules govern the use of language. The first type is <termref term="constitutive rules">constitutive rules</termref>, which define words&#8217; meanings. Constitutive rules tell you what words stand for what objects (Searle, 1965). For example, in the English language, <em>dog</em> represents a four-legged domesticated animal that is a common household pet. In Spanish, the word <em>perro</em> represents this same animal. Constitutive rules involving informal or metaphorical expressions can make things challenging when you&#8217;re trying to learn a new language. For example, someone new to English may get confused when a friend says, &#8220;My dogs are tired,&#8221; if the speaker really means, &#8220;My feet hurt.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p24" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">The second type comprises <termref term="regulative rules">regulative rules</termref>, which control how you use language. Regulative rules guide everything from spelling to grammar to conversational structure. Examples in the English language include &#8220;Add an <em>s</em> or an <em>es</em> to a noun to create its plural form&#8221; and &#8220;When someone asks you a question, you should answer.&#8221;</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-3" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="117">
<section-metadata><section-title>Language Conveys Meaning</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p25" block_type="txt-ni">Language enables you to convey meaning to others in two ways. The first is the literal meaning of your words, as agreed on by members of your culture. These are known as <termref term="denotative meanings">denotative meanings</termref>. Such meanings are what you find in dictionaries; for example, <em>family</em> means &#8220;a group of individuals related through common ancestry, legal means, or other strong emotional or social bonds.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p26" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">But the word <em>family</em> evokes different meanings for different people. Some may hear the word and immediately think, &#8220;Individuals I can count on for love and support.&#8221; Others may hear it and think, &#8220;People who are always judging me!&#8221; Such variations represent <termref term="connotative meanings">connotative meanings</termref>&#8212;the meanings you associate with words based on your life experiences. What does the word <em>family</em> mean to you?</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p27" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Denotative and connotative meanings can create confusion if you don&#8217;t manage them carefully. For example, suppose your friend aces an exam that you flunked. You text her, &#8220;I hate u!&#8221; The denotative meaning suggests you feel hatred toward your friend. But the connotative meaning&#8212;your real message&#8212;is &#8220;I&#8217;m envious but proud of you.&#8221; If you and your friend have a history of communicating with each other in this way, your friend will probably read your message as you intend. But with a person you don&#8217;t know as well, an &#8220;I hate u!&#8221; text could backfire. To use verbal communication competently, choose your words carefully and clarify connotative meanings if there&#8217;s a chance someone could misunderstand your message.</p>
<box title="DOUBLE TAKE" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx3-1" block_type="bx3-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p28" block_type="bx-v3-tc"><strong>CONNOTATIVE MEANINGS: THIS</strong> <image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-3" alt="image" src="images/OR.jpg"/> <strong>THAT?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p29" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Depending on your personal experiences, the word <em>gambling</em> can have vastly different connotative meanings. When a friend says she is going gambling, do you think that sounds fun, boring, wasteful, or something else entirely?</strong></p>
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-untab-1" block_type="un_table">
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-2" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-4" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Tim Pannell/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-5" alt="image" src="images/OR1.jpg"/></td>
<td>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-4" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-6" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P03.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Ken Seet/Corbis</asset_source>
</figure></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_118" block_type="page_start">118</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-4" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="118">
<section-metadata><section-title>Language and Culture Are Intertwined</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p30" block_type="txt-ni">Members of a culture use language to communicate their thoughts, beliefs, attitudes, and values with one another, and thereby reinforce their collective sense of cultural identity (Whorf, 1952). Consequently, the language you speak (English, Spanish, Mandarin, Urdu), the words you choose (proper, slang, profane), and the grammar you use (formal, informal) all announce to others: &#8220;This is who I am! This is my cultural heritage!&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p31" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Each language reflects distinct sets of cultural beliefs and values. However, a large group of people within a particular culture who speak the same language may (over time) develop their own variations on that language, known as <termref term="dialects">dialects</termref> (Gleason, 1989). Dialects may include unique phrases, words, and pronunciations (such as accents). Dialects reflect the shared history, experiences, and knowledge of people who live in a particular geographic region (the American Midwest or the Deep South), share a common socioeconomic status (urban working class or upper-middle-class suburban), or possess a common ethnic or religious ancestry (Irish English or Yiddish English) (Chen &#38; Starosta, 1998).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_119" block_type="page_start">119</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p32" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">People often judge those who use dialects similar to their own as ingroupers and are thus inclined to make positive judgments about them (Delia, 1972; Lev-Ari &#38; Keysar, 2010). As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link> discusses, this is a cultural influence; ingroupers are people you perceive to be culturally similar to you. In a parallel fashion, people tend to judge those with dissimilar dialects as outgroupers (people who are culturally dissimilar to you) and make negative judgments about them. Keep this tendency in mind when you&#8217;re speaking with people who don&#8217;t share your dialect, and resist the temptation to make negative judgments about them. For additional ideas on managing ingroup or outgroup perceptions, see <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link>.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-2" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="119">
<section-metadata><section-title>Verbal Communication Skills</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p33" block_type="pul"><strong>Even though people use language all the time to verbally communicate, not everyone does so skillfully. Knowing the difference between words that are understandable, inclusive, and respectful, and those that aren&#8217;t&#8212;and putting this knowledge to use when speaking with others&#8212;is essential to competent verbal communication.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p34" block_type="txt-ni">While attending his nephew&#8217;s graduation ceremony at the University of Washington, Steve expected to hear a formulaic keynote address extolling &#8220;the importance of being successful&#8221; and &#8220;having a competitive edge.&#8221; But William Gates Sr.&#8212;father of Microsoft billionaire Bill Gates and cochair of the Bill &#38; Melinda Gates Foundation&#8212;didn&#8217;t give the usual graduation speech. Instead, he said, &#8220;My favorite axiom is this: &#8216;We are all in this together.&#8217;&#8221; He talked about how important family and friendships are for life happiness. Then he broadened his discussion to global citizenship: &#8220;Citizenship means that we behave according to the belief that every person matters just as much as every other person.&#8221; As Gates spoke, the crowd quieted. Students and parents alike stopped texting and chatting and began listening. At the climax of his speech, Gates declared:</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx5-1" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p35" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>William Gates Sr.&#8217;s commencement speech shows how powerful language can impact an audience. Have you ever been similarly affected by a speech? Why?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-5" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-7" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P04.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Courtesy of the University of Washington</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_120" block_type="page_start">120</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p36" block_type="bm-ext">People suffering in poverty are human beings. They are not national security assets. They are not markets for our exports. . . . They are human beings who have infinite worth in their own right without any reference to us. They have mothers who love them, children who need them, and friends who cherish them, and we simply ought to help them.<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p37"><sup>2</sup></link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p37" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p36"><sup>2</sup></link>Speech excerpt from Bill &#38; Melinda Gates Foundation (2010).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p38" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">When he finished, 43,000 students and family members rose to give a standing ovation. Immediately after, people in the stadium began texting and chatting again. But this time, their messages and comments were uniform: &#8220;That was an amazing speech!&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p39" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Undoubtedly, the profound nature of Gates&#8217;s topic helped make his speech memorable. But a person can talk about important things in vague, wordy, or distorted ways that make listeners tune out. In Gates&#8217;s case, it was his <em>choice of words</em> that created the biggest impact: understandable, honest, and inclusive language that crossed gender and cultural boundaries. Gates made an audience of thousands feel as though they were joined together in something bigger and better than simply sitting in a stadium, listening to a speech.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p40" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">How can you harness the power of language in similar ways when you communicate verbally? Try four things: (1) create understandable messages; (2) use &#8220;I&#8221; and &#8220;we&#8221; language; (3) avoid gender-based presumptions; and (4) be mindful of cultural differences.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-5" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="120">
<section-metadata><section-title>Create Understandable Messages</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p41" block_type="txt-ni">As noted in our chapter opener, performance poets like Ed Mabrey or Kait Rokowski can&#8217;t win poetry slams just by crafting small, elegant poems. Instead, they must verbally communicate their creations in an understandable fashion to audiences. But what makes messages <em>understandable</em>? In his exploration of language and meaning, philosopher Paul Grice noted that in order for people to optimally understand your communication, you should strive to abide by the <termref term="cooperative principle">cooperative principle</termref>: making your verbal communication as <em>informative</em>, <em>honest</em>, <em>relevant</em>, and <em>clear</em> as required for a particular situation (Grice, 1989).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p42" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Be Informative.</strong></phrase> Being <em>informative</em> means presenting all the information that is appropriate and important to share. It also means not providing information that isn&#8217;t appropriate or important. For example, suppose your sister is getting married and you are in the wedding party. When you make a toast at the reception following the ceremony, everyone will expect you to comment on how the couple met and how their love for each other is inspiring. To <em>not</em> say these things would be remiss. On the other hand, you won&#8217;t want to be <em>too</em> informative by sharing inappropriate details (such as stories about their sex life) or unimportant details (such as what was on the menu at the restaurant where they first met).</p>
<box title="UNDERSTANDABLE MESSAGES" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx1-1" block_type="bx1-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p43" block_type="ph-cap"><strong>Shows like <em>Girls</em>, <em>Empire</em>, and <em>Crazy Ex-Girlfriend</em> feature characters who constantly struggle with creating understandable messages, whether talking to friends, lovers, or coworkers. How do such messages impact not only the communication in the moment but also the relationships of the people involved?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-6" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-8" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P05.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Jessica Miglio/&#169; HBO/Courtesy: Everett Collection</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-7" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-9" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P06.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Fox Network/Photofest</asset_source>
</figure>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-8" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-10" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P07.jpg"/>
<asset_source>Tyler Golden/&#169; The CW Network/courtesy Everett Collection</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_121" block_type="page_start">121</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p44" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Be Honest</strong>.</phrase> <termref term="Honesty">Honesty</termref> is the single most important characteristic of competent communication because other people count on the fact that the information you share with them is truthful (Grice, 1989). Being honest means not sharing information you&#8217;re uncertain about and not presenting information as true when you know it&#8217;s false. For example, let&#8217;s say that during a meeting, someone asks you a question you&#8217;re unable to answer. Rather than fumbling through a potentially incorrect response, acknowledge that you don&#8217;t know the answer, and determine a way to get the required information. Dishonesty in verbal communication violates standards for ethical behavior and leads others to believe false things (Jacobs, Dawson, &#38; Brashers, 1996).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p45" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Be Relevant.</strong></phrase> You are <em>relevant</em> when you present information that&#8217;s responsive to what others have said and applicable to the situation. As examples of responsiveness, when people ask you questions, you provide appropriate answers. When they make requests, you explicitly grant or reject those requests. Dodging questions or abruptly changing topics is uncooperative and may be seen as deceptive. In the wedding toast scenario, a relevant speech would cover the couple&#8217;s relationship. Going off on tangents regarding your own relationships would be irrelevant (&#8220;Seeing them together reminds me of my own love life; just last week I . . .&#8221;).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_122" block_type="page_start">122</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p46" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Be Clear.</strong></phrase>Using <em>clear language</em> means presenting information in a straightforward fashion rather than framing it in vague or ambiguous terms. This was one of the most impressive aspects of Gates Sr.&#8217;s commencement speech: he used clear, concise language that everyone easily understood: &#8220;People suffering in poverty . . . have mothers who love them.&#8221; (Check out <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch15.xml">Chapter 15</link> for suggestions on how to use clear language in your own speeches.)</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p47" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">At the same time, using clear language doesn&#8217;t mean being brutally frank or dumping offensive or harmful information on others. When you find yourself in situations in which you have to deliver bad news (&#8220;Your project report needs serious revision&#8221;), tailor your message in ways that consider others&#8217; feelings (&#8220;I&#8217;m sorry for the inconvenience this may cause you&#8221;). Similarly, you&#8217;ll improve the likelihood of positive outcomes during conflicts by expressing your concerns clearly (&#8220;I&#8217;m really upset&#8221;) while avoiding language that attacks someone&#8217;s character or personality (&#8220;You&#8217;re such an idiot&#8221;) (Gottman &#38; Silver, 1999).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p48" block_type="h3"><phrase block_type="h31"><strong>Misunderstandings.</strong></phrase> Of course, just because you use informative, honest, relevant, and clear language doesn&#8217;t guarantee that others will understand you. When one person misperceives the meaning of another&#8217;s verbal communication, <termref term="misunderstanding">misunderstanding</termref> occurs.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p49" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Misunderstanding occurs frequently online, owing to the lack of nonverbal cues that help clarify intended meaning. One study found that 27.2 percent of respondents agreed that e-mail is likely to result in miscommunication of intent, and 53.6 percent agreed that it is relatively easy to misinterpret an e-mail message (Rainey, 2000). The tendency to misunderstand communication online is so prevalent that scholars suggest the following practices: <em>If a particular message must be absolutely error-free or if its content is controversial, don&#8217;t use e-mail or text messaging to communicate it</em>. Whenever possible, conduct high-stakes encounters, such as important attempts at persuasion, face-to-face. Never use e-mails, posts, or texts for sensitive actions, such as professional reprimands or dismissals, or relationship breakups (Rainey, 2000). To learn how to create understandable messages and avoid misunderstandings during conflicts, see <link href="#choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx7-1">How to Communicate: Disagreement with Family</link> on pages 124&#8211;125.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx5-2" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p50" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong>Mediated communication platforms like FaceTime and Skype help eliminate the possibility of misunderstanding someone when you&#8217;re not able to talk in person. How does the language you use when interacting via webcam differ from the language you use when texting?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-9" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="right" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-11" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P08.jpg"/>
<asset_source>David Malan/Getty Images</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-6" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="122">
<section-metadata><section-title>Use &#8220;I&#8221; and &#8220;We&#8221; Language</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p51" block_type="txt-ni">When verbally communicating, avoid using <termref term="&#8220;you&#8221; language">&#8220;you&#8221; language</termref>&#8212;phrases that place the focus of attention and blame on other people, such as &#8220;You let me down&#8221; or &#8220;You make me so angry!&#8221; Instead, use <termref term="&#8220;I&#8221; language">&#8220;I&#8221; language</termref>&#8212;phrases that emphasize ownership of your feelings, opinions, and beliefs. &#8220;I&#8221; language makes it clear that you&#8217;re expressing your own perceptions rather than stating unquestionable truths, making it less likely to trigger defensiveness in others (Kubany, Richard, Bauer, &#38; Muraoka, 1992). For instance, imagine you&#8217;re involved in a group project, and some group members are working harder than others. If you bring up this topic with the group, saying &#8220;I think it&#8217;s important that the workload be evenly distributed&#8221; will seem less threatening than &#8220;You people aren&#8217;t doing your fair share!&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_123" block_type="page_start">123</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p52" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">At the same time, strive to build solidarity through <termref term="&#8220;we&#8221; language">&#8220;we&#8221; language</termref>&#8212;phrases that both emphasize inclusion and enhance feelings of connection and similarity (Honeycutt, 1999). In the group project example, you might say &#8220;We all want this project to be a success&#8221; in order to emphasize how the whole group is working together. One study found that married couples who used &#8220;we&#8221; language maintained more positive emotions during disagreements and had higher overall marital satisfaction than couples who did not (Seider, Hirschberger, Nelson, &#38; Levenson, 2009). To compare and contrast the differences between &#8220;you,&#8221; &#8220;I,&#8221; and &#8220;we&#8221; language, see <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-tab-2">Table 5.1</link>.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx6-1" block_type="bx6">
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-tab-2" block_type="table" caption-placement="top">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tab-label">TABLE 5.1</phrase></strong> <strong>&#8220;YOU,&#8221; &#8220;I,&#8221; AND &#8220;WE&#8221; LANGUAGE</strong></table_caption>
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-11a" alt="image" src="images/man.jpg"/></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-11b" alt="image" src="images/woman.jpg"/></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-11c" alt="image" src="images/both.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>SITUATION</strong></td>
<td><strong>&#8220;YOU&#8221; LANGUAGE</strong></td>
<td><strong>&#8220;I&#8221; LANGUAGE</strong></td>
<td><strong>&#8220;WE&#8221; LANGUAGE</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A friend blows up at you when you cancel dinner plans.</td>
<td>&#8220;You really hurt my feelings.&#8221;</td>
<td>&#8220;I&#8217;m feeling really hurt.&#8221;</td>
<td>&#8220;We need to work harder on not hurting each other&#8217;s feelings.&#8221;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A classmate forgets to make a main point during a group presentation.</td>
<td>&#8220;You totally messed up our presentation.&#8221;</td>
<td>&#8220;I feel like our presentation had some mistakes.&#8221;</td>
<td>&#8220;Although we made some mistakes in our presentation, we totally rocked the paper.&#8221;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>A coworker isn&#8217;t filling out order sheets correctly.</td>
<td>&#8220;You need to do a better job on your order sheets.&#8221;</td>
<td>&#8220;I think the order sheets could be done a bit better.&#8221;</td>
<td>&#8220;We can improve the quality of our order sheets with better inventory management.&#8221;</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p53" block_type="pho-src">VoodooDot/Shutterstock</p>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-7" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="123">
<section-metadata><section-title>Avoid Gender-Based Presumptions</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p54" block_type="txt-ni">Many people believe that men and women have different verbal communication preferences and practices. Specifically, they assume that women use and prefer &#8220;indirect&#8221; and &#8220;flowery&#8221; language, whereas men use and prefer &#8220;direct, clear, and concise&#8221; language (Spender, 1990). But scientific research has found that men and women are actually more similar than different when it comes to language. For example, after reviewing data from more than 1,000 gender studies, researchers Dan Canary, Tara Emmers-Sommer, and Sandra Faulkner (1997) found that if you consider all the factors that influence communication and compare their impact, only about 1 percent of people&#8217;s verbal communication behavior is related to gender. The researchers concluded that during verbal communication, &#8220;men and women respond in a similar manner 99&#37; of the time.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_124" block_type="page_start">124</p>
<box title="HOW TO COMMUNICATE &#124; Video Skills" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx7-1" block_type="bx7-t">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p55" block_type="bx7-h"><strong>DISAGREEMENT WITH FAMILY</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p56" block_type="bx7-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-12" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> One way to improve your communication competence is by adapting your messages to others&#8217; behaviors. Learn how to navigate a disagreement with a family member by going to LaunchPad at <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong> and completing the <strong>How to Communicate video scenario</strong> for <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml">Chapter 5</link> to practice your skills.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p57" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>CONSIDER THIS:</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p58" block_type="bx7-txt">Your mom decides that a great way for your family to reconnect is to take a two-week road trip next summer, driving across the country to see your grandparents. She sends you and your siblings an e-mail, highlighting the sights you&#8217;ll see and how much &#8220;fun&#8221; it will be. Everyone is excited&#8212;except you. Although you get along well with your family, the idea of being trapped in a car with them for half a month sounds like a nightmare! What&#8217;s more, you&#8217;d planned on working full-time over the summer to earn money for school.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p59" block_type="bx7-txt"><strong>WHAT WOULD YOU DO?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p60" block_type="bx7-txt">The following advice illustrates how to use your verbal communication skills when handling sensitive topics. As you watch the video, consider how the dialogue reflects the cooperative principle and properly uses &#8220;I&#8221; and &#8220;we&#8221; language. Then, test your knowledge of key skills, and create your own responses to the <strong>What if? video prompts</strong>.</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-10" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-13" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_05_HTC-1.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;I&#8217;d like to talk with you about our plans for next summer. When would be a good time for me to call? Or can we talk at home this weekend? I&#8217;ll be there on Saturday morning.&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-exp3-1" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p62" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-14" alt="image" src="images/1.jpg"/> <strong>SCHEDULE AN OFFLINE ENCOUNTER</strong> with your mom by sending her an e-mail or text, asking when she can talk with you on the phone or meet with you in person.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_125" block_type="page_start">125</p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-11" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-15" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_05_HTC-2.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;I know how excited everyone is about the trip, especially you. But I just can&#8217;t take two weeks off from work. I need those hours to afford school next year. I hope you can understand my situation and that I&#8217;m not disappointing you too much with my decision.&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-exp3-2" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p64" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-16" alt="image" src="images/2.jpg"/> <strong>EXPRESS YOUR OPINION</strong> informatively and honestly, being careful to use &#8220;I&#8221; language to take accountability for your feelings.</p>
</box>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-12" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-17" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_05_HTC-2a.jpg"/>
<caption><strong>&#8220;Why don&#8217;t we invite Grandma and Grandpa to fly out and join us for the Fourth of July? I have that weekend off, so we can all be together and reconnect as a family.&#8221;</strong></caption>
</figure>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-exp3-3" block_type="mn3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p66" block_type="mn-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-18" alt="image" src="images/3.jpg"/> <strong>USE &#8220;WE&#8221; LANGUAGE</strong> to emphasize family inclusion, offering alternatives for a family get-together.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p67" block_type="bx7-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-19" alt="image" src="images/arrow.jpg"/> <strong>WHAT IF? But what if things don&#8217;t work out as shown? Test your ability to adapt your communication by watching the What if? videos and planning a response for each situation.</strong></p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-2" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p68" block_type="bl-first">What would you say when your mom doesn&#8217;t want to talk in person and writes back, &#8220;I&#8217;m really busy with work right now&#8212;let&#8217;s just chat over e-mail&#8221;?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p69" block_type="bx7-last">How would you handle your mom&#8217;s anger at your reluctance to go? &#8220;This may come as a shock to you, but the whole world doesn&#8217;t revolve around you and your work schedule! You need to make a decision about what&#8217;s more important: your work or your family.&#8221;</p></li>
</list>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_126" block_type="page_start">126</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p70" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">So why do people think that men and women use language differently? Perception. Because people <em>believe</em> that men and women are different, they <em>perceive</em> differences in their communication&#8212;even when such differences don&#8217;t exist. In a well-known study documenting this effect, researchers gave two different groups of participants a copy of the same speech (Mulac, Incontro, &#38; James, 1985). One group was told that a man had authored and presented the speech; the other group, that a woman had authored and presented it. Participants who thought the speech was female in origin perceived it as having a more &#8220;artistic quality&#8221; and complimented the language for being &#8220;pleasing, sweet, and beautiful.&#8221; Participants who were told that a man had authored the speech viewed it as having more &#8220;dynamism&#8221; and complimented the language as &#8220;strong, active, and aggressive.&#8221; Yet both groups read the same speech.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p71" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">The lesson? You don&#8217;t need to adjust your verbal communication to your listeners&#8217; or readers&#8217; gender. Men and women appreciate language that is informative, honest, relevant, and clear. Everyone prefers talking with people who avoid placing blame through &#8220;you&#8221; language and who use &#8220;I&#8221; language to take responsibility for their own actions and feelings. Additionally, using &#8220;we&#8221; language creates a sense of unity with others, regardless of their gender.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-8" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="126">
<section-metadata><section-title>Be Mindful of Cultural Differences</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p72" block_type="txt-ni">As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link> discusses, different cultures often have different ideas about what constitutes competent verbal communication. To help you communicate competently with people from other cultures, consider the following guidelines.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p73" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">First, think about whether the people you are communicating with are from a high- or low-context culture. As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link> notes, in <em>high-context cultures</em> (China, Korea, Japan), people presume that listeners share extensive knowledge in common with them. As a result, they don&#8217;t feel a need to provide a lot of specific details in their messages. In <em>low-context cultures</em> (Germany, Scandinavia, the United States), people tend not to presume that listeners share their beliefs, attitudes, and values, so they tailor their verbal communication to be informative, clear, and direct (E. T. Hall &#38; Hall, 1987).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p74" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Consider what this cultural difference means for expressing constructive criticism. If you told a classmate from a high-context culture, &#8220;I thought your presentation had several problems,&#8221; he or she would likely perceive your comment as intolerably direct and rude. A more comfortable comment for this classmate might be, &#8220;What issues do you think arose in your speech?&#8221; But if you asked a classmate from a low-context culture this question, he or she might interpret it as cryptic. To avoid such confusion, try to tailor the directness of your language to your listeners&#8217; cultural preferences.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_127" block_type="page_start">127</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p75" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Second, adjust your verbal communication to match others&#8217; speech rates and desired balance of &#8220;turn taking&#8221; (Bianconi, 2002; Coupland, Giles, &#38; Wiemann, 1991). Observe how rapidly the person you&#8217;re talking with speaks, and how long a turn he or she takes when talking. Then match the person&#8217;s speech rate, and use similar turn lengths. Monitor any feedback while you&#8217;re conversing (such as nodding or fidgeting) to see whether your conversation partner wants you to continue or stop. (For more details on accommodating, see pp. 110&#8211;111 in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link>.)</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p76" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Third, and most important, don&#8217;t change your language or voice in substantial ways just because you&#8217;re speaking to someone from another culture. For example, many Euro-American college students switch to simplistic language and talk slower and louder when interacting with Asian and Asian American students, as if they were talking with small children. This change in speech behavior is viewed as both patronizing and insulting by recipients (Jimenez &#38; McCornack, 2011).</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-3" block_type="h1" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="true" level="1" print_page="127">
<section-metadata><section-title>Verbal Communication Challenges</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p77" block_type="pul"><strong>&#8220;Sticks and stones may break my bones, but words can never hurt me.&#8221; Nonsense. The words you choose have the power to cause grievous injury to the emotions and self-esteem of others. But by learning to identify and avoid destructive forms of language&#8212;and constructively respond when others use them&#8212;you can become a more competent verbal communicator.</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p78" block_type="txt-ni">He is the most prejudiced, verbally aggressive, deceptive, and slanderous character ever to show up on television screens. He has been described as &#8220;a bundle of pure, unadulterated evil.&#8221; He&#8217;s <em>South Park</em>&#8217;s Eric Cartman&#8212;a boy plagued by greed, hatred, and an unquenchable thirst for power. Through hundreds of episodes, Cartman has tried to reignite the Civil War, feigned disability, tricked another boy into eating his own parents at a chili cook-off, and released an almost endless anti-Semitic verbal assault on his classmate Kyle.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p79" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Cartman&#8217;s terrible communication choices often have disastrous outcomes. His manipulation of and cruelty to others only occasionally nets him happiness, and he never learns from his mistakes. This makes him endearing in a strange way: his communicative failings make viewers feel good about their capacity to change and improve. So whether you love Cartman or loathe him, laugh at his offensive antics or recoil from them, he reveals an essential truth about the dark side of verbal communication: when you use prejudiced, aggressive, deceptive, or defamatory language, you sow the seeds of your own destruction.</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-9" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="127">
<section-metadata><section-title>Prejudiced Language</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p80" block_type="txt-ni">As <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch04.xml">Chapter 4</link> discusses, <em>prejudice</em> means presuming negative things about other people based on their group affiliation (ethnicity, religion, age, gender, sexual orientation). It is a negative form of <em>stereotyping</em>. People who use <termref term="prejudiced language">prejudiced language</termref> speak in ways that display contempt, dislike, or disdain for a group or its members. In <em>South Park</em>, for example, Cartman uses prejudiced language almost constantly when he talks with his Jewish friend Kyle and when he sees hippies&#8212;anyone with long hair and tie-dyed clothing.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_128" block_type="page_start">128</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx5-3" block_type="bx5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p81" block_type="bx-v3-txt"><strong><em>South Park</em>&#8217;s Eric Cartman is the cartoon definition of how <em>not</em> to communicate. His unabashed bad behavior is shocking but also shows viewers the consequences of poor communication skills. How do you handle any real-life &#8220;Cartmans&#8221; you run into?</strong></p>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-13" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-20" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31904_05_P09.jpg"/>
<asset_source>&#169; Comedy Central/Courtesy: Everett Collection</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p82" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">There are as many types of prejudiced language as there are groups. A person can use language that&#8217;s prejudiced toward men or women (<em>sexist language</em>) or toward gays, lesbians, bisexuals, or transgender persons (<em>homophobic language</em>). It can also be used to criticize various ethnicities (<em>racist language</em>), people of different ages (<em>ageist language</em>), and even socioeconomic groups (<em>classist language</em>). Some people use prejudiced language when discussing physical or mental disabilities, political affiliations, social or religious groups, and even college majors.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p83" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Most of us readily recognize racist, sexist, and disability-related slurs. But prejudiced language can be less obvious&#8212;for example, when people use ethnic and gender-specific modifiers to describe others, even when such descriptors are unnecessary to the point they&#8217;re making (&#8220;the Hispanic doctor&#8221; or &#8220;a male nurse&#8221;). Subtle prejudiced language also shows up in the use of such expressions as &#8220;That&#8217;s so gay,&#8221; to mean that something isn&#8217;t cool or acceptable. Such expressions are hurtful and perpetuate negative stereotypes.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p84" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">What can you do if another person&#8217;s language is prejudiced and offensive? As we discuss in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch08.xml">Chapter 8</link> about managing conflict, confronting others is rarely easy, but it can be done. Consider the following suggestions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-3" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p85" block_type="bl-f">Determine the risk of confrontation. Is the person likely to be open to your point of view? A friend, family member, or peer may be willing to listen. However, if it&#8217;s a stranger or someone with power over you (like your boss), it might be best to ignore the comments or to leave the situation.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p86" block_type="bl-m">If you choose to confront the person, avoid an approach that causes the person to lose face, creating embarrassment. Instead, talk with the person privately, and open with an affirming statement (&#8220;I know that you probably mean no harm when you say, &#8216;That&#8217;s so gay&#8217;&#8221;).</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p87" block_type="bl-m">Next, state your feelings about the prejudiced language, and politely ask the person to revise his or her language (&#8220;I feel uncomfortable with this phrase because I have a brother who&#8217;s gay; I would appreciate it if you didn&#8217;t use it&#8221;).</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p88" block_type="bl-m">Finally, listen to and acknowledge what the person says in response. If necessary, reassert your request that the prejudiced language be avoided (&#8220;I understand that you mean nothing by it, but I would still appreciate it if you didn&#8217;t use it&#8221;).</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_129" block_type="page_start">129</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-10" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="129">
<section-metadata><section-title>Verbal Aggression</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p89" block_type="txt-ni"><termref term="Verbal aggression">Verbal aggression</termref> is the use of language to attack someone&#8217;s personal attributes, such as their weight, looks, intelligence, or physical ability (Infante &#38; Wigley, 1986). Verbal aggression is distinct from prejudiced language in three respects: the goal is to intentionally injure a particular person&#8217;s feelings, the attack targets unique personal attributes rather than group affiliation, and the message often includes profanity.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p90" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Verbal aggression can take the form of <termref term="cyberbullying">cyberbullying</termref>: habitually attacking a person using the Internet, interactive and digital technologies, or mobile phones.<link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p91"><sup>3</sup></link> Individuals engage in cyberbullying by sending numerous insulting text messages, such as &#8220;u r so fat and ugly!&#8221; or writing Facebook posts or tweets denouncing someone as a &#8220;whore&#8221; or &#8220;loser.&#8221; The impact of cyberbullying can be devastating. Such was the case with Phoebe Prince&#8212;a high school student in Massachusetts&#8212;who killed herself following repeated acts of verbal aggression by her fellow female students via text messages, Facebook posts, and face-to-face encounters. Sadly, hundreds of similarly cyberbullied children attempt suicide every year.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p91" block_type="co-fn"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p90"><sup>3</sup></link>Adapted from <link href="http://www.www.stopcyberbullying.org">www.stopcyberbullying.org</link> (2010).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p92" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">Why are people verbally aggressive? Sometimes the behavior is triggered by a temporary state of stress, anger, or exhaustion. Other times it&#8217;s in reaction to real or perceived slights. In the Phoebe Prince case, the girls attacked her because they felt Phoebe had &#8220;crossed a line&#8221; by befriending and dating their boyfriends (Bazelon, 2010). Still others act that way because they believe that using profanity, insults, and threats will get them what they want, like Cartman from <em>South Park.</em></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p93" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">It&#8217;s hard to communicate competently with verbally aggressive people. Imagine giving a speech in a public forum, such as a student union meeting, and having someone stand up and yell, &#8220;Shut up, you loser!&#8221; What would you say and do? To manage verbally aggressive individuals, researcher Dominic Infante (1995) offers three suggestions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-4" type="unordered" block_type="bluebullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p94" block_type="bl-f">Avoid communicating in ways that may trigger aggression in the first place, such as teasing, baiting, or insulting others.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p95" block_type="bl-m">If you know someone who is <em>chronically verbally aggressive</em>&#8212;meaning he or she is verbally aggressive most of the time&#8212;avoid or minimize contact with that person.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p96" block_type="bl-m">If you can&#8217;t avoid such interactions, try to remain polite and respectful. Don&#8217;t interrupt the aggressive person. Stay calm, and acknowledge the other person&#8217;s perspective if possible. Avoid retaliating with personal attacks of your own; they&#8217;ll only escalate the aggression.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p97" block_type="txt-ni">For ideas on how to handle verbal aggression online, see <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p98">Table 5.2</link>.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx6-2" block_type="bx6">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p98" block_type="txt-ni">TABLE 5.2</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p99" block_type="txt-ni"><strong>HOW TO HANDLE VERBAL AGGRESSION ONLINE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p100" block_type="txt-ni"><strong>If you receive a text, e-mail, or online post that is aggressive or hostile toward you, try the following steps to respond competently and not escalate the situation:</strong></p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-5" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p101">Consider the intent of the message carefully to help you determine whether you should respond. Is the sender intentionally trying to provoke you? Did the sender just get carried away with emotion? Is the sender aware of the tone of the message?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p102">If you choose to respond, create a draft message first, save it, and then revisit it in a few hours. Do not send the message yet.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p103">Later, check your response. Is it informative, honest, relevant, and clear?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p104">Did you avoid &#8220;you&#8221; language and use &#8220;I&#8221; and &#8220;we&#8221; language where appropriate to minimize defensiveness and bridge your differences?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p105">Make sure your message is respectful and polite, avoiding any hint of personal attack or retaliation.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p106">Only once you are sure the message fits these requirements should you send it.</p></li>
</list>
<figure id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-fig-14" block_type="un_figure" numbered="false" mmtype="image" mmsrc="" attr="">
<layout align="center" width="large" border="true"/>
<image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-21" alt="image" src="images/MCC_31238_05_T02.jpg"/>
<asset_source>VLADGRIN/Shutterstock; Max Griboedov/Shutterstock</asset_source>
</figure>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_130" block_type="page_start">130</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-11" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="130">
<section-metadata><section-title>Deception</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p107" block_type="txt-ni"><termref term="Deception">Deception</termref> is the deliberate use of uninformative, untruthful, irrelevant, or vague language for the purpose of misleading others. Deception takes many forms. People may be overly vague in what they say, trying to &#8220;veil&#8221; the truth. They may dodge a question or change the topic to avoid embarrassing or problematic disclosures. The most common form of deception is <em>concealment</em>: leaving important and relevant information out of messages (McCornack, 2008). <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-tab-3">Table 5.3</link> explains other types of deception, including avoidance, lying, and being vague.</p>
<box title="" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx6-3" block_type="bx6">
<table id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-tab-3" block_type="table" caption-placement="top">
<table_caption><strong><phrase block_type="tab-label">TABLE 5.3</phrase></strong> <strong>TYPES OF DECEPTION</strong></table_caption>
<layout align="center" width="large"/>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-21a" alt="image" src="images/avoidance.jpg"/></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-21b" alt="image" src="images/concealment.jpg"/></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-21c" alt="image" src="images/lying.jpg"/></td>
<td><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-21d" alt="image" src="images/vague.jpg"/></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Changing the topic to avoid revealing troublesome information</strong></td>
<td><strong>Responding with partial truth&#8212;but leaving out important information</strong></td>
<td><strong>Presenting a message that is entirely false</strong></td>
<td><strong>Answering questions with ambiguous language, designed to hide the truth</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Example:</strong> A coworker asks if you&#8217;ve heard anything about layoffs, and you shift the topic to sports (&#8220;Speaking of layoffs, did you hear about the baseball strike?&#8221;) to avoid telling him that he&#8217;s going to be fired.</td>
<td><strong>Example:</strong> Your dentist asks if you&#8217;ve been flossing and you say, &#8220;Yes, I have&#8221;&#8212;but you conceal the fact that you&#8217;ve only flossed twice in the last month.</td>
<td><strong>Example:</strong> You give an informative speech telling your class about &#8220;your summer working on a ranch,&#8221; but the whole story is made up, based on a post you saw on Reddit.</td>
<td><strong>Example:</strong> Your friend asks your opinion about a new dress that she obviously loves, and you say, &#8220;It&#8217;s so unique!&#8221; to hide the fact that you think it looks horrible on her.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p108" block_type="bx6-sc">Adrian Niederhaeuser/Shutterstock</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_131" block_type="page_start">131</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p109" block_type="txt-ni">Deception is especially commonplace online. People can easily hide and distort information in chat or e-mail messages, and recipients of messages have little opportunity to check accuracy. Some people provide false information about their backgrounds, professions, appearances, and gender online to amuse themselves, to form relationships unavailable to them offline, or to take advantage of others through online scams (Rainey, 2000). However, most people provide accurate information on social networking sites like Tumblr or Instagram because close friends will hold them accountable for what they post (Back et al., 2010).</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p110" block_type="txt-ni">Whether it&#8217;s face-to-face or online, deception is unethical, impractical, and destructive. It exploits the message recipients&#8217; belief that speakers are communicating cooperatively by tricking them into thinking that the messages are informative, honest, relevant, and clear (McCornack, 2008). Deception is unethical because it denies others information they may need to make personal or professional decisions, and it demonstrates disrespect (LaFollette &#38; Graham, 1986). Deception is impractical because a lie typically leads to more lies (McCornack, 2008). Even something as simple as telling a friend that you like his new jacket when you don&#8217;t can get you into trouble. From then on, when you&#8217;re with your friend, you would have to remember to always praise the jacket rather than criticize it. Otherwise, he will discover your lie. Finally, deception is destructive; when discovered, it has unpleasant personal and professional consequences (McCornack &#38; Levine, 1990), such as conflicts among friends or romantic partners, loss of trust from an audience, or even dismissal from a job.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_132" block_type="page_start">132</p>
<box title="MAKING COMMUNICATION CHOICES" numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-bx2-1" block_type="bx2-v2-h">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p111" block_type="bx-v2-txt"><strong>PROTECTING A FRIEND FROM HARM</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p112" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>1</strong></phrase> <strong>CONSIDER THE DILEMMA</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p113" block_type="bx-v1-txt-nia">Kevin is your best friend on campus. He is funny, athletic, and hardworking. He&#8217;s also painfully shy; it&#8217;s often difficult for him to meet new people.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p114" block_type="bx2-txt">It&#8217;s a Friday night, and you and Kevin decide to head to a nightclub to celebrate the end of a tough week. You both take turns as the designated driver, and tonight is your turn to drive. Shortly after arriving at the club, Kevin orders a couple of drinks and approaches a woman and asks her to dance. You are excited that he took the initiative to meet someone new, but you figure he&#8217;ll be back after one or two songs. After a half hour passes, however, you see he is still with her. You signal to him, and when he walks over, he says, &#8220;She is <em>so</em> hot!&#8221; You, however, have a different impression. &#8220;Do you know her?&#8221; you ask, &#8220;because she doesn&#8217;t seem your type.&#8221; Kevin laughs and says, &#8220;I&#8217;ve had classes with her before&#8212;she&#8217;s fine. Her name is Aliana.&#8221;</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p115" block_type="bx2-txt">As the hours slide by, it&#8217;s clear that as Kevin continues to drink, he is acting far outside his normally reserved demeanor and is starting to embarrass himself in front of other people at the club. He is making a serious play for Aliana, and he&#8217;s feeding her drinks, one after the next, so now both of them are wasted. You decide to intervene, but when you tell Kevin it&#8217;s time to go, he says he&#8217;s going home with Aliana. When you tell him you don&#8217;t think that&#8217;s a good idea, Kevin snaps, &#8220;Don&#8217;t tell me what to do! You&#8217;re not my mother!&#8221; Worried about him, you&#8217;re uncertain about your next move.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p116" block_type="bx2-h1-c1"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>2</strong></phrase> <strong>CONNECT THE RESEARCH</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p117" block_type="bx-v1-txt-nia">Research suggests that more than one-third of college students drink heavily, and that such drinking contributes to a &#8220;hookup culture&#8221;&#8212;an environment in which students engage in risky sexual behavior with people with whom they have no relationship connection (Paul, McManus, &#38; Hayes, 2000). This creates dilemmas when people wish to protect their intoxicated friends from the negative outcomes associated with such behaviors.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p118" block_type="bx-v2-txta">Researchers Lisa Menegatos, Linda Lederman, and Aaron Hess (2010) looked at college students&#8217; verbal communication strategies for trying to stop drunken friends from hooking up with strangers. They found that college students in such situations commonly use one of three strategies to intervene:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-6" type="unordered" block_type="greenbullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p119" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b"><strong>Persuasion:</strong> They try to convince their friend not to go home with the other person, emphasizing the potential health and social consequences, such as the risks of pregnancy and sexually transmitted disease, and regrets that may be experienced in the morning.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p120" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b"><strong>Deception:</strong> They trick their friend into not leaving with the other person. For example, they might tell their friend that they&#8217;ll provide a ride to the hookup&#8217;s house but drive to a restaurant to get something to eat instead.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p121" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b"><strong>Confrontation:</strong> They verbally or physically discourage their friend from leaving with the other person by assertively telling the friend that it&#8217;s time to leave the club or even physically removing the friend from the club, if necessary. Alternatively, they might confront the person who is pursuing the hookup, telling him or her to leave their friend alone.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_133" block_type="page_start">133</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p122" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b"><phrase block_type="bm-txt-v1"><strong>3</strong></phrase> <strong>COMMUNICATE</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p123" block_type="bx-v1-txt-nia">Before making a communication choice, consider the facts of the situation, and think about what the research tells you about communicating with an intoxicated friend who is engaging in risky behavior. Also reflect on what you have learned about deception (pp. 131&#8211;133), verbal aggression (p. 129), and verbal communication skills (pp. 119&#8211;127). Then, answer these questions:</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-7" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p124" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">What ethical obligation do you have to stop Kevin? What other factors about the friendship and the situation should you consider when deciding what to do next?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p125" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">Of the three communication approaches researchers have identified for such a situation, which would you most likely try? What other approaches would you consider?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p126" block_type="bx-v2-nl-v0b">What would you say to Kevin next?</p></li>
</list>
</box>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec2-12" block_type="h2" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="2" print_page="133">
<section-metadata><section-title>Defamation</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-exp2-2" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p127" block_type="wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-22" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you review! Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p128" block_type="txt-ni"><termref term="Defamation">Defamation</termref> is intentionally false communication that harms a person&#8217;s reputation. In written form, defamation is called <em>libel</em>; in spoken form, it&#8217;s <em>slander</em>. Defamation isn&#8217;t just ineffective verbal communication; it can result in legal charges against the person who commits it. But whether such charges will stick depends largely on whether the target of the defamation is a public figure (politician, celebrity, famous athlete) or a private citizen. For public figures, the legal system counts criticism as &#8220;free speech.&#8221; To have defamation charges upheld, public figures must demonstrate that those who made the statements <em>acted with malice</em> and <em>knew that their claims were false.</em></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p129" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">In cases involving private citizens, such as gossip or online rumors, legal action is more likely. Private citizens don&#8217;t have the same access as public figures to media outlets that can counter defamatory statements; they also don&#8217;t open themselves up to criticism by being a public figure. Consequently, private citizens&#8217; rights to protect their reputations outweigh free-speech rights to criticize and defame.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p130" block_type="bm-txt-v1*">What does this mean in practical terms? When communicating with others&#8212;especially online (which is permanent) or in a speech (which is public)&#8212;don&#8217;t write or say anything that could harm a private citizen&#8217;s reputation. For example, blogging about a coworker engaging in sexual harassment, or giving a speech in which you denounce a local businessman as racist, may result in someone filing a lawsuit against you. Although you have free-speech rights to (fairly) criticize public figures, you do <em>not</em> have the right to publicly assail private citizens in ways that damage their reputations. When it comes to verbal communication, the old adage is true: if you don&#8217;t have something nice to say about someone, don&#8217;t say anything at all.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e_page_134" block_type="page_start">134</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-4" block_type="cr-h" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="134">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER 5 REVIEW</section-title></section-metadata>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-5" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="134">
<section-metadata><section-title>CHAPTER RECAP</section-title></section-metadata>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-8" type="unordered" block_type="bullet">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p131" block_type="cr-bl-v0"><termref term="Verbal communication">Verbal communication</termref> is the use of written or spoken language to interact with others. Language is symbolic, is governed by rules, conveys meaning, and is intertwined with culture.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p132" block_type="cr-bl-v0">You can increase your verbal communication skills by creating messages that adhere to the <termref term="cooperative principle">cooperative principle</termref> and by using <termref term="&#8220;I&#8221;">&#8220;I&#8221;</termref> and <termref term="&#8220;we&#8221; language">&#8220;we&#8221; language</termref>.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p133" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Although there are many common stereotypes about how men and women communicate, studies show that men&#8217;s and women&#8217;s verbal communication is more similar than different.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p134" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Consider how cultural factors like <em>high-</em> or <em>low-context</em> culture, preferred speech rates, or desired balance of turn taking can influence interactions, and try to adapt as best you can.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p135" block_type="cr-bl-v0">Avoiding verbal communication pitfalls such as <termref term="prejudiced language">prejudiced language</termref>, <strong>verbal aggression</strong>, <strong>cyberbullying</strong>, <strong>deception</strong>, and <termref term="defamation">defamation</termref>&#8212;and learning how to handle situations when others use them&#8212;will help you improve your communication competence.</p></li>
</list>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p136" block_type="cr-txt-ni"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-23" alt="image" src="images/launchpad.jpg"/> LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> offers unique video scenarios and encourages self-assessment through adaptive quizzing. Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong> to get access.</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p138" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-24" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> LearningCurve adaptive quizzes</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p139" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-25" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> How to Communicate video scenarios</p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p140" block_type="cr-ul"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-26" alt="image" src="images/arrow1.jpg"/> Video Clips that illustrate key concepts</p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-6" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="134">
<section-metadata><section-title>KEY TERMS</section-title></section-metadata>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p141" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p20">Verbal communication, p. 116</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p142" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p22">Symbols, p. 117</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p143" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p23">Constitutive rules, p. 117</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p144" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p24">Regulative rules, p. 117</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p145" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p25"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-27" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Denotative meanings, p. 117</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p146" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p26"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-28" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> Connotative meanings, p. 117</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p147" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p31">Dialects, p. 118</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p148" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p41">Cooperative principle, p. 120</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p149" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p44">Honesty, p. 121</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p150" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p48">Misunderstanding, p. 122</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p151" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p51"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-29" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> &#8220;You&#8221; language, p. 122</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p152" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p51"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-30" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> &#8220;I&#8221; language, p. 123</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p153" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p52"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-31" alt="image" src="images/arrow2.jpg"/> &#8220;We&#8221; language, p. 123</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p154" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p80">Prejudiced language, p. 128</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p155" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p89">Verbal aggression, p. 129</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p156" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p90">Cyberbullying, p. 129</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p157" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p101">Deception, p. 130</link></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p158" block_type="cr-ul"><link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-p122">Defamation, p. 133</link></p>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-7" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="135">
<section-metadata><section-title>POP QUIZ</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-exp2-3" block_type="mn2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p159" block_type="cr-wl-txt"><image asset-id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-img-32" alt="image" src="images/tick.jpg"/> Looking for more review questions? <strong>LearningCurve</strong> can help you master key concepts from this chapter. Go to <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-question-1" number="1">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p160" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">You and your sister using the phrase &#8220;blue moon&#8221; to signal to each other when your mom is in a bad mood is an example of &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-9" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p161" block_type="cr-ll-v1">regulative rules</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p162" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">constitutive rules</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p163" block_type="cr-ll-v1">connotative meanings</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p164" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">denotative meanings</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-question-2" number="2">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p165" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Which of the following is <em>not</em> one of the four characteristics of understandable language, according to the cooperative principle?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-10" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p166" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Honest</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p167" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Symbolic</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p168" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Clear</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p169" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Informative</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-question-3" number="3">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p170" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">Phrases that both emphasize inclusion and enhance feelings of connection and similarity are known as &#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;.</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-11" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p171" block_type="cr-ll-v1">&#8220;we&#8221; language</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p172" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">understandable messages</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p173" block_type="cr-ll-v1">&#8220;I&#8221; language</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p174" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">the cooperative principle</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-question-4" number="4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p175" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">According to researcher Dominic Infante, how can you competently communicate with verbally aggressive people?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-12" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p176" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Avoid teasing, baiting, or insulting others.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p177" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Minimize contact with people who are chronically verbally aggressive.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p178" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Remain polite and respectful, and don&#8217;t retaliate with your own attacks.</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p179" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">All of the answers are correct.</p></li>
</list>
</question>
<question id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-question-5" number="5">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p180" block_type="cr-x-que-mc">According to <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-tab-3">Table 5.3</link>, Types of Deception, which of the following types refers to revealing only part of the truth while leaving out important information?</p>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-13" type="ordered" block_type="loweralpha">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p181" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Vague</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p182" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Avoidance</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p183" block_type="cr-ll-v1">Lying</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p184" block_type="cr-x-que-mc-ans">Concealment</p></li>
</list>
</question>
</section>
<section id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-sec1-8" block_type="cr-h1" title="" chapter="ch5" numbered="false" level="1" print_page="135">
<section-metadata><section-title>ACTIVITIES</section-title></section-metadata>
<box numbered="false" id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-exp4-1" block_type="mn4">
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p185" block_type="cr-wl-txt">For more activities, visit LaunchPad for <em>Choices &#38; Connections</em> at <strong><link href="http://www.macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e">macmillanhighered.com/choicesconnections2e</link></strong>.</p>
</box>
<list id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-list-14" type="ordered" block_type="numbered">
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p186" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>What Went Wrong?</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p187" block_type="cr-txt">Think of a recent conflict or unpleasant encounter you&#8217;ve had. It can be with anyone: a professor, a friend, a roommate, a family member, a coworker. Write out exactly what you and the other person said, to the best of your recollection. If it was a text-based interaction, use the e-mails, texts, or tweets for reference. Now, look at the language that you and your partner used. How did specific things that each of you said contribute to the unpleasantness of the interaction? Revisit the coverage of the cooperative principle and &#8220;I&#8221; and &#8220;we&#8221; language on pages 120 &#8211;123. What could you have said differently to help the situation be more positive or to better explain your point of view?</p></li>
<li><p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p188" block_type="cr-nl"><strong>Just a Little White Lie</strong></p>
<p id="choicesconnections2e-ch5-p189" block_type="cr-txt">With a partner, discuss the definitions and differences between the types of deception outlined in <link href="choicesconnections2e-ch05.xml#choicesconnections2e-ch5-tab-3">Table 5.3</link>: avoidance, concealment, lying, and vague. Do you consider some of these types more deceptive than others? When, if ever, is it acceptable to use these forms of deception? Is it ever ethical to deceive? Provide examples and rationales for each.</p></li>
</list>
</section>
</chapter>
</manuscript>